[Music]
[Applause]
hello everyone hello it's been a very
strange
day so I'm going to tell you about what
happened and then I'll start the lecture
so I got up this morning and
uh started to put my together and then I
tried to sign into my Gmail
account and it said that it had been
disabled because I violated the terms of
service with
Gmail and I
thought well I didn't violate any terms
of service that I know of now I set up a
new YouTube channel yesterday called
Jordan B Peterson clips and so we made
some technical changes and so I thought
maybe it had something to do with with
that and I had been shout out of Google
one other time years ago so when you get
shut out like
that there's a little form you can fill
out and so I filled out the form and I
said that I had been shut out and uh
that I didn't know why and I sent it off
and then I realized one of my staff
members called me and said that she was
locked out of the YouTube account and I
thought oh yeah the YouTube account is
hooked to the Gmail account so that
meant that I couldn't get access to any
of my YouTube videos they were still up
and online but I couldn't get access to
them I couldn't post last week's
biblical lecture for for for example and
so that was worrisome and made me
suspicious and then about two hours
later something like that I got an email
from Google and they said that they had
reviewed the my request to be reinstated
and that I had violated Google's terms
of agreement or terms of service and
they weren't going to turn my account
back
on and I
thought and they didn't say why they
didn't say anything I got there was no
warning whatsoever about any of this
they didn't tell me why and they didn't
say why in the email response and so I
wrote them back and I said because they
said I could I wrote them back and I
said this might not be a good idea
basically
and you might want to think about it and
then I tweeted tweeted what had happened
right I took screenshots and I tweeted
and I contacted a whole bunch of
journalists because it turns out that I
know a whole bunch of journalists and
so and so then what happened then was
that um I got a call from The Daily
Caller in the United States I had done
an interview with them last week which
isn't posted yet and they interviewed me
and within 20 minutes posted it online
and so they have a fairly big audience
and so that was good and then somebody
phoned me from Ottawa and I did a live
radio show about that and that was good
and then a number of other journalists
contacted me and I sent them the
information but another one of my staff
actually my son emailed me and he said
look you should hold off because maybe
there's still a mistake here and I
thought yeah there might be it might be
just a mistake but then why in the world
did I email Google and they contacted
and they said they would not reinstate
it and they didn't provide me with any
information so I contacted the other
journalists and I said well you never
know maybe this is just a mistake so
let's hold off and then while I was
about half an hour later while I was
trying to get into my I use this AdWords
account that's linked to Google I don't
run ads on my videos but I need the
AdWords account because it helps me add
some little gadgets to the videos that I
wouldn't otherwise be able to and I was
I was playing with that the system came
back online I thought well that's
interesting and lots of people had
emailed me and twittered me and some
people within Google and some people
elsewhere and they were doing whatever
they were going to do to help me get all
this material back up and running and so
something worked my suspicions are that
what worked was the publicity now so but
maybe not you know and it's very weird
being in this situation because there
has been a number of recent episodes
where these larger companies Facebook
Google patreon not that it's a massive
company but it's starting to become
reasonably significant have decided on
rather arbitrary grounds to shut down
their users and this is very ominous to
me partly because we've we've turned our
Communications over to very large
systems or very large systems have
emerged to mediate our communication
right I mean there's lots of benefit to
it so you don't want to get too cynical
about it but we're blind with regards to
the policies that regulate the the the
actions the regulatory actions of these
large organizations and that's really a
bad thing and something else is even
more ominous really ominous you know
it's highly probable that we're going to
build political algorithms into our
artificial intelligence and this sort of
thing will be regulated by machines that
no one understands and that's a really
bad idea and that's a really likely
possibility so anyways I was all
confused about this I thought Jesus
maybe I flew off the handle you know
because I was sort of it was stressful
man you know because I have like 150,000
emails in that account like that's a lot
of emails and it's all my correspondence
for the last 10 years you know so it's
an archive as well as an ongoing email
system I have a commercial email system
that I just set up three weeks ago with
like six different email addresses now
to try to organize my correspondent so I
wasn't completely unable to communicate
but my calendar was gone and that's a
bloody disaster because because like
I've got things scheduled out forever
and I don't remember what they are I
can't even remember what I'm doing in a
day so much less in a month but I
thought maybe I flew off the handle and
I was worried that I contacted the
journalist too soon and you know but
anyways it all worked out so then what
happened well just as I was coming to
this lecture I stepped outside and there
was a little package outside luckily it
wasn't a bomb there's a there's a
package outside nice little package we
looked my wife and I looked inside it
and there was a couple of bottles of
wine in there so that was nice and there
was a little note and so I'm going to
read you the little note because it's
actually pretty
interesting
so so this person said that they had
finally tackled the self-authoring suite
so they seem to be happy about that but
that's not so interesting except
peripherally a friend on Twitter has
contact with Google
Engineers she said quote I spoke with
some friends inside Google who offered
to help and I did get contacted by quite
a few people at Google who said that
they had been you know watching my
lectures and so on and were happy about
what I was
doing anyways I spoke with some friends
inside Google who offered to help but
they suggest he set up a backup plan the
teams are feeling significant pressure
from advocacy
groups and quote I have at least four
Google Engineers who offered to speak up
on his behalf but they know the Team
Dynamics and
unfortunately especially YouTube is an
sjw
Cesspool I hope this information is
useful to you it's like yeah it's kind
of useful all right so that was that was
part of what happened today and so
anyways I still don't really understand
it right because I don't know why it got
shut down and I don't know if anything I
did got it turned back on and I don't
know the reasons for it and that's also
rather ominous it seems to me that when
I was thinking it through and was that
you know I have a
fairly what would you call it
respectable YouTube following I don't
know if you'd necessarily call it
respectable it's fairly large YouTube
following and it seems to me that it
would have been appropriate for Google
if they were going to shut down my
account to tell me why I would think and
also maybe look me up maybe especially
after I emailed them and then maybe not
to have emailed me back and said no
we're not going to reinstate you but
we're not going to tell you any reasons
they didn't say they wouldn't tell me
any reasons they just didn't tell me any
reasons and then it also seems very
strange to me that it just all of a
sudden went back on after two hours and
so well so I don't know what to make of
that maybe
more information will come to light over
the next few days I hope that I didn't
jump the gun but it's very a very
peculiar set of circumstances I thought
it was kind of amusing actually that the
video that they stopped me from posting
today was the last biblical lecture you
wouldn't necessarily think that that
would be the sort of thing that people
would want to stop from being posted but
um we're in very very strange times
so that was my adventure for today and
so I
didn't you know I hate speakers who
apologize to the crowd before they talk
to them because you
know if you're speaking to people and
they've put all this effort into coming
then you shouldn't tell them what a
sorry and useless creature you are
before you talk to them you know and ask
for their forbearance and forgiveness
it's like it's a little you're a little
late for that but I'm still going to do
that a little bit today because you know
I wanted to spend all day preparing this
lecture I mean I've prepared it a lot
beforehand but that rattled me up a lot
and so I didn't prepare as much as I
could have anyways we'll stumble forward
and see how it goes I I'm I'm I'm
reasonably familiar with the stories now
and
so onward and
upward so I'm going to reiterate this
you know I've learned
something I have this idea that it would
be a good idea for young people and and
older people citizens of the West let's
say to learn more about their
culture and their civilization right
because it's a great civilization and
it's it's it's taken a lot of work to
put together but I don't think that we
really know I mean I know a fair bit
about it although I wouldn't consider
myself nearly as educated as a person
should be but I'm not too badly educated
and but I tell you going through these
biblical lectures verse by verse just
makes me even more aware of how
unbelievably ignorant I am you know and
partly for two two reasons like one is
because I've been using this
biblehub.com place and I think I told
you last week but I wanted to reiterate
it because it's important it's so
interesting the way that they've set it
up because you can go through the
biblical stories verse by verse and then
for each verse there's a whole small
font page of comment from multiple
sources and so you know not only is the
Bible hyper hyperlink in the way that I
discussed in the first lecture with all
the verses referring to not all the
other verses but lots of them but it's
un it's got its tendrils out into
literature you know direct commentaries
on the text but also all the all the
literature that's been influenced by it
so it's it's it's an unbelievably
Central and core text and it's so
interesting to read a book where every
sentence has been commented on well
really in volumes and then just to get a
sense of that volume of material you
know how much power brain power there's
been put into this and and to also
understand how Bloody ignorant like I'm
so ignorant about this there's all this
work and and it seems that we've left it
to decay in the dust and it's a big
mistake man it's a big mistake because
the people who were writing these
commentary it's like you know a lot of
it's from the 14th and 15th and 16th
century it's kind of archaic and it's
it's some of it's outdated and some of
it you wouldn't agree with but if you
read all the commentaries side by side
you know you get a pretty good blast of
wisdom coming at you and like the thing
about wisdom is it stops you from
running face first into walls you know
it's not just there to to so that you
can talk to people at parties about what
university you graduated from you know
and it it's there because the the
information is unbelievably useful you
know one of the things that I've
realized that I want to return to
tonight because I've been thinking a lot
about this idea of the Ark you know and
I I think I mentioned to you last week
that I'd figured out that there was this
idea that Noah was perfect in his
generations and that meant that he had
set his family in order it wasn't just
him but he had set his family in order
and because of that when when the
catastrophe came like it comes to
everyone he was able to withstand it
because he had the support of the people
who were near and dear to him and that's
really important when things come along
to lay you low like if you're alone and
and the flood comes it's like man
goodbye to you if you've got 10 or 15
people supporting you in a tight Network
you know and and your your inter
relationships with them are pristine and
you can tell them the truth and they can
tell the truth back to you it's possible
that you might be able to find that thin
way that will preserve you when when
when when you know the Terrible Things
come knocking at your door and so
there's this the the idea of the Ark is
very very Concrete in Noah it's actually
a structure that that he and habits you
know it's a concretized almost like a
child story and I'm not being cynical
about that because there are some bloody
brilliant child children's stories but
you know it's really concretized but
then Abraham comes along and instead of
an ark there's a covenant right now it
says in the story of Noah that Noah
walked with God and and of course
Abraham it isn't clear exactly that he's
walking with God or before God which
we'll get into later but you see I see
this as part of the increasing psych
psychologization of the sacred ideas
that were acted out by archaic people so
first of all it's concretized in the
form of a a ship that actually sustains
you when the floods come right it's it's
very concrete imagery the sort of thing
you might see in a movie but then with
Abraham it turns into a psychological
Covenant in some sense it's like a
contractual agreement now it's a cont
it's a contractual agreement between
Abraham and God but but that doesn't
really matter that I mean obviously it
matters but it's that it's it's only
it's only half of what's important about
that the other half is that it's a
contract and you know one of the things
that you do with your ideal let's say is
you establish a contract with it you
also establish like a social contract
with other people right that that's what
keeps society organized and so there's
this idea that emerges in the Abraham
stories of a sacred contract and that
has the same function as the arc and
what it does because what happens in
Abraham we'll see more of this today is
that he
you know God tells him to go forward
into the world and we we talked about
that last week and he does that he
encounters famine and he encounters
tyranny and he encounters powerful
people who want to take from him what is
his I mean God sends him out in the
world but it's not like he has an easy
ride of it it isn't easy at all it's as
hard as it can be but there's this
consistent emphasis in the text and I
think it's something really worth
attending to that if you maintain your
contract which and that has that has to
do with honesty and trust and truth and
all of those things if you maintain your
contract then you have a good
possibility the best possible
possibility of making your way through
the catastrophy in the chaos and I I
don't want to be naive about this you
know when I read Jung and I started to
understand the idea of the hero
archetype you know the idea that the
human being is a is a force a logos
force that can stand up against chaos
and catastrophe and tragedy and evil and
Prevail I never did think that that
meant that if you did stand up and and
tell the truth that you would
necessarily Prevail right it's not it's
not it's not a magic trick it's your
best bet that's the thing you don't have
a better option and so and that's what's
that's what that see the idea is
emerging in in the abrahamic text it's
like people are figuring this out that
would be progressive revelation that's
one way of thinking about it and you can
think about that religious terms but you
can also think about it as Humanity
Consulting itself right each individual
talking to themselves which is what we
do when we when we think and each indiv
idual communicating with every other
individual and Gathering a body of
wisdom that helps people or Orient
themselves in the toughest conditions
and it it's an incremental process and I
think that I really do believe that
that's speaking purely secularly I do
believe that that's what manifests
itself in the biblical stories right
it's the dawning Enlightenment of
mankind something like that as we start
to understand the principles by which we
have to live in order to orient
ourselves properly in the
world so and I also do believe and this
is this is the thing that's the unspoken
question is like you don't you don't
have any idea how rich and fulfilling
your life could be despite its tragedy
and limitation if you stop doing the
things that you know to be wrong it's a
really Grand experiment and you know one
of the things that God tells Abraham
constantly as as the story progresses
especially every time Abraham makes a
sacrifice is God says walk with me and
be perfect it's something like that and
and so the injunction is well aim high
establish this relationship with the
highest thing that you can conceive of
which you might as well do that because
well what are you going to do establish
a relationship with the most mediocre
thing you can conceive of or you're
going to establish a relationship with
the lowest thing you can conceive of
people do that and I wouldn't recommend
it it's a really bad thing and there's a
lot of pain associated with that and
maybe you know there's there's pain that
can expand into a world destroying Force
down that route and there's absolutely
no doubt about that so what is there
something superstitious and foolish
about attempting to establish a
contractual relationship with the source
of all being I mean I I I just don't see
that as a as an erroneous conception and
you know it's not necessary perhaps to
get lost in the details we can argue
forever about what God might or might
not be but we could at least say that
the concept of God is an embodiment of
Humanity's highest ideal right we could
at least agree on that and then you
might say well is that real and the
first thing I would say about that is ah
there's a lot of things about the world
we don't understand and the second thing
I would say is it depends bloody well on
what you mean by real that's for sure
and that turns out to be a very
complicated question
so okay so we left Abram remember at the
end last time he had just gone off to
fight a bunch of kings and get his
nephew back which seemed to be a pretty
courageous act and so that that brought
a story to an end and it's interesting I
think what happens in The Narrative is
that there's a story so Abraham is
somewhere and he goes somewhere else
right that's a story and he has
Adventures along the way and those
Adventures are usually the typical kind
of Adventure which is a a rift in the
structure of the story an exposure to a
kind of chaos and Novelty and then a
reconstitution of the of the mode of
being so that's That's a classic story
right you are somewhere you're a certain
way you're moving forward something
happens that you don't expect it blows
you into pieces it introduces chaos
right you you face the dragon you get
the gold or maybe the bloody thing eats
you and the story is over and then and
then you get to where you're going but
then the question is well what happens
when you get to where you're going and
that's a really important issue
because one of the things that happens
to people all the time in their life is
that they get to where they're going and
then they don't know what to do right so
for example you graduate from University
it's like okay story over who Are You
Now who are you the next day and so so
what happens is when you succeed then
there's a success crisis and the success
crisis is well I've run this story to
its end now what and that's exactly what
happens in in the abrahamic stories and
they're punctuated by a a period of
contemplation and sacrifice so every
time an abrahamic story comes to its end
then Abraham makes another sacrifice and
communes with God and then he figures
out what to do next and that seems that
seems right it it seems psychologically
right because what you should do when
your story comes to an end when you've
achieved what it is that you want to
achieve or perhaps when you're in
terribly Dire Straits but we won't talk
about that at the moment when you've
achieved what you need to achieve then
the next question is okay well now I'm
that person or I have that character
what what do I need to do next and some
of that is always well what do I need to
give up now what do I need to let go of
so I can move to the next Plateau right
assuming that your life is a hopefully a
a sequence of upward moving what would
you call them it's like sopus except
you're actually each time you climb up
the mountain you get a little higher on
the mountain it's something like that so
it's SI with an optimistic bent and and
and maybe if you push the rock up the
mountain properly and let it roll down
then and if you do that right then it's
okay every time you roll it back up it's
it's better in some sense I don't think
that's unrealistic either and
so Abraham goes and rescues his nephew
from this this these T tyrannical Kings
that's very brave and he doesn't take
any reward for it because as far as he's
concerned it's just a manifestation of
the right thing and then he has another
Vision after these things that's the
battle the word of the Lord came unto
Abram in a vision saying fear not Abram
I am thy shield and thy exceeding great
reward and Abram said Lord God what will
thou give me seeing I go childless and
the steward of my house is this elier of
Damascus and Abram said behold to me
thou Hast given no seed and lo no one
born one one born in my house is mine
Heir and behold the word of the Lord
came to him saying this shall not be
thine Heir but he that shall come forth
out of th own thine own bowels shall be
thine hair and he brought him forth
abroad and he said now look to heaven
and tell the Stars if you're able to
numble them number them and he said unto
him so shall thy seed be and Abram
believed in the Lord and he counted it
to him for righteousness and he said
unto him I am the Lord that brought thee
out of er the chelis to give this land
to you to inherit it and he said Lord
God whereby shall I know that I shall
inherit it and then he does this
sacrifice take me an eer a heer of 3
years old and a she goat and a ram and a
turtle do and a young pigeon and then
God comes down and well Abraham goes
into a trance that's what it appears to
be in the story um and has a great
Terror and then God Appears to him
and I'll just review this commentary
again this is from Joseph Benson and
when the sun was going down that's about
the time when you wash up for the
evening and he's he's he's praying and
waiting towards evening a deep sleep
fell upon Abraham not a common sleep
through weariness or carelessness but a
Divine ecstasy that being wholly taken
off from things sensible he might be
wholly taken up with a contemplation of
things spiritual very strange very very
strange series of interpretations
because it does seem that what happens
to Abraham that he falls into some sort
of revelatory trance and so
um when as I've taken some pains to
explain we don't really understand such
things and and we can't rule out their
existence because there's too much
evidence that they do in fact occur uh
perhaps it's a technology that we no
longer possess that's one possibility
perhaps we no longer know how to access
these sorts of states of Consciousness
it's certainly
possible and lo a horror of great
Darkness fell upon him this was designed
to strike awe upon the spirit of Abram
and to possess him with holy reverence
holy fear prepares the soul for Holy Joy
God humbles first and then lifts lifts
up yeah well I think that's right too
like you know one of the experiences
I've had in my life fairly commonly in a
variety of different ways this is
especially true when I was paying a lot
of attention to my dreams which I did
for about 15 years I guess something
like that now and then I would feel like
I'd learned some things and had sort of
Consolidated them and then before I went
to sleep I'd think okay
I'm ready to learn something else it's
like and I didn't say that without
trepidation and you because usually when
you learn something you know it's not
that Pleasant because you usually learn
something about why you're wrong and the
deeper the thing that you learn the more
you learn about why you're wrong and
there's a death that's associated with
that because then you have to let that
part of you that's wrong die and that's
that's that's the sacrifice right and so
you have to make a sacrif you have to be
willing to make a sacrifice before
you're going to learn something and the
and perhaps your what you'll learn is in
proportion to your willingness to make a
sacrifice and I really do believe that I
do believe that as well
because I also think
that if you commit to something that
means that you don't do a bunch of other
things right so that's the sacrifice of
all those other things you commit to it
and you set your SS on it if you really
commit to it and you get the sacrifice
right so to speak then the probability
that that thing will be successful
vastly increases and I think that that's
also not a naive or or a naive way of
thinking or a foolish way of thinking I
my experience has been that that's the
case and so back to the dream I mean I
do think that we learn in trepidation
and that most of the time if if you have
to be laid low before the new revelation
can make itself manifest and I think
that's also what happens to people often
in psychedelic experiences when they
have a bad trip is they don't get
through the bad part of it and maybe
that's because there's so much mess in
their lives now I'm speculating but it's
informed speculation
there's so much mess in their lives that
the altered state of consciousness makes
manifest that it's like a little trip
through hell and but the mess is so
complete and comprehensive and all
pervading that there's no way they can
get through it now if they could get
through it and started to sort those
things out then you know there would be
perhaps a what would you call it a
compensatory positive Revelation at the
end but the first thing is if you want
to learn something is that you're going
to encounter
well you have to figure out what's wrong
before you you can figure out what
wisdom you need next to guide yourself
and that's no laughing matter right and
um so I think that that's what it that's
what this refers to I think that's the
sort of psychological experience that
that refers to I also think we built
this a little bit into this into the
future authoring program you know I read
this really cool paper once reviewed by
this guy named Jeffrey Gray jeffre gray
wrote a book called The neuros pychology
of anxiety man and that is a great book
it is impossible to read it took me
really it took me like 6 months to read
it and the reason for that is that he
reviewed about 3,000 papers and they
were all neurological papers and and and
heavy psychological SL biological papers
he actually read them all and he
understood them and he synthesized them
and then he wrote this book about the
synthesis and so and he's very very
careful with terminology and so to read
the book you have to understand brain
anatomy and you have to understand neuro
neuro pharmacology and you have to
understand Animal Behavior Uh the whole
literature on animal behavior and a
whole whopping uh uh dose of human
psychology and cybernetics it's like
it's a vicious book but you really learn
something when you read it if you go
through it bit by bit like and it's it's
it's had an overwhelming influence on
psychology even among people who haven't
read it which is most of the people who
cite it by the way and so but he said he
he he outlined this real cool study
maybe it was a sequence of studies about
how to motivate rats you know and rats
are a lot like us you know in positive
and negative ways and uh you know
biochemically and and uh psycho
pharmacologically they're very very
similar and they have very complex
social environments and you know they
have hierarchies and they play and they
laugh Jack PP Yak PP found out that rats
laugh if you tickle them you could
tickle them with like the end of a
pencil eraser but you can't hear them
laughing cuz they laugh ultrasonically
like bats so you have to record it and
then slow it down then you can hear them
giggling away when you tickle them so so
which is you know you think oh going to
spend $50,000 on a study demonstrating
that rats laugh and you think well wait
a second wait a second that's a major
league study you know because he's
outlined a a ludic circuit that's a play
circuit and Yak panks have discovered
the play circuit in mammals that's a
bloody big deal you know if you get that
by like rubbing rats with a pencil
eraser Well good for you so anyways so
gray talked a lot about how to motivate
a a rat and you might have heard about
BF Skinner you know he used food pellets
to motivate his rats but what you don't
know about Skinner is that those rats
were starved to three4 of their normal
body weight so they would they would
work for food man so skinners rats were
kind of oversimplified but you can get
rats to work for food they don't have to
be that hungry you can get them to work
for food and they'll do all sorts of
things they'll press levers and and
they'll open bar open doors and they'll
solve problems and you know they'll do
all sorts of things and one of the
things you can do to kind of measure how
much the rat is motivated is let's say
you've run him through a maze and he
knows there's some food at the end of
the maze you can tie a little spring to
his tail and see how hard he pulls when
you open the door to the maze so that's
because that's how much rat work the rat
is willing to do so you can measure that
or you can see how fast he skitters down
the maze and you can get an estimate
about the rat's motivation and so then
you might say well how motivated is a
hungry rat and the answer would be
depends on how hungry he is but there's
another answer it also depends on what's
chasing him when he's going after the
food so if you have a rat and you you
have food over here and you waft in some
cat odor rats hate cat odor and it's
innate they never have to see or smell a
cat to be absolutely petrified by cat
odor so if you waft in some cat odor and
then open the door that rat will Zoom to
that food a lot faster than it will if
it's just hungry so a rat running away
from something that it doesn't want
towards something that it does want is a
very motivated rat and so one of the
things we did with the future authoring
program that's gerain to this idea of
Terror because there's there's this idea
in the Old Testament that the fear of
God is the beginning of wisdom and it's
a pretty harsh idea but but there's
something really useful about it because
one of the things you see with people
all the time time is that they're maybe
they're trying to stumble forward
towards their ideal as poorly defined as
it might be but then they're afraid
right they're afraid about what they
might encounter and that stops them
because fear does stop people it freezes
you like a prey animal and so people
move ahead but then they get afraid and
then they stop moving ahead and so and
that's not so good because negative
emotion is a really powerful motivator
so we're more motivated by negative
emotion than positive emotion
quantitatively speaking quantitative
quantitatively speaking you can measure
that and that's I think because we can
only be so happy but we can really be
suffering and dead you know so we have
to pay more attention to the negative
and that's bad because the negative can
stop you and then in my clinical
practice you know I often talk to people
who are trying to make a difficult life
decision and and they they're weighing
out the costs and the benefits of making
the life decision you know and one of
the things I always talk to them about
is wait a second that's an incomplete
analysis you have to weigh out the
benefits and the costs of doing this and
you have to weigh out the costs and
benefits of not doing that not doing it
and that's not the same as the zero that
you assume that you're starting with
right because to not make a decision
also has a cost and sometimes the cost
of not making a decision is far worse
than the cost of making a decision even
if the decision is risky and so one of
the things you can derive from that and
this is very useful I think is
that this is also I think why it's so
useful to contemplate your mortal so to
speak is you're screwed no matter what
you do you know and that actually frees
you is that you you you have path a that
has catastrophes and you have path B
that has catastrophes and you don't get
to have the no catastrophe path but you
get to pick which one and that's really
something because if you know that
there's terrible risk associated with
everything that you do and don't do then
you can afford to take some risks
because you're not you know and this is
all within the arc metaphor I'm still
making the case that despite the fact
that your life is essentially
catastrophic you can you can make a
covenant with the highest ideal and that
will take you through it the best way
possible I'm I'm I'm still making that
case
so so then you think okay well I'm
trying to make this decision I'm going
to go try to do something difficult and
isn't that terrifying and then you think
yeah but wait a minute what's really
terrifying is not doing it and then you
think about the cost of not doing it so
in the future authoring program we have
people do this little meditative
exercise which is okay just think about
your insufficiencies by your own
definition right the way that you don't
do what you know you should do about the
things that you do that you shouldn't do
that you know you shouldn't do beyond a
shadow of a doubt right there's some
things like that and that that's bad
habits and and poor aim and all of the
resentment and hatred and aggression and
unresolved conflicts and all those
things that are dementing you and
warping you and then think okay those
things get the upper hand man they get
get the upper hand and they take you the
worst possible place you could go in the
next 3 to 5 years what exactly does that
look like and so you sketch all that out
and you think hey I don't want to go
there and so the next time that a
Temptation comes up you think well it'd
be a lot better for me if I didn't
succumb to this temptation it's like
that's kind of weak hey you'd look a
little better if you didn't eat like a
cheesecake a day or something like that
you know that's that's something but
it's not the same as um I'm going to
have diabetes and I'm going to lose my
damn leg in in 5 years if I don't get my
eating under control that's motivating
and so then the Temptation comes along
and you think oh how about no seriously
how about no not just because a a higher
good would be obtained if I avoided it
but because a a terrible catastrophe
would be averted if I didn't and so well
so you want to get your fear behind you
right you want to get it behind you
where it's pushing you forward instead
of in front of you where it's stopping
you and you get your fear behind you
pushing your for you forward by actually
thinking through the consequences of not
putting your life together and the least
of those is that you waste it and suffer
right because you're going to suffer
anyways man so you waste it and suffer
that's a bad deal because maybe if
you're going to suffer you could at
least do something Noble and glorious
and upright and powerful and honorable
and admirable and helpful and and
difficult you know that's just so much
better and maybe that's good enough so
that you think hey you know little
offering it's basically worth it at
least it's a way forward you know at
least it's a way
forward and he said unto Abram know of
assurity that thy seed shall be a
stranger in a land that is not theirs
and Shall Serve those people and they'll
afflick them for 400 years God he's
hedging his bets here a lot right he
says to Abraham well go out you know
into the world and then he confronts him
with a famine and he confronts him with
a tyan and with powerful people he wants
to take his wife and then he loses is
his nephew and who he has a fight with
then he has to go fight a war and now
you know he's reconstituting this
Covenant and God says yeah you're going
to
have a nation is going to come from you
but they're going to be slaves to
tyrants for like 400 years it's
like he's not a great salesman exactly
but but the thing about it is that the
thing that I like about it is that it's
realistic you know and you got to think
too because who knows why is that the
Bible exists or why people wrote it but
you know if they're going to sell you
something I don't know if this is the
way to do it you know because unless
you're a Salesman who's sophisticated
beyond belief because you'd think that
if it was just a matter of controlling
the masses let's say which is one say
Marxist interpretation of religion or or
providing people with a primitive
defense against death anxiety which is
essentially the Freudian interpretation
that you'd kind of make the deals that
God cut with Abraham a little more on
the positive and Polished side instead
of making them a realistic offer
constantly like they are that that's
also that's that that's part of the
reason I think it is reasonable to treat
the Bible as literature it's it's more
than literature it's something other
than literature but you can treat it as
literature and I think the reason that
you can treat it as literature is
because the characters are all complex
including the character of of God
himself is complex and sophisticated
it's not one-sided and it's it's
paradoxical and incomprehensible at
times but I think good literature is
like that because you know true Art
here's something about true art this is
something I learned from Yung it's so
smart he was so smart so imagine that
you inhabit the land that you know
conceptually and practically and then
imagine outside of that there's that
massive space of things that you don't
know and even outside of that there's
the space of things that no one knows
right so it's the known territory
surrounded by the unknown that's the
canonical archetypal landscape and the
unknown manifests it itself to you and
that's where new knowledge comes from
but the question is how is that
knowledge generated and it doesn't just
leap from completely unknown to
completely articulate in one move that
isn't how it happens it has to pass
through stages of analysis before it
becomes articulable and the first stage
of analysis as far as I can tell is that
you act it out so if something really
surprises you the first way that you
react to it your category is actually
embodied you like this that that's your
first category it's not ceptual at all
it's embodied and then maybe you start
to like you're at home at night and you
know something startles you and you
freeze and then it's dark and then your
imagination populates the darkness with
whatever might be making the noise and
that's the sequence it's like embodied
response imaginative representation
exploration articulation that's how
information moves from the unknown to
the known and and artists are the people
who stand on that imagistic Frontier and
they and they put themselves out into
the unknown and they and they they take
a piece of it and they and they
transform it into some mythological
image and they don't know what they're
doing exactly because they're Guided by
their intuition if they're real artists
otherwise they're just propagandists
they have to be contending with
something that they don't understand and
what they do is they make it more
understandable you know and and then
people gaze at those artworks or or they
listen to the stories and then they
start to become informed by them but
they don't know how or why I was at the
modern art museum museum of art and in
New York I'm afraid I don't remember
which one unfortunately but it I was in
this amazing room you know it had all
these Priceless paintings from the from
the late Renaissance hanging in it you
know each painting worth who knows a
billion dollars maybe the Priceless
painting so the room was it's a shrine
and it was full of people from all over
the world who were looking at these
paintings you think well what the hell
are these people doing coming to this
room looking at these paintings like
what what are they up to one of them was
a of the Assumption of Mary right
brilliantly composed and there was all
these people looking at it and I thought
what are they doing they don't know what
that means like why are they looking at
that painting why is it in this room why
does it cost a billion dollars why is
that painting worth so much and the
answer to that is well we don't really
know like it happened they're they're
sacred objects in some sense and we gaze
at them in ignorance and wonder and the
reason for that is that the unknown
shines through the Mattis and in
partially articulated form and so
well that's the role of
Art and that's the role of artists you
know
and real artists real artists are
contending with the unknown right and
they're possessed by it they have a
personality trait openness that makes
them do that they can't even help it and
I've had lots of creative people in my
clinical practice and I can tell you the
worst thing for Creative people is to
not be creative because they just die
and it because it's it's it's it's like
maybe you're a tree with a few major
branches you know that's your
personality so if you're extroverted man
you can't be cut off from people because
you just wither and if you're agreeable
you have to be in an intimate
relationship or you die you know and if
you're conscientious man and you and
you're unemployed you're just going to
eat yourself up because you have to have
a duty and you have to carry a load
because you just can't stand it
otherwise and open people have to be
creative they have to be because
otherwise they die they don't have any
vitality and so they're cursed with the
necessity of putting a foot out into the
unknown and making sense of it and then
they're also cursed with the necessity
of trying to make a living while they're
doing that which they can't because you
can't it's almost impossible to monetize
creative creative action as many of you
who are creative will no doubt find out
it's very very frustrating it's not that
creative action is without value right
because the creative people are
entrepreneurs and the creative people
Revitalize cities and the creative
people make things magnificent and
beautiful you think about what's
happened in Europe over the last
Thousand Years say 2,000 years this
amazing unbelievable collaboration to
make things so beautiful that they're
they're jaw-dropping when you walk into
them and you think about the economic
value of that right I mean I think it's
it's either France or Spain that's the
most visited country in the world it's
one of those two I think there's more
tourists in France than there are people
most of the time and part of the reason
for that is it's just so damn beautiful
you just can't stand it and you think
what's the economic value of that it's
absolutely incalculable and what's
interesting too is that you build that
beauty in and then the farther away you
get from it in time the more valuable it
becomes right instead of decaying it has
exactly the opposite effect its value
magnifies and one of the things that I'm
deeply ashamed of as a Canadian is that
our sense of beauty is so underdeveloped
we're so primitive it's not even
primitive that's the wrong word because
you
know I don't know what it is it's it's
it's second rate it's second rate at
least it's Terror too because people are
afraid of beauty but the idea that art
is the conservatives really have a
problem with this in particular because
conservative people tend not to be that
creative and it it's a Myster Myst by
temperament it it's a mystery to me
because they should be concerned with
economic development and beauty is so
unbelievable crucial to Economic
Development it just yells out at you you
know so anyway so that's what artists
are doing and so one of the things I
would say is buy a damn piece of art you
know find one that really speaks to you
and and buy a piece of art because you
invite that into your life and it's it's
a look out if you do it if it's a real
piece of art because you'll also get a
you know a little introduction to the
artist and then that'll seep into your
life and that'll change things like mad
but it's really it's unbelievably worth
it because it it opens your eyes to the
domain of the Transcendent that's the
right way of thinking about a real piece
of art is a window into the Transcendent
that's what it is and you need that in
your life because you're finite and
limited and bounded right by your
ignorance and your lack of knowing and
unless you can make a connection to the
Transcendent then you don't have the
strength to Prevail and that's part of
the Covenant that's part of the Covenant
with God and you can see that because
you look at these magnificent Cathedrals
that our civilization built over the
centuries you know some those they're
still bu building the sangria familia in
in in uh Barcelona right and it's an
amazing building I think it's going to
take them like 300 years to build that
you know people in the Middle Ages
they'd start building a cathedral and
they' think oh we'll be done this in 300
years you know you imagine the vision
that it took to invest in something like
that we we look at quarterly reports we
can't think 300 years into the future to
build something of that kind of
remarkable remarkable what those
Cathedrals are so they're they're
perfect they're trees first right
they're a forest right the gothic
Cathedrals they're they're a forest and
the sun is shining through the branches
that's the stained glass and they're the
perfect balance of light and structure
because they're representing something
about the proper structure of being
which is something like the proper
balance between light and structure and
and they represent like the sacred
tragedy of mankind that's why they're in
the shape of a cross and they're open to
the sky that's why they have a dome and
they're full of gold so that it Glitters
because that's like the city of God you
know and and and you you can see that
that integral to to our culture is the
idea that beauty is one pathway towards
God and it's and it's and if you can't
find another pathway then why don't you
use Beauty sure most of you do that with
music because music is the one thing
that modern people can't be cynical
about thank God for that and being
fascinated by music because of that it
it speaks meaning to people right even
nihilistic Punk Rockers are so damn
engaged with their music that they can
hardly stand it and you can knock on
them and say look you know you're having
a Transcendent religious experience and
they'll just tell you to [__] off
because
[Applause]
that's because that's that's what punk
rockers have to do
but but that's still what's happening
you know I mean it's still what's
happening so okay
so okay so I I got into all that because
I was talking about about the Bible as
literature you know and and and trying
to and trying to lay out because we we
need in our culture to justify the Arts
and you have to I don't want to do that
by talking about high culture talking
about something abstract and event
that's the wrong way to go about it this
is vital you know like one of the things
that's really interesting about the
University of Toronto is that the the
one side of the campus where we are is
beautiful medieval Cathedral and the
other side is God awful Factory and you
know and and that and the thing is the
attitude towards knowledge has
paralleled that architectural
transformation you know at one point the
humanities let's say were a sacred
Endeavor and and so was the art of Being
educated in the university and that's
turned into like mass factory and that's
reflected in the architecture this isn't
accidental none of this happens none of
this happens by random chance you know
it's not like there's a conspiracy or
anything because there isn't but that
doesn't mean that these things aren't
Tangled together and the loss of Beauty
in the universities is a catastrophe
because without that beauty there's no
call to higher being you know you this
is also why you know i' I've mentioned
to people that they should clean up
their rooms that's become quite the
internet meme but I'm really serious
about it CU it's really hard to do that
and I've been cleaning up my room by the
way for about 4 months now because my
life was thrown into such a catastrophe
and and also we were renovating and so
but it isn't just that you clean it up
you also make it beautiful and be it's
really hard to make something beautiful
and it's really worthwhile and what's
really cool is if you learn to make
something beautiful even one thing if
you can just make one thing in your life
beautiful then you've establish a
relationship with beauty and then you
can start to expand that relationship
with beauty out into into the world like
into other elements of your life and
that is so worthwhile it's just
incredibly crazily worthwhile and that's
an invitation to the Divine you know you
have to be daring to do that and people
are terrified of it people are terrified
of color they paint their walls beige
they're terrified of art they buy some
mass-produced thing because they don't
want anybody laughing at them for their
lack of taste and they would get laughed
at because they have no taste but you
have to well it's right because what do
you know right you have to develop it
and so you're going to stumble along and
make mistakes to begin with and you're
going to show yourself because if you
buy oh I think this is pretty and you
know somebody comes over and goes what's
up with you it's kind of hard on your
self-esteem but but it's a St you're
stumbling towards the right you're
stumbling towards the kingdom of God
that's what you're stumbling towards
when you try to make an aesthetic
decision and to put something in your
life that's beautiful and it's
unbelievably worthwhile to do that and
you have to steer clear of the frauds
and the con artists and all of that and
art is full of that of course because
it's difficult to distinguish between
the real thing and the fraud but but
it's unbelievably worthwhile and so back
to literature I'm I'm I'm telling you
this partly because I've been thinking a
lot about the humanities and the
Arts and practically speaking because I
know that artistic types are also
entrepreneurial types they're the same
personality types and so it's very much
worthwhile to make an economic and
practical case for this sort of thing
you study literature in the humanity so
that you can familiarize yourself with
the wisdom of our civilization man you
should do that because people have been
working on this thing for a long time
and it's Rich Beyond comparison so why
wouldn't you do that and you teach
yourself to to read and you teach
yourself to speak and you teach yourself
to think and you teach yourself to
communicate and I can tell you if you
can read and think and and communicate
you are absolutely 100%
Unstoppable and that's another thing
that's so interesting about Humanities
education that's at the core of the
University it's like there's nothing
more economically valuable than teaching
people how to articulate themselves and
communicate because they can identify
problems they can formulate solutions
they can negotiate to consensus they
they can negotiate on their own behalf
or on the behalf of others it's like
there's absolutely no downside to it
except that there's responsibility that
goes along with it but it doesn't matter
because there's no escape from
responsibility you can either take it
voluntarily or you can take it
involuntarily those those are your
options but there aren't any other
options and so we need to understand the
role of art and literature and and stop
thinking about it as an option it's not
an option it's not an option what is it
said man does not live by bread alone
that's exactly right we live by Beauty
we live by literature we live by Art and
literally not metaphorically we cannot
live without it because life is too
dismal and and and tragic in the absence
of the sublime so and ourselves we have
to be Sharp so that we can survive
properly and Orient the world properly
and not destroy things including
ourselves and
so and so back to the Bible which I do
think is a reasonable it's reasonably
construed as a piece of literature
because it's deep and because the people
who wrote it had at least one foot in
the unknowable and they're trying to
communicate what they experienced in the
unknowable to make it known and that's
partly what we're trying to do in this
series and what you're trying to do
while you're listening and all of that
and so good for
that and also that Nation whom they
Shall Serve I will judge and afterward
they'll come out with great substance
there'll be a period of tyranny you know
and there's a psychological truth to
that too one of the things I learned
from Reading nche because you can learn
a lot from Reading nche that's for sure
he he talked about the Catholic church
and you know n is often construed as a
great critic of Christianity and and he
certainly was but he was no casual
critic in fact I think he was the sort
of critic that you'd like to have as a
friend
because he was the sort of critic that
said well here's the great things you've
done and that you could keep doing but
here's a bunch of really things that you
did that you really should stop doing
and he talked about the Catholic church
and he said what the Catholic church had
done to the European mind in particular
was discipline it so that over a period
of a, years 1300 years 1,400 years there
was this rule that there was a a
conceptual structure within which you
had to interpret everything thing and
what that did was turn the European
educated European mind into a
systematizing cognitive entity and that
once that systematizing cognitive entity
had been established then it could free
itself from those underlying
disciplinary structures and go off and
do such things as produce the Scientific
Revolution for example which required
incredible systematic thinking and so n
had this really interesting idea about
freedom and he believed that slavery was
an intermediary between the undeveloped
individual and the free individual that
you had to you had to submit yourself to
some intense disciplinary process for
some period of time in your life before
you could develop any true freedom and
so you think maybe you want to learn to
play the piano it's like that's not
going to be any fun for a really long
period of time right because you're
really bad at it and there's a million
things you have to memorize and you have
to stumble around like a well like an
amateure and the same thing happens when
kids learn how to read and some of them
never get past that point and they never
get to the point where they can enjoy
reading but in order to put yourself
together you have to put yourself in a
vice and allow yourself to be
constricted and mangled even by the the
thing that enslaves you but the the goal
should be that as a consequence of
submitting to the discipline that you
become disciplined and then once you
become disciplined you can emerge from
the disciplinary structure as someone
who's free and that's something that's
very much worth thinking about as well
so that's Illustrated conceptually in
this in this
piece of literature let's say because
what what the psychological meaning of
what God tells Abraham is that all
people all people are subject and I mean
not equally obviously all people are
subject to the Tyranny that precedes
freedom and that that idea is is
repeated over and over in the Old
Testament it comes out most particularly
in the story of Moses right because of
course that's the story of movement from
tyranny where do you go from a tyranny
it's an absolute catastrophe you go from
a Tyran into the desert you know where
you starve it's harsh that's what
happens in the in the story of Exodus
and so that's so interesting too because
what it means is that sometimes if
you're going to move uphill the first
thing that happens is you move downhill
a lot and so if you want to escape from
The Straits that bind you now you're not
going to move forward and go up you're
going to move forward and go down and
that's another reason this is also
something that Yung talked about a lot
is that you know on the road to
Enlightenment you encounter all the
things that you don't want to encounter
first like all the weaknesses of
yourself all the realizations of the
tyranny of the world and the catastrophe
of Nature and all of that and so you
step out of your encapsulation your
ignorant encapsulation and it's
immediate plummet into something that's
a desert let's say where everything is
chaotic and where you're wandering
around without Direction a real
catastrophe so it's you know because one
of the things you might ask yourself is
that if Enlightenment is possible then
why aren't people enlightened because if
it was just a matter matter of going
from a good place to a better place it's
like well man let's just get at it it's
no it's no problem right why would we
ever stop doing that but it seems not to
be that it's that you're here and that's
not good and it's unstable and you step
out of it and it's like down down to
where you don't want to be and you have
to contend with that and then maybe you
can start your struggle upward and so
Abraham God is telling Abraham this and
he's also telling him that it's okay
it's rough though and now and thou shalt
go to thy fathers in peace Thou shalt be
buried in a good old age but in the
fourth generation they shall come hither
again that's the Israelites the the
descendants of Abraham for the iniquity
of the amorites is not yet full God is
going to leave the tyrants alone until
they've manifested their full tyranny
for reasons that we don't fully
understand and it came to pass that when
the sun went down and it was dark Behold
a smoking furnace and a burning lamp
that passed between the pieces Al Albert
Barn said the oven of smoke and lamp of
flame symbolize the smoke of Destruction
which we've already talked about this
catastrophe of of the initial stages and
the light of Salvation they're passing
through the pieces of the victims and
probably consuming them as an accepted
sacrifice are the ratification of the
Covenant on the part of God as the
dividing and presenting of them were on
the part of
Abram in the same day the Lord made a
covenant with Abram saying unto thy seed
I have given this land from the river of
Egypt unto the Great River euphra
IES now Sarai Abram's wife beam no
children and she had a handmade an
Egyptian whose name was Hagar so this is
a big catastrophe for Abraham especially
in those times and perhaps now as
much although perhaps people aren't as
conscious of it as they once were I mean
for Abraham without a a biological son
there was no there was no there was no
vision forward into the future you know
and I mean we don't really know what
sort of time span over which these
archaic people thought but the medieval
people we already said could think 300
years into the future without without
batting an eye and these people who were
who were concerned about their
descendants were obviously thinking
about existence in a way that wasn't
just focused on their immediate
existence right they were thinking about
well their children and their
grandchildren maybe their
great-grandchildren maybe the whole
society that that stemmed out from them
and that's that's smart you know one of
the things I learned from PJ at least in
part was that
his idea of the equilibrated state which
he thought about as partly part of the
biological basis of the idea of moral
progress it's something like that he was
a very very smart PJ know he said that
the the proper equilibrated state is one
where imagine you have a family you got
five people in it and you're doing what
you want in in your family what's good
for you but you're doing it in such a
way so that the other four members of
your family agree with what you do and
that it also facilitates them doing what
they want and what they should be doing
and so it's a really tricky arrangement
because it isn't just for you it's for
you in a way that's for them and you
could also see that that would be
something that would be a multiplier
right because if you have everyone
working voluntarily towards the same
common goal then you get a multiplying
effect of that and then you might think
well it's not just you and your family
it's you and your family today and next
week and next month the next year and 10
years from now so you have to take the
time span into account and then it
should be you and your family in a way
that works well in society and then it
should work well now and next week and
next year and into the future it should
be iterable right that's like
sustainability it's something like the
idea of sustainability and that's that's
I would say that's a reasonable way of
conceptualizing the holy city it's it's
something like that you know if you're
if you're trying to make it concrete
it's like how should you live your life
well let's say you live your life in a
manner that justifies its limitation and
tragedy that's a good start but then
let's say that it does that in a way
that also reduces the limitations and
suffering of the people that you
interact with and now and into the
future well maybe there's a way to do
that I mean a good negotiation does that
right because if you're negotiating with
someone like your wife for example what
you want is for her to agree with the
negotiation and one of the things that
PJ said which I think was brilliant
brilliant he said if you take an
equilibrated system a family let's say
and a dise equilibrated system so that
would be one where let's say the father
is a tyrant and everyone is operating
under his Whip and you put them in a
head-to-head
competition the equilibrated system will
outcompete the disequil system because
the enforcement cost is such that it
will slow the system down you know
because you'll get resistances from the
people inside the system they'll work it
the system will be working at counter
purposes to itself plus there's
enforcement costs and so a tyranny
cannot beat an equilibrated system and I
was really excited to encounter that
idea because when I encountered it I was
also trying to figure out if there was
some
quantitative difference between the
systems say of the Soviet Union and
maest China and the systems of the West
apart from just you know arbitrary World
interpretation as the postmodern
nihilists might have it if there was
something fundamental at stake in the
terrible cold war that we fought or if
it was just a matter of opinion you know
in the pedian take was that well roughly
speaking is that the West Was An
equilibrated system not perfectly
equilibrated but reasonably equilibrated
in that people were essentially even if
they were slaves to some degree they
were at least voluntary slaves instead
of involuntary slaves and that that was
better the system was actually
technically better and not just as a
matter of interpretation so that's a
lovely thing to know and I think it's a
really really solid really really solid
idea I haven't been able to you know put
crowbars under that idea and lift it up
I think it's a good one
so now Sarai Abram's wife baram no
children so okay back to children well
so one of what one of the things that's
worth thinking about with regards to
reading these old stories because we're
so we're very arrogant modern people eh
we look at these old stories and we
think ah we've transcended all that
Superstition it's like don't be so
bloody sure about that these people
weren't stupid and so there's there
there are ways that they viewed the
world that we don't have anymore and one
of them seems to be this concern for
Descendants because that just isn't part
of our way of thinking we have very
short-term way of thinking maybe it's
it's not even one lifetime long it's
certainly not multiple lifetimes long
and it isn't clear to me at all that
that's for the best and you know the the
constant complaint that the
environmentalists generate some of which
is Justified and some of which is just
anti- capitalist anti-patriarchal
nonsense that should be cleared out of
that entire conversation is that we need
to take a longer View and consider more
things in our purview when not when we
act and like that's fair enough like do
we really want an ocean that has nothing
in it but jellyfish because that's
really what we're we're doing and we're
doing it very very rapidly and the data
on that are very clear and so you know
when you lift up your eyes and you make
a connection with something that's
Transcendent then that should bring more
of the world within your purview and and
maybe that's concern for the endless
number of descendants that you might
have you might think too well you know
if you're a successful person if you
have a successful family God only knows
how many people you will be the father
of right it's completely cuz you're a
Nexus right all sorts of things have
come together in the cosmos to produce
you and then all things sorts of things
manifest themselves from you you have no
idea what your potential the potential
consequences of your actions might be as
they Cascade across time right you have
no idea and so Abraham at least is
concerned with these sorts of things and
God seems to be concerned too because he
promises Abraham that if he maintains
the Covenant that the most important
things that he needs will come to
him and they're pretty serious about
this so Sarai talks to Abram she's not
very happy about the fact that she can't
have children she says behold now the
Lord hath restrained me from bearing I
pray thee go in unto my maid it may be
that I obtain children by her and Abram
hearkened to the voice of Sarai well
that's not a very trivial thing I
wouldn't think I don't imagine that that
Sarah was Sarai was very happy about
turning her maid over to her husband and
potentially being usurped in the whole
childbearing uh in the whole
childbearing process not in the least
but you know so it's also a major
sacrifice on sarai's part there's no
doubt about that and of course it's very
difficult for us to talk about the
ethics of the fact that Hagar was a more
or less involuntary participant in this
but that was the times absolutely the
case and of course slavery and
indentured servitude is the way of
mankind except in very very in very very
limited circumstances Carl Yung had
something to say about that too which I
really
liked he said that part of the reason
that modern people have
it's not the only reason there's the
Industrial Revolution obviously but part
of the reason that modern people have
been able to escape from the catastrophe
of tyranny and slavery is because we've
agreed to make ourselves our own
slaves right so instead of owning a
slave you own yourself in a sense and so
you Trot yourself off to work and
exploit yourself so that you can stay
alive and maybe it's not something that
you want to do but you've taken on the
role of slave in some sense in
relationship to your own Survival
instead of forcing someone else to do it
which is also something I think that's
very Noble about the West is that we're
willing to enslave ourselves as
individuals and we're not we're not
doing that to other people now we're
doing it to some degree obviously
because the society is imperfect but
that's something that's very much worth
thinking about so and Abram hearkened to
the voice of Sarai and Sarai Abram's
wife took Hagar her maid the Egyptian
after Abram had dwelt 10 years in the
land of Canaan and gave her to her
husband Abram to be his
wife
that's the other thing that's been so
interesting about doing this one of the
other things about doing this biblical
series and it's one of the things that's
so cool about Google um despite the fact
that they cut off my
account um you can find any piece of art
that ever existed on Google and so
that's great so you know when I'm trying
to illustrate these these lectures I
type in Abraham Renaissance and then
like I get 200 Renaissance paintings
it's so great and then I can look at
them one of the other things that's so
remarkable is that all of these the
major themes of these stories have been
illustrated by people of
spectacular M mind mind expanding Talent
you know there's just this
endless array of well look at that I
mean that's an amazing
painting and so and there's and and of
this there's there's dozens of paintings
on on this theme and it's just another
indication of how obsessed people you
know this was the only book that existed
for years and people were absolutely
obsessed by it and produced all these
amazing things from it and we're in
danger of losing that and that's a big
mistake because it's magnificent a
little humility would go a long way
towards restoring
it and he went into unto Hagar and she
conceived and when she saw that she had
conceived her mistress was despised in
her eyes so Hagar was successful and
like that was a Hallmark of feminine
success now and certainly then and so
she started to Lord it over Sarai which
seemed a little bit on the
ungrateful side I would say because
Sarai made a big sacrifice to allow
Hagar to become Abram's wife and so a
little bit of gratitude would have been
in order I suppose at least that's how
the story goes and Sarai said unto
Abraham my wrong be upon thee I have
given my maid into thy bosom and when
she saw that she had conceived I was
despised In Her Eyes the Lord judged
between you and
I and Abraham said unto Sarai Behold thy
maid is in thine hand do to her as it
pleases you and when Sarai dealt hardly
with her Hagar fled from her face and
the angel of the Lord found her by a
fountain of water in the wilderness by
the fountain in the way to Shure and he
said Hagar sir's maid whence camest thou
and withi wilt thou go and she said I
flee from the face of my mistress Sarai
and the angel of the Lord said
return to thy mistress and submit under
her hands and the angel said I will
multiply your seed exceedingly that it
shall not be numbered for multitude and
the angel said behold thou art with
child and th shall Thou shalt bear a son
and shall shall call his name ishmail
and Ishmael means God Hears by the way
because the Lord hath heard thy
Affliction and he'll be a wild man his
hand will be against every man and every
man's hand against him and he shall
dwell in the presence of all his
brothers and she she called the name of
the Lord that spake unto her thou God
seest me for she said have I also here
looked after him that seeth me wherefore
the W well was called beer
laroy and that means the well who sees
me and lives it's an interesting
interlude because you know Abraham God
has established this Covenant with
Abraham and obviously things are going
wrong in the household in a really
serious way like a really serious way
because well he's now had a child by
another woman and that the two women are
not getting along and one is beating the
other because of her
insubordination and and contempt and so
she's so desperate she runs out into the
desert where she's probably going to die
and God comes along and says anyways to
to to to Hagar that her son shall as
well be the father of Nations and so
that's partly a reflection back on the
power of Abraham's Covenant right even
though even though things are going
terribly wrong locally let's say the
fact that Abraham has made this
overarching agreement with God means
that all of these catastrophes are
taking place within a bounded space
within the ark we could say that's one
way of looking at it and I I do think I
do think that that's right because it
seems to me that you know if everything
falls apart around you there's there's a
couple of things you're going to want
you're going to want someone standing
beside you that's for sure that you can
trust you're going to want your family
around you and you want going to want
them to have your back and you're going
to want know that you didn't do some
godamn stupid thing to bring all hell
down on yourself and if you're lacking
any of those when that crisis comes
there's a high probability it will
flatten you and you won't be able to get
up you know it does seem to me you can
ask yourself this question when things
collapse around you how much utility is
knowledge of your own moral virtue it's
bad enough to be late it's bad to be
laid low but to be laid low and to know
that you were the fault you were at
fault for for it and worse the things
that you did that you knew you did that
were wrong brought you there then I
think you have nothing to stand on in
that situation and that's also the
circumstances under which I think you're
more more likely at least to be
abandoned by people around you so given
that you know that the catastrophe is
coming right that the tragedy of life
will strike you the question is well how
do you fortify yourself against that and
all obviously to some degree you do that
by being materially sensible and these
old people in the the test in the Old
Testament these ancient people they
weren't blind to the utility of having a
good crop and some animals you know that
that's a that's a integral part of their
life to take care of themselves
physically but they're also wise enough
to know that there's an element of
moral NE what would you call it there's
a necessity for moral integration that
defends you against the catastrophy of
existence even more effectively than
anything material and even more that
this stability of the material things is
more dependent on the Integrity of your
spirit than the Integrity of your spirit
is dependent on the material things and
I think the evidence for that is
actually quite clear I read read a very
interesting book a while back called the
wealth and poverty of Nations that was
written by a Harvard Emeritus professor
of history and one of the things that he
claimed I liked it I thought it was very
smart was that the only true natural
resource is interpersonal trust if you
can set up a society where people trust
each other then it will instantly become
rich and he used the example of Japan
which is a very conscientious society
and very rich Society but the Japanese
have no natural resources right none to
speak of and yet they're rich and then
you have countries like the Soviet
Russia and and much of South America
where there's just natural resources
that you know they're just like
Venezuela it's just more natural
resources than you know what to do with
and the places are absolute
catastrophes absolute catastrophes of
cynicism and Corruption and so he
attempted to document the relationship
between default interpersonal trust
among citizens within countries and
their their productivity and their their
GDP and their their standard of living
and found a very very tight relationship
and and I like that a lot and I've got a
story about that quickly that I think is
very interesting I'll tell you two
stories one sort of
generic um well I'll tell you one
personal first so one day I lent my car
to one of my graduate students and he
took it to Montreal was this old
Cadillac and uh he got it was a really
bad rainstorm in Montreal and he was in
one of the highways that are like set
into the ground and there was like 6
Ines of water and he was turning a
corner hit the brakes and skid it on the
water and smacked it into the wall and
on the corner of the of the bumper you
know and so then he brought it back and
he was very apologetic about it and and
uh his name was Matt Shane tell you that
because Matt might hear this and I can
shame him a bit for doing this 20 years
ago you know and uh he's a professor at
uh the Ontario Institute of Technology I
think now and quite a successful one but
anyways he brought the car back and I
went and got it evaluated for damages it
was like $1,700 or something to repair
it and or maybe more but it was almost
as much as the car was worth I thought
well I'm not going to do that so I went
online and I typed in the part and uh if
you do that you can get people to bid on
sending you a used part from all over
North America so that's kind of cool so
there's all these junk dealers have got
together and they have this you know
network of communications so you put in
the car part and then they send you a
bid and so this guy said uh well I'll
send you the bumper assembly which is
the whole bumper and the lights for like
250 bucks and I thought yeah okay you
you could do that that'd be good so then
I said yes and then he called me up
about half an hour later this guy from
way down south he had a really deep sort
of Mississippi accent he said wait a sec
was that for the bumper or the bumper
assembly and I said well it was for the
bumper assembly he said Oh I thought it
was for the bumper and then he said but
that's okay I'll send it to you anyways
I thought well that's pretty good so I
said well thank you and then I hung up
and then half an hour later he called me
up again and he said look I just went
out and looked at that bumper assembly
and there's a plastic trim piece on the
side and it has a scratch in it and I
thought I better tell you that just in
case you you didn't want it I thought
wow that's so amazing it's like there's
a miracle man it's like this guy he's
somewhere in Miss Mississippi I'm never
going to see him again ever I'm never
going to have any contact with him like
he made a bad deal right because the
part was worth more than he decided to
sell it to me for but he stuck with this
deal and then he went over and above the
Call of Duty he said well this part that
I'm selling you to you for way less than
it's worth is damaged so I thought I
better tell you it's like man you got to
recognize a miracle when you see one
that was a miracle so I I said Hey look
it's thanks for calling man so okay I
can handle the scratchs send the part
and he did and and I got the car fixed
and forgave Matt and you know it had a
happy ending so so that's
trust right because I didn't know him
from Adam and he's a primate full of
snakes just like the rest of us and yet
he was willing to simplify himself to
the point where I could just take him
absolutely at his word and that meant we
could trade even though we were
strangers it's like man do not
underestimate the utility of that and
then there's eBay so when eBay first
started you know the idea was it's not
going to work cuz you'll send me junk
and I'll send you a check that bounces
and that'll be the end of eBay right and
so these escrow agents popped up so you
could ensure your transaction with them
was for like 10% of the transaction they
would get the check and the goods and
make sure that they were okay and then
send them on or ensure the transaction
but what happened was the escrow agents
didn't make any money and the reason for
that was no one cheated now you think
about how amazing that is right you
bring these people together across a
whole continent they've never seen each
other before they're never going to
interact with each other again and this
was before there were any reputation
ratings on eBay and yet the default
transaction was you describe your goods
honestly including their flaws you set a
reasonable price I decide to pay you
ship the goods and I pay you and it
works and what happened was that eBay
produced It produced a tremendous amount
of capital that was previously frozen so
Frozen capital is when you've invested
money in something but the thing is no
longer useful to you so the money is
just sitting there Frozen right so to
speak and you can't get it Loose because
well you've got a attic full of junk how
are you going to get rid of that oh eBay
and so all of a sudden all these things
that were just junk became valuable and
everybody got richer and none of that
wouldn't would have happened without the
Covenant that we established between
each other that's predicated on trust
and so you might say that trust is the
currency and currency is trust because
it's a promissary note right and if
people lie that and the currency gets
debased very very rapidly and so the
economy runs on trust and
so that's part of the overarching
Covenant so Abraham makes this Covenant
with God and he decides that he's going
to aim high and live a good life and
tell the truth and that puts this
boundary around him it's like a Walled
Garden it's like a Walled Garden and
inside there there's all sorts of things
that are Happ that are complex and
difficult but outside there's a boundary
and the boundary is well maybe things
won't it's like God says After the flood
he says I'll never send a flood again
that's part of the story and so there's
an intimation there that no matter how
bad things get they won't get so bad
that they'll be catastrophic but there's
a but there's a coded to that which is
that you have to maintain the Covenant
and we don't know what that means you
know because you know you think it's
pretty obvious that if you treat people
well if you really think about it and
you're not being naively optimistic and
like you know a nice good person with
all the weakness that that that that
that that uh that that Intimates if
you're being hard-nosed and sensible you
understand that if you treat people if
you trust people that's an act of
Courage if you're not naive right if
you're naive it's an act of stupidity
because you might get bit and you
probably will and if you're naive and
you get bit you will suffer for it it'll
traumatize you but if you're not naive
and you know you can get bit then you
might ask well what should you do with
people and the answer is you should
trust them not because you're naive and
not because they couldn't betray you and
not because you don't know that they
could betray you but because if you hold
out your hand in trust then you're
inviting the best part of that person to
step forward and that won't happen
unless you take that initial step and
that's courage not naivity and so to
trust someone once your eyes are open
that's an act of courage and that opens
up the world you know and you might say
okay and so there's this idea in the
story that you can withstand it a fair
bit of the catastrophe of Life by
establishing the proper Covenant and by
acting in a trustworthy Manner and
extending your hand to people
properly and you might say well okay
that's sensible I can understand how
that would work and I can certainly see
how the opposite wouldn't work because
you know if I have to be absolutely
terrified that you're going to betray me
at every possible moment and we're in in
a negotiation we're not going to get any
work done man because I'm going to be
figuring out what you're up to all the
time and you're going to be figuring out
what I'm up to all the time and we're
just not going to get anywhere you'll
come and say you're going to do
something and I can just simplify you I
can say you're going to do what you said
you do I don't have to worry about you
and then the same applies to me and then
we can go do something and that's how we
generate wealth so then you might say
well if what's the ultimate limit of
that you know like we know that there's
corruption in our society that people
betray each other and there's deceit and
all of that and it causes things like
the periodic collapse in 2008 which was
complicated but was partly engendered by
corruption like what would be the upside
if we acted if we really determined to
act honestly what do you think it is
that people would be able to do with the
world if we stopped acting in a corrupt
manner I mean what what's the like what
what is the upside do you think we could
could could how far back could we push
aging do you think if we hit it hard for
50 years could we triple our lifespan it
wouldn't surprise me you know all these
terrible diseases that beset the planet
we could get rid of them there's no
reason for hunger and starvation we make
enough food it's like what would happen
if we
stopped acting badly how much better
could things get well you start locally
I think you start with yourself and you
start with your family but you know
there's intimations of the Divine
there's intimations of the kingdom of
God and the Covenant with God in the Old
Testament it's like you think well we
speak secularly you think well that's an
unprovable assumption it's like well
just hold on a sec what's the Assumption
here exactly what is the upper end for
Humanity I mean who's who's going to say
right who's going to say especially in
this day and age man there's so many
things happening that you can't even
comprehend them what could we do if we
put all of our effort into it well you
can experiment with that CU you can
start in your own household you can
start in your own room and you can make
miracles happen in the confines of your
own space there's no doubt about that
all you have to do is try you'll see
that that happens it h and people are
writing to me and telling me that
they're trying this and that that's
exactly what's happening and
so so we don't want to be too cynical
about about where we might be headed and
Hagar bore Abram a son Abram called his
son's name which Hager bear Ishmael who
is by tradition the forefather of
several Arab Nations and of Muhammad
himself and Abram was 4 score and6 years
old when Hagar bear Ishmael to
Abram so that's the end of another story
and then so that section ends and then
again we have an encounter between
Abraham and God when Abraham was 90
years old and 9 99 years old the Lord
appeared to him and said I the almighty
God walk before me and be thou
perfect Alexander McLaren who was a a
Biblical commentator who lived in the
early 19th century
said this phrase walking before God is
Not precisely Walking with God because
that's what Noah did right he says it's
rather that of an act of Life spent in
continual consciousness of being named
naked and opened before the eyes of him
to have whom we have to give account I
was pretty happy to stumble across that
because it I mean I might have picked
and chosen of course you never know that
whether you do that but it does seem in
keeping with the narrative strain of the
chapter right because what what we've
hypothesize so far is that God has
called Abraham and said you know get out
there in the world go go to where it's
unknown go to where you're a stranger
and get away from the familiar go out to
the unknown establish yourself and great
things will come but regardless of the
proximal evidence great things will come
of it and so I think that's what the
walking before God refers to it's not
like Abraham is acting in certainty
there's no certainty here that that's
the act of the leap of faith even
because it does require a leap of faith
for you to move into the world because
the world is a catastrophe
self-evidently the world is a
catastrophe and so there's there's
there's every reason for you to assume
that you should just sit in your
basement and hide from it but that's
that's not it doesn't help it doesn't
make make things better and the thing is
perhaps you're not built for that you're
not built to hide I don't think the
people are built to hide I think it
destroys
them and so walking before God in some
sense means that Abraham we could say is
taking the lead he's the person that's
going out there into the unknown God
says well great things are going to
happen but he's a little short on
details that's for sure so the weight is
still on Abraham and that's a good thing
because it also that ennobles Abraham
right that's the other thing that's so
cool is that if God had just laid out
the whole story and and and you know
brushed the the the the branches from
Abraham's path while he was walking
forward well then there'd be nothing for
Abraham to do there'd be no nobility in
his own Pursuit and this is another
thing that we don't understand very well
it's a really tough thing to understand
is like how much trouble would you want
there not to be it's a weird question
right because you want to have something
to contend with you want to have
something that that forces from you the
best that you have and so you have to
have real problems it's something like
that would you dispense with all your
real you could just lay down on a bed
and have paum infused into your mouth
you know if all your problems were
solved and so maybe you want difficult
problems that you can solve something
like that because there's some I don't
know what it is about it there's there's
the overcoming and the and the growth
that comes along with that there's
something about the nobility of the
Enterprise you certainly see that when
you go about having children for example
which is you know the psychological
literature is quite clear if if you do
momentto moment comparisons of people
who have kids and people who don't have
kids the people who don't have kids are
happier and so psychologists who tend to
get things wrong even when they make
intelligent discoveries like that one
immediately some of them jump to the
conclusion that because happiness is the
goal that well there's something about
children that you know make you unhappy
and that's not good it's like well wait
a second that maybe that's the wrong
metric it's like of course you're less
happy once you have children because you
have to worry about them you know my
neighbor down the street who's very
smart woman said to me once you can only
be as happy as your unhappiest child and
which I thought was really good you know
that's really smart but then it isn't
well if having children doesn't make you
happy the answer isn't don't have
children it's like don't be so stupid
about being happy that's the answer it's
because there's a nobility in the
pursuit right and of course now you're
responsible you know you have a new baby
you think especially if you're a new
parent you
think what the hell is this and what am
I going to do with it you know it's like
and and then you're you're done for the
rest of your life you never sleep
properly again because you're going to
be worried about this creature that you
have to take care of but like what the
hell good are you if you're not doing
that or something else equally difficult
because you just you just haven't been
called out yet unless you take on a
responsibility like that the idea that
life is you know that happiness is the
purpose of life it's like great for
happiness man if it comes along you
should be thrilled that it's visiting
you but the notion that that's that
that's what you should pursue that's
that's the weakest possible notion first
of all as soon as something terrible
happens to you you're done it's like
life is to be happy it's like well now
you have cancer so how's that how's the
happiness thing working out for you
now or maybe it's not you you know maybe
it's your father that has Alzheimer's
disease or some damn thing and you know
it's like it's a rare person that
doesn't have some catastrophe one one
person away from them it's like life is
to be happy it's that's not right and
and we can at least derive that from
these stories that isn't what they say
at all God's perfectly happy in the
stories to Grant the people with whom he
forms a covenant happiness and
prosperity but there's never a word that
that's the purpose the the rule is aim
high and get your bloody act together
that's the rule and establish this
contractual Covenant with the ultimate
ideal and that will see you through the
catastrophes and that's a much more
mature way of looking at life as far as
I'm concerned because all you have to do
is have your eyes half open and you see
that the fundamental reality of life is
tragedy and suffering there's that's
inescapable the quest that doesn't mean
that it it makes life unbearable or that
it makes being something that shouldn't
have existed right that isn't what it
means but it means that you have to
contend with it and you have to get
ready and the willingness to adopt
responsibility for yourself and for
others is is the precondition for that
and and then maybe if you do that
properly then now and then you get some
happiness you know you can sit at the
end of a day and you have half an hour
where your conscience is clear and
there's nothing that you need to be
doing and you can relax and think you
know that that's all right things are
okay and thank God for that and that's
that's maybe where you get your
happiness
so yeah that's something that's growing
up man obviously and and to not know
that and to not be taught that like
everyone should be taught that it's so
obvious we should be taught that well
and that's partly what these biblical
stories
do and I'll make my Covenant between me
and thee and will multiply thee
exceedingly and Abram fell on his face
yeah and God talked with him saying as
for me behold my Covenant is with thee
and thou shalt be a father of many
nations God says this a lot to Abram
right it's almost like he has to remind
him now and then and it's not surprising
because he keeps going through these
unbelievable Adventures you know that
are really psychologically and socially
shattering so it's a good thing that
this reminder pops up in on fairly
frequently but of course Abraham is also
open to it and I think what does it mean
you
know I'll talk personally for a moment I
guess so I've asked myself a lot of
questions in the last eight months man I
can tell you that and I'm still asking
myself a lot of questions and I've been
conferring with a lot of people because
I had lots of people who were helping me
negotiate whatever the hell this is
that's happening and you know I could
ask them how I was doing and they would
tell me a bunch of of things I was doing
wrong and some things I was doing right
and I could listen to them I was asking
questions all the time about how the
hell I should manage this properly and
you know what what I was trying to do
and what seemed to serve me properly was
to figure out how to do it correctly
that was the issue it's like I didn't
really care what happened and I guess I
really don't care what happens but I do
care if I do it correctly because I
don't want to screw it up I don't want
to screw things up and that seems to be
a reasonable goal for people I mean
wouldn't you like that as a goal that
you don't screw things up because you
can't control too you know your life
isn't fully under your control by any
stretch of the imagination but it might
be nice to to not have your conscience
eating at you saying look you know you
had a big opportunity there and you
mucked it up CU you're weak and blind
and you didn't listen that's no good the
C the catastrophy is bad enough as I
said without you being the bloody source
of it and
so
well that's Abram falling on his face I
guess and also communing with God it's
like you you don't he wants to get it
right he wants to get it right and
there's these these things that beckon
and promise
but but it's it's it's bloody easy to
make a catastrophic mistake and you'll
do that in your life you know
and and maybe humility is one of the
things that can prevent that because you
can look and you can think okay what am
I doing wrong what am I doing wrong what
can I do better how can I do this
properly and then maybe you know you get
you get you get the intimation of the
proper way to move forward and maybe
that's what protects you when things are
chaotic and and in strife and who knows
what that's
worth neither shall thy name anymore be
called Abraham which means High King if
I remember correctly but thy name shall
be Abraham for a father of many nations
have I made thee Oh yes Abraham High
father look at that that Abraham means
father of a multitude and I will make
thee exceedingly fruitful and I will
make nations of thee productive right
productive and that seems to be
something that's that's good to be I
mean like one of the things that I've
thought about
deeply I thought deeply about death and
the death of my family members and about
funerals and I thought about it partly
because I had this weird experience once
that I think I told you about where I
took one of my clients to see an EMB
bombing which was a very strange
experience and I had a chance to talk to
the funeral director you know cuz they
have weird jobs you know and there's
this idea well the Freudian idea that
people suffer from this terrible death
anxiety and there's a whole line of
social psychological theory theorizing
called Terror management Theory that's
predicated on the idea that we defend
ourselves against death anxiety with our
belief systems and like it's a pop it's
Ernest Becker's idea he wrote the denial
of death which is a great book but
there's a weakness in it because you see
some people who aren't like that you
know like emergency room nurses aren't
like that and paliative Care nurses
aren't like that my my sister-in-law is
a Paleo of care nurse that's a hard job
right because you go in there you're
caring for people you have and they're
in pain they're on their last legs
you're trying to make them comfortable
and you have a relationship with them
because how the hell are you going to
make them comfortable if you don't and
then they go and die on you and that
just happens that's what happens every
day right and what's weird is that
people can be paliative care nurses it's
like how do you figure that out because
people can actually thrive in the face
of death strangely enough and like these
Funeral Parlor directors they were
interested to talk to because that's all
they do right they just deal with they
deal with death and grief all the time
and it was very interesting talking to
them because I talked to two of them
they found their job extremely
meaningful and I asked them well you
know does that what does that do to your
life you know you're saturated with
death and suffering and there and this
is the same answer that I got from the
paliative care nurses that it doesn't
undermine your life it enriches it now
who would guess that right I mean what
what the hell that just doesn't make any
sense at all but what it does is speak
to human possibility because God only
knows how tough you are you know I mean
if you read history and you read about
what people have done you think wow
we're pretty tough people
are I read uh there was a shipwreck in
the
Antarctica 100 years ago or so and I
read the the story it was an
autobiography if I remember correctly of
the of the captain I might be wrong
about that but I've got the basic story
right well they had a shipwreck in the
Antarctica was then they were there for
a whole year in the Antarctica you know
and none of them died not one he didn't
lose a single man not one he kept them
morale high and then they took this boat
that was on the ship and they crossed
like 400 miles of the roughest ocean the
roughest frigid ocean in the world right
you don't go in that ocean and then they
went to an island and they walked across
the island across these mountains that
no one else has ever
climbed since and they went to the city
on the other side of the island and they
got a boat and they went and rescued
their compatriots and everyone survived
it's like endurance is the name of the
book you read that book man you think
wow people are really tough you know and
if and it's it's ridiculous so who knows
how tough you are and maybe you find out
by going out to find out how tough you
are right so you take on a challenge one
that you think you can Master just
that's just a bit beyond your grasp and
you master it and then you're a little
tougher and you think hey that worked
out pretty well and so then you're more
of a monster and then you go out and you
find another challenge that's even
bigger and you think well maybe I can do
that too and all of a sudden you can and
you get a little bit bigger and God only
knows what the limit is of you and you
find out by pushing yourself against the
world and of course that's what Abraham
is doing and
so see we're very pessimistic us modern
people you know we're pessimistic about
Humanity that's for sure dismal wretched
Planet destroying cancer on the planet
right as the club of Rome described us
so pleasantly back in the 1960s you know
and and I don't know maybe we're ashamed
of the Cold War maybe we're ashamed of
all the destruction in the 20th century
and the hydrogen bomb and and the you
know the continuing catastrophes of our
societies and and we're deeply ashamed
of that and ashamed of ourselves
personally but it's a hell of a thing to
you know call us a cancer on the planet
there's just no excuse for that because
what you do with cancer is eradicate it
and I don't think that that's a very
Noble motive
personally and I think it says a lot
about the people who would use such
phraseology that they would dare to
conceptualize Humanity in that manner
but you know it would be nice if we
could be optimistic and I think again
the problem with being optimistic is
that it's naive so then the question is
is there an optimism that's not naive
and I think there is and the optimism
that's not naive isn't just a
a a visualization of how strong people
can be so one of the things that I I
tell people I've told my students in my
class in maps of meeting here's a goal
you want to be the person at the funeral
of your father that everyone can rely on
how would that be you want to be the
person who's broken and and and useless
and adding to the misery in the corner
and look I'm not making light of
people's grief you know I'm understand
grief but who do you want to be when
there's a
crisis right do you want to be the
person that everyone can turn to for
strength it's like why the hell not why
not that as a goal that'd be a good goal
because then if there's a crisis then
there will be it won't be such a bloody
crisis because there'll be someone there
that can deal with
it you know so when I went and talked to
these people at the funeral home I
envisioned that I thought okay well this
is something you have to contend with if
you're going to be alive and adult you
have to contend with death and suffering
and you have to be ready for it and you
have to be there for the person because
that's all they're going to have and so
there's a goal man and in this time of
nihilism you know it's what's the point
of life people ask and and they're
taught that at universities what's the
point of life everything's
interpretation Humanity's a cancer on
the planet you know well how about no
how about not that how about that
there's something to
[Applause]
and I will establish my Covenant between
me and thee and thy seed after thee in
their generations for an Everlasting
Covenant to be a god unto thee and to
thy seed after thee and I will give unto
thee and to thy seed seed after thee the
land wherein thou art a stranger all of
the land of Canaan because of course
Abraham went out into the land of
strangers
right but it says that he'll Master If
he if he keeps his Covenant he'll Master
the land of strangers that's a wonderful
thing to know and I think a true thing
you know because if you're dealing with
strangers I've dealt with lots of
strange people in my life but I'm a
clinical psychologist and that isn't to
say that everyone that I've dealt with
was strange because that's not the case
but I have encountered some very strange
people and you
know the way to deal with strange people
is to you never lie to a strange person
that's the thing especially if they're
paranoid you never lie to someone who's
paranoid it it will come back to bite
you and if you're in an extreme
situation with someone who's very
unpredictable the only thing you have
that works is the truth that
works
I'll tell you a little story this is in
my book so I had this landlord in
Montreal he lived next door to me he was
an ex hell's Angel's biker he'd spent a
lot of time in prison and his wife had
borderline personality disorder and she
committed suicide when I lived there and
he was a rough guy and he was a
kqu he spoke jeel which I could hardly
understand and uh he didn't really know
what to make of me and I didn't really
know what to make of him um but we got
along you know and I was very careful
talking to him as as you might imagine
but but I I was it was very and we we
went over my wife and I went over there
and we had spaghetti dinner one night
and we sort of communicated and I bought
a poster from him because he made these
wooden posters that had neon on them and
that's how he made a living he'd kind of
trained himself to be a bit of an
Electronics guy and so he made these
things and he was trying to quit
drinking and we talked about that he was
a lot older than me he was like 20 years
older than me I was about 25 at this
point and uh we got along pretty well
but every now and then he'd go out and
get and drink and he could really drink
you know like he was one of these guys
who could drink like 60 beer and you
think well no one can drink that much
and you're wrong I studied alcohol for
like 10 years some of my subjects
fathers drank 40 o of vodka a day and
had been doing it for 20 years so you
can drink a lot and he could drink a lot
and what would happen he was trying to
not drink but he'd go out and go on a
binge and then he'd be gone for like
three days and he'd drink up all his
money and then we'd hear him out in the
backyard howling at the moon with this
little little ugly dog he had you know
and he'd howl and the dog would howl and
he'd howl and the dog would howl and and
it was rather unsettling and made my
wife
nervous
and and uh but worse you know now and
then he'd come to the door at like 3 in
the morning e and he'd knock on the door
and he'd be standing there and I don't
know how much experience you've had with
rough guys who are alcoholic and who are
drunk but it's they can
be upright and unconscious at the same
time and so that was the state that he
was in you know he'd be just swaying and
he'd ask me if I would like to buy his
toaster or his microwave because he
needed some money to keep drinking and
you know I didn't really want to buy his
toaster or his microwave but when the ex
Hell's Angel je all speaking 60 beard
drunk kqu biker shows up at your door at
3:00 in the morning and offers you to
sell offers to sell you his microwave
the easiest thing is to say I really
need a
microwave
so so you know I bought the microwave
and toaster and some other things but
then but then my wife talked to me and
she liked my landlord you know even
though she was afraid of him she liked
him and and she said you can't buy any
more any more appliances because it's
not good for him and I thought huh
that's an interesting problem you know
so what the hell am I going to do about
this because no I don't want to buy your
microwave just doesn't seem to be the
right answer at 3 in the morning
so so one time he took me out on his 750
Honda and he put me on the back of it he
wanted to show me his layer I guess his
Hangouts and I got his wife's helmet on
but it didn't fit it just sit on the top
of my head and he said I got on the bike
and he said if the cops chase us we're
not stopping and then and then away we
went and we went to these like these
bars downtown on S law they were very
rough places and he got into like four
fights that night because he was a rough
guy you know and these kind of punk guys
would come up to him and sort of
challenge him and act stupidly around
him and he was very skeptical and if you
were acting stupidly around him for any
length of time he' just hid you because
he felt that that's what you deserved
and perhaps he was right you know so so
I had firsthand opportunity to observe
him so anyways he sure enough about a
week or two after we had this
conversation he showed up at the door
knock knock knock you know open the door
and he was standing there you know with
his eyes kind of half closed and he was
swaying and he had I don't remember what
the appliance was this time but he
wanted to sell it to me and I
said I'm not Paul I can't buy this I'm
not going to buy this because I know
you're trying to quit drinking and if I
give you this money then you're going to
go and drink it up and it's not going to
be good for you
and what else did I tell him I think I
told him as well that this whole thing
of him coming to my house at like 2 in
the morning was scaring my wife who he
liked and that it had to stop and
believe me man I I was thinking about
what I was saying cuz he was watching me
like a rough guy watches you and a rough
guy watches you like this he thinks if
you say one thing that indicates
contempt you're going to bloody well pay
for it and so I was finding my words
like you know I was crossing a swamp and
trying to look for the for the Rocks
underneath the surface and I said what I
had to say very very carefully and he
looked at me for about 15 seconds and
that's a long time to be looked at at
3:00 in the
morning and he
left and he never came back to sell me
anything again and we got along fine but
that's a good illustration of
this issue with regards
to truth and success in The Strange Land
because I was in The Strange Land when I
was talking to my neighbor my landlord
then and I managed to say what was true
carefully enough so despite the fact
that he was a very violent person and
that he was a very intoxicated person
and that he had every reason to be
suspicious of me and we couldn't
communicate very well and I didn't do
what he wanted that he took it and he
left and there was no problem and life
went on just fine after that and so we
don't want to underestimate the utility
of establishing this bounded
relationship with the ideal and
attempting to live with some nobility in
truth while aiming at the highest ideal
there's nothing about that that's
anything
but strengthening and
positive and it's exactly what you need
to set against the catastrophe and
uncertainty of life and as far as I can
tell that's what these abrahamic stories
are attempting
to
communicate so we'll stop there thank
[Applause]
you
I have to make an announcement I'm going
to do a talk August 22nd I think not
sure of the date but I'll I'll find out
with Gad sad from Concordia and
so and with a with an ex social worker
named Serena Singh and with faith Goldie
I think faith is going to be there as
well so the tickets for that will go on
sale I'm not hosting this someone else
is dealing with it but the tickets for
that will go on sale within
approximately a week and I'll post that
on my I'll probably make an announcement
on YouTube but I'll twit Twitter it
Twitter it and all of that so and I
think I mentioned to you guys last week
that I would like to continue this
series but I think I'll do it once a
month and I'll try to do it in this
theater but I haven't got
word from the people who run the theater
that's the university whether or not
it'll be accessible but I'll figure
something out and so oh hi Serena Serena
is the person who's going to be hosting
this 2 it's August
22nd 7 to 10 p.m. at Ryerson Monday okay
tickets go on sale Monday all right and
then and then
uh oh there's a special freedom of
speech edition of the Hemingways
restaurant Jordan Peter Peterson
discussion group tonight so that's at 1
p.m. so um you're all welcome to attend
that so that's 1:42 Cumberland Street
okay so that's it for announcements I
guess and then let's say for questions
yes I was going to let you ask the first
question last time wasn't I okay so I
will do that and so let's make sure
again everybody to speak into the mic
clearly so that the YouTube people can
hear and uh you know the ghostly YouTube
people and and so go ahead question I
was quite impressed with your
presentation last week and uh I wasn't
quite sure where it was going at one
point and would neither neither was
sry and that's okay because at one point
I I listened and I thought what you
basically were talking about this is
what I saw you were embodying mind body
and spirit and bringing it all together
as one and you touch on it a bit tonight
when you when you talk about truth this
is where we need to go right and I know
you say be positive and all that and
yeah that's right I agree it's scary
what's going on right now however we
have the power to stay in the positive
what you talked about last week you
talked about using our intuition which I
consider our higher self using
Consciousness and you made reference I
can't remember exactly what you what you
said but you held your hand and uh you
talked about emotions and bringing
intellect on top and when you said
emotions everything just lit up for me
because I'm thinking that's our heart
chakra that's what combines our lower
self our physical being the material
stuff all the all the stuff that doesn't
really motivate us with our higher self
and when when you talked about emotion I
want to talk about the emotion of love
and I find so many people are terrified
it's a four-letter word I know but it
doesn't have to be bad okay so I
remember why when I talked to you last
week why I wanted you to ask this
question so okay so I've talked a lot in
this lecture series about truth and know
I think there's a battle in the biblical
stories all the way through between love
and truth in terms of their Primacy and
so So and I've concentrated a lot on
truth in my own thinking but I and it's
hard to talk about love because it's a
word that people have mouth to death you
know as soon as you start talking about
love then people should just go into a
different room and and not listen to you
you know because it it gets it can get
sappy and new Agy just like that and and
I don't like that at all but but it's
still something that has to be contended
with and I think so I've been trying to
conceptualize let's say what this
Covenant might might con Institute and I
think the love part so here's this so
you know there's this book by Gira
called fa and it's in two volumes f one
and F two logically enough one was
written much later than the other and Fa
basically sells the soul to the devil
for for knowledge and the devil in FA is
mephistophiles and mephistophiles is
quite a well-developed character and
Gira has mephesto say what he's about
which is really quite cool so it's like
the adversary of the world evil itself
gets a chance to speak and make its case
and Gira thought this was so important
that he actually had mephistophiles
announce himself once in FA one and then
using the same words you know phrased
differently again in in part two and it
really struck me it really struck me and
so what mephistophiles says is
that the world is such a Charter House
of suffering and destruction that it
would be better if it never
existed and so that what he's working to
is to bring existence to an end because
it is not justified by its
suffering it's like that's it's an
argument very similar to the argument
that made by
Ivan cam camarat of thank you thank
Russians e you can't pronounce them or
live with them you
can't but he basically he's an atheist
and does a very good job of detailing
out The Atheist argument or maybe an
anti-theist argument and he's arguing
with
his his brother alosa who's a mon
monastic noviciate who's a very good guy
but not an intellect Ivan's an intellect
and a very powerful one and he basically
tells alosha
that the all of the cosmos isn't worth
the suffering of one child he tells this
story about this and this dovi took this
from a newspaper about this parents that
locked their four-year-old daughter in
an ouse overnight and she screamed about
it until she froze to death and so dovi
used that argument he tied that into
Ivan's anti-theist argument against
elosha it's very very powerful argument
the brothers katsov is an absolutely
mindboggling amazing book I would highly
recommend it um and so that's the meilan
perspective mopan perspection is
perspective is that being itself is so
corrupt that it shouldn't
exist so then you think okay well that
fair enough that's a decent argument
it's understandable but the problem
comes when you try to implement that and
what happens when you implement it as
far as I can tell you adopt that me
meilan attitude of bitterness and
resentment and destruction is that you
make all the suffering that you're
complaining about far worse I think
that's what happened at the base of
things in the 20th century is that there
was a powerful movement among human
Humanity to bring being itself to a halt
you know what culminated in the
development of the hydrogen bomb and and
the high probability for many at many
periods of time that we were going to do
something permanent and fatal which
seems like a bad idea it seems like a
bad idea so what's the opposite of the
mephistophelian attitude and I think the
opposite of that is what's presented in
the biblical stories in the guise of
love and that is the wish that things
would be good it's something like that
that's what love is I think is that it's
the attempt to orient yourself towards
making things better and it it's
predicated on something like a deep
appreciation for being def despite its
suffering and deficiencies and maybe a
decision that you're going to act to
bring about things to move things
towards the good and I think that's the
thing that sets the parameters of the of
the aim it's it's the opposite of the
mephistophelian attitude it's like to
work towards the betterment of being
because you've decided that you're going
to open your heart to existence
something like that and it's within that
framework that truth takes place I think
because truth has to serve something it
can can serve truth but it has to be
bounded inside something and I think
that that's what it's bounded inside so
what I what I was going to refer to with
that was um David Hawkins wrote power
versus force and he put it on a
quantifiable scale all different
emotions he called it Consciousness and
he put love at 528 Hertz he put shame at
20 I'm not sure if I've got these 100%
right um guilt I think at 30 fear at 50
and it shows you how far the people who
are really knocked down have to get to
love and I'm thinking if we could
quantify love on a term it means
different things to everybody and
rightly so but can we get to that
frequency and if you look at the sesia
notes you know the musical notes have
you I'm I'm I'm afraid I'm G to I'm
going to ask you to stop if you would
because I should I should go to another
question if you thank you very much okay
let's so you've been an educator through
the rise of the smartphone and my
question basically relates to
procrastination and task delay needless
task delay specifically and given the
unprecedented level of distraction that
we have in today's world I just wanted
to get your perspective from a
psychological standpoint on other than
cleaning your damn room what would you
suggest to a student who's looking to
overcome these
things well I think with any let's call
it addictive
process I mean email is powerfully
addictive right partly it's it's a slot
machine and and I mean that technically
so when you pull it's that's a variable
ratio reinforcement schedule if I
remember correctly and it's very
addictive
because if you pull on the slot machine
arm enough you will win and you never
know which pull will reward you and so
not only is that addictive it's very
hard to extinguish that and
so emails like that because there's
always something beckoning and now and
then it's a jackpot and social media is
like that because you know people are
posting interesting things and so well
how do you overcome an addictive process
and partly you do it by replacing it
with something
better right
so when people study drug and alcohol
use they they often make an elementary
mistake which is to try to figure out
why people use drugs and alcohol that's
that's not a smart thing to wonder we
know why people use cocaine cocaine
directly stimulates the systems that
produce positive emotion it's like so
there's no mystery there the mystery
with cocaine is very very simple why
don't people take cocaine all the time
until they die that's the mystery really
because you can get isolated rats to do
that so and and for some people alcohol
has the same kind of effect except it's
mediated by op
but often what people have to do to get
themselves out of an addictive process
is to find something better to do to
replace it and so I would say the
problem with the gadgets and I mean
they're amazing things is that they
interfere with they approximately
interfere with medium to long-term goals
I would say and so I think the first
thing you have to do to bring them under
control is figure out what it is that
their use is interfering with it has to
be something important right so you
think well I I I want want to do
something important what is that well
could be personal maybe you want to have
a relationship you want to get married
you want to have kids you want to have a
career that's meaningful you know you
want to have a life you you want to have
an abrahamic adventure and be the father
of Nations let's say well you can't be
ratting away on your cell phone and
doing that and so I think I think part
of it is to set your sights high and and
make a plan and figure out who you could
be and see if obsessive you utilization
of smartphone fits into that vision of
nobility and it will partly because
they're they're unbelievably powerful
communication devices but so so often
it's it's for lack of something better
to do and it also interferes so that's
about the best I can do with
that hello Dr Peterson so uh you've been
um you you've been talking with some of
the conservative uh candidates for
leadership this year um I know you
talked with most all of them right not
all of them but a number of them you you
talked with Andrew though right yes I
did yeah so um so something very
interesting uh popped up in my Facebook
feed so it was a ad for the conservative
party and um it was suggesting that we
uh cut you cut uh funding to public
universities that don't support free
speech and yeah that was probably my
fault yeah see precisely because because
this is something you say in some of
your Wilder moments you suggest that we
should cut the universities funding by
25% and let them battle it out for the
remains and he's taken that to you know
his his platform but now what you're
doing is uh well you're well one of the
things you're doing is you've created
this website um that identifies uh the
postmodern lexicon and helps people um
uh distinguish between uh postmodern
courses and not and so people don't take
them um or take them if they want yeah
yeah so that's it's it'd be interesting
to know like what sort of malevolent
postmodernists just study you
meticulously and try to use all your uh
knowledge of it anyway so but but what
you've said though you said that um what
we need to do is starve it out from the
source yeah okay so I yeah that look so
yeah I do I know where you're going so
about two weeks ago 3 weeks ago I went
up to Northern saskat and my parents
have a cottage up there it's way the
hell out in the middle of nowhere and uh
there's no cell phone although we do
have internet now which is you know
probably bad and good but anyways I got
to take a bit of a break which was good
because I haven't really been able to
think because you know more broadly
about say what I'm doing because who the
hell I don't know what the hell I'm
doing exactly this is a this is all very
strange and but but one thing I thought
about I was out on the lake I was
canoeing around and I I thought I'd
thought about war you know because I was
very irritated I'm very irritated about
what's happened to the
universities and there's a hint of
malevolence about it and I I'm not a fan
of ideological possession and I've been
set back up on my heels a lot over the
last eight months by the the onslaught
of what emerged when I said that there
was words I wouldn't say
and so it's put me into a defensive
posture let's say and I had been
thinking in terms of War metaphors you
know
like this is a Battleground and that
there's a war going on an ideological
war and I do believe that that's true
but then I was reading and I I did this
partly for this course I was reading The
Sermon on the Mount and one of the
things it says is resist not evil and I
don't know what to make of that line and
so I was talking to a bunch of people
about it reading about it a lot and
trying to figure out what it meant and
partly what it means is don't waste time
right because when you're fighting
against something then there's something
else you're not doing and then I thought
also when I was out there on the lake I
thought well do I really want to be in a
war because War that's not that's
not that's not uh that's not heaven
that's for sure it's really stressful
and people get hurt
and so I thought well maybe that's just
the wrong way of thinking about it even
though there's a Battleground issue here
and I thought well wait a second maybe
maybe the right thing to do in a
situation like this and this is maybe
something that those on the alt right
might consider is
that you the right thing to do maybe is
to outline A Better
Way rather than go out directly on the
attack now that might be seem somewhat
at odds with my idea of the website and
perhaps it is somewhat at odds with that
I'm I'm not sure about that but what I'm
trying to do instead of conducting this
like a war let's say is to conduct it
like a movement towards something better
and and that would be better now with
regards to cutting the University's
funding I thought about that too and I
thought wait a second that's not going
to work out because it's inviting
political interference into higher
education now the political interference
might be of the counterbalancing because
the evidence that the humanities in
particular have tilted almost 100% to
the left is overwhelming and so maybe
some counterbalance from the right would
set things more towards the middle but
the problem is is when you open up the
door to political interference with
higher education content you can't close
the door again and so on reflection I
thought that it probably was a
suboptimal idea and that would be better
instead was to and what this is what I
want to do when I launched the website I
want to ask students the students who
will be using it's like what do you want
from University CU here's here's your
options you can you can come out
ideologically possessed right you can
buy this Doctrine this pathological
Doctrine and you can become bitter and
resentful and you won't learn to
communicate properly and you won't read
the great works of civilization and you
won't learn to think and write you it
won't become Noble in body and
spirit is that what you want or do you
want the opposite do you want a real
education and and then I want to explain
what that means like I did tonight to
some degree you know that there's
absolute value in learning how to put
yourself together and to communicate and
to familiarize yourself with with with
the classic works of civilization and I
want to offer that I want to do what I
can to offer that as the proper
alternative instead of staying ins
sconed in this notion of a battle which
is just I just don't think it's the
right metaphor so I don't either and Dr
Peterson I just want to say that I think
what you're doing is absolutely
miraculous it helps change my life and
I'm sure at least raise your hand if Dr
Peterson has helped change your
life so for the better or for the
worse ask him to look at it well it's
about it's about 40 people maybe and
that's miraculous you know and I think
and and your thinking is going to be
it's going to be it's going to be all
over the place in the Canadian election
into years and I think that God that's a
horrible thing to contemplate you you to
watch out for it buddy and you need and
and and there's there's going to be a
lot of talk about how um how how uh
Andrew Shear's uh political message is
going to stem from yours and I think
it's really important that he he doesn't
censor himself like other conservative
politicians are doing and and because I
don't know we we we need to unite under
a a valid thoughtful articulate
conservative voice and what do we have
now we have we have Trump that's what's
you know we we we don't have any we
don't have any strong articulate male
voices in our in our um in our political
discourse right now that's what it feels
it's definitely time for you to develop
one so looks like you're on the right
path hello hello Dr Peterson uh thank
you for everything you've done this past
year and I do mean everything the
political stuff the this lecture Series
going to get you to move just yes great
belt it out man okay so uh I'll try to
be succinct I have I have two comments
and one question okay my first comment
is you mentioned how you were prevented
from uploading your YouTube video uh
from last week yeah um I actually attend
that lecture and I make pretty detailed
notes so if you want maybe I can email
you it's okay I've got it it's my
account's reinstalled rein stored rein
stored restored yeah and so it's okay
it's okay it's it's straightened out and
I'm going to upload all the videos to a
bunch of other sites and so this isn't
going to happen again so but I
appreciate that I actually miss some
lectures and I do want to look at them
online uh my second comment is about um
um sort of kind of going into the
commentaries of Christian theologist
over over the centuries uh like you've
done yourself um I just would like to
encourage everybody to also look at not
just Western Christianity but also
Eastern Christianity like the Orthodox
writings uh there's a big difference
between the two and that that the
Western sort of theology comes out of
the Roman uh uh Roman law Roman justice
so there's a lot more of an emphasis on
kind of justice and Christ came he died
on the cross for our sin so there's that
kind of like legal uh payback you know
what I mean right whereas the Eastern
the Eastern theology is a lot more
um like it it focuses a lot more on love
and on sort of the uh the positive
aspects and if you do read like the
first four centuries of Christianity
where there was no Schism uh there's
very little mention of like a sort of uh
legalistic framework it's a lot more I
don't know a pric or more um heartfelt I
guess so I think it's important that we
also in the west look at the Eastern
counterpart um especially more so now
because I I do perceive a lot of fake
love as being at the center of this
malevolence that you mentioned so like
you know this whole thing about um
demonizing the opposition saying that
they're they hard they have no love this
and that I perceive that as a lot of
fake love um and I think that we have to
keep in mind what true love is sometimes
it looks ugly like in dealing with
psychiatric patients maybe like other
countries are not as liberal as Canada
but they get results a lot more often
you don't say as many psychiatric
patients on on the road for example in
Greece where I'm from so yeah that was
kind of my comment that we need to focus
a lot more on what real love is I think
and not just the uh the kind of love
that you can put on a scale cuz I I
don't think that you can put love on a
scale so I've been talking as some of
you know to this guy Jonathan Paso who's
a an orthodox Carver and he started a
YouTube channel and he's talking a lot
about Orthodox issues and I'm pretty
ignorant when it comes to Orthodox
Christianity um but from what I
understand of it so far there's plenty
to be learned so yeah I I'm Orthodox
myself uh I just recently came back to
my faith two years ago um basically that
was the original Christianity then there
was a Schism of 1 54 between East and
West because of the uh uh the conflicts
that these new Christian Christians have
with a pope and then after that you also
had theism intern within the West
between Catholicism and and the
Protestants so that's kind of like the
big difference that Christianity
actually actually came from the East so
I think that's why it's important that
we look at the most ancient tags because
those were the ones that were closest to
the original message um so not to my
question
um it's about atheism
um you might hear a lot of times people
criticizing uh anybody that has any sort
of belief in in a deity or a god um that
uh you're just somebody that has an
imaginary friend um you know like the
the heavenly father that you have to uh
adhere to that you have no will of your
own so then I there's also like wouldn't
the cont argument be
that okay so if I have a good
relationship with my father and that's
why I'm more likely to accept a higher
deity than could it be that you as an a
IST um maybe you have conflict with your
father and that's why you're ad adverse
to kind of submitting to a higher being
that um that kind of dictates your life
well you're you're you're attempting a
psychoanalysis of atheism you know and
and there's many factors that go into
atheism um I would say that you could
make that case in some situations but
not in all um I do think though and I I
think this is perhaps where your
question is stemming from is that it's
no fluke that at the same time
that one of the consequences of the
death of God that n announced back in
the 1800s is the allout assault on
masculinity that's occurring in our
culture now and those things are
associated and I do think that does have
to do with a lack of faith in the
masculine spirit and that's a very bad
thing because well it's a bad thing for
everyone obviously because women have a
partially masculine spirit and they have
to put up with men and so to demolish
that or to fail to nurture it which is
certainly what's occurring is just a
pathway to Absolute disaster so
Y Peterson so this is the type of
question that you hate because it's in
the category of why why you believe what
you believe and uh it's a type of
question that uh makes you say I have it
right from the last time quote what the
hell makes you think it's any of your
business so I'm going to try to try to
frame it properly okay and I'm asking
this at lecture 10 of 12 and after
having listened to quite a few hours of
you here and elsewhere okay and in so in
your second interview with transliminal
media you lay out a few things I have
some quotes here I'll skip them for
brevity you get to the point where
you're discussing the embodiment of the
logos by Christ as a historical figure
and then you say quote is his
resurrection real did his body resurrect
I don't know in today's lecture you you
you alluded to the fact that there are
states of Consciousness that perhaps we
don't know how to access anymore and
let's say that I'm with you there let's
say I'm with the idea that there are
unknown there are unknown ways to get
intimations of the Divine that the
embodiment of the logos is associated
with physiological Transformations the
upper limits of which are unknown and
that we might currently classify as
paranormal but to dumb it right back
down to my level I'm asking about the
guy commonly depicted with long hair
nailed to a cross until de is a doorknob
and all of this goes to the heart of the
question of literalism and religious
interpretation it goes to the heart of
kind of you know what we're doing here
at this lecture series are we examining
the psychological significance of these
stories or are we entertaining the
possibility of these Fantastical events
I might be struggling with the concept
but I I haven't been able to square away
and reconcile those statements by you so
the question is on the on the question
of the resurrection of Christ why is
your answer to your own question I don't
know instead of at the very least
probably
not well you're definitely right about
me hating that
question well I call this series the
psychological significance of the
biblical stories for a reason you know
and the reason was
that
I'm harshly qualified to talk about such
things when I step outside of
that then I'm not where I should
be I don't think
that see I don't think that this is I'm
not going to get this right I can't get
the words exactly right this isn't about
what I believe personally it's partly
because I don't know what I believe I
don't know what I believe the world's a
very strange place I've had some very
strange experiences in
it I don't think it's helpful for me to
to step outside my my jurisdiction and
speculate
precisely the easiest thing would be to
say I think I said what I had to say
today I don't think that we know what
the up ER limits of human possibility
are I don't know what that means
metaphysically what I do understand from
the gospels is that even the accounts of
Christ's Resurrection are complex and
difficult to
understand I think from Reading yung in
large part that you can make a very
strong case for the symbolic meaning of
the death and Resurrection I think it
does stand for the capacity of the human
logos to die and resurrect continually
as it stries
upward I'm not willing to say that
that's all it means because I don't know
what everything means and I don't know
about the fundamental metaphysics of
being like I do believe that it's
accurate to construe being as a
Battleground between good and evil I
believe that I believe that is the most
accurate way of representing being it's
not the most accurate way of
representing the objective world that's
not the same thing being is that set of
experiences which we inhabit and that's
only partly objective and it's not
obviously reducible to the material not
in any straightforward way because we
don't understand the material substrate
of being at all you know it's it's and
when we do attempt to understand it say
at the quantum level we run into
Mysteries that that baffle the most the
most intelligent of us and aware so I'm
going to have to leave the question
hanging but partly because partly
because I don't know what I think but
partly
because there has to be a line between
what I believe and what what I can
communicate you know what you believe is
Beyond Your Capacity to articulate if
you the most at the deepest levels of
belief and I can only share with you
what I have actually come to understand
and there's things that I don't
understand and that's definitely one of
them I don't know how to draw a line
between the symbolic significance of the
biblical events say the symbolic and
psychological significance of the
biblical events and the metaphysics
that's underneath them and I think you
see the same thing in Yung because when
Yung writes technically and formally he
never talks about God he always talks
about the image of God which is not the
same thing the image of God would be
your subjective experience of God it
says nothing about the objective reality
of God because your subjective
experience can't say much about
objective reality but even in Yung you
get this mix you know sometimes it's
psychological but then he he makes a
metaphysical move and I think that
reflected also his the limits of his
knowledge because Yong had profound
revelatory experiences he was a very
strange person you know and I I
think so I think what's best for me is
to stay on the ground that I'm competent
on and to say what I can say about the
psychology and to reach beyond that
brief briefly when it's necessary but
other than that to leave it to hell
alone till I understand it better
assuming that I ever do so
than so uh because of these lectures
I've been reading the Bible and well I'm
obviously not finished but I'm fairly
familiar with uh with how it goes and uh
I've been thinking about two parts of it
in specific which is the story of Isaac
and the the crucifixion of Christ and
particularly one of the things that that
uh Christ says on the cross which is uh
my God my God why have you forsaken me
and I've been trying to understand that
because that's one hell of a thing for
the Son of God to say and you think that
would have been edited out yeah no
seriously it's like why isn't that gone
you know it it it it's it's very
inconvenient yeah and
in well we hav you haven't touched on
the story of Isaac yet but there's this
thing the called typ ology which I'm
sure you're aware of but basically the
idea that what's going on in the Old
Testament is sort of the laying out of
types for Christ and that Isaac is
essentially a type of Christ because
they have all these
similarities and so I've been thinking
about it in that context and thinking
about the parallels between them between
Isaac and Christ and one of the things
that also struck me was mostly the
differences between Isaac and Christ and
the main difference it seems to me is
sort of a difference in direction of
sacrifice so the sacrifice is of Abraham
is Abraham sacrificing his son to God
and then the S the sacrifice of Jesus Is
God sacrificing his son to Mankind and
I've been trying to understand basically
how that works and in relation to the uh
you and Western Civilization for 2,000
years yeah well there is these
transformations of sacrifice right that
can so the next thing that happens in in
these stories is that the circumcision
circumcision starts to come in as a
sacrifice and it seems to be something
like the beginnings of replacement for
sacrifice of animals it's you know
there's this this psychologization of
sacrifice so first it's pure external
enacted out and then it becomes
something that's more conceptual like it
becomes embodied in the form of the
circumcision and then it becomes more
conceptual and that conceptual
transformation keeps occurring and and
it seems to well it culminates to some
degree in this idea of the sacrifice of
Christ who's who's God sacrificing his
son to mankind but the sacrifice is much
more complex than that right it's also
Christ sacrificing himself to God and
and I think the the the issue there is
something
like well let's say You're supposed to
offer up the best that you have to God
that's the sacrifice that's what happens
with the high quality animals that that
able sacrifices okay but there's
something better than the best that you
own well what's that well part of it
might be well the relationships you have
with people are you willing to sacrifice
them to pursue the highest good well
then are you willing to sacrifice
yourself or your son like your son might
be that's a tough one I can understand
the idea of sacrificing yourself better
I'm still wrestling with this story of
Isaiah obviously because that's such a
complicated story and I do think it's
reasonable to think about it as a form
of foreshadowing at least the way the
Bible is set up of course people who
aren't Christian wouldn't agree with
that but that that's fine
um the idea that you would offer
yourself as a sacrifice to God that that
seems to me to follow quite logically
because well obviously you have nothing
greater to give than the best of
yourself right so you sacrifice yourself
to the highest good and that's part of
the man that's part of the way in which
humanity is redeemed that makes sense to
me that just seems like for me that's
that's a pretty straightforward
psychological truth the sun issue that's
that's a lot tougher thing to wrestle
with because one of the things I was
thinking with the uh with what Jesus
says on the cross is that one of the
interpretations of that uh is basically
that Jesus in that moment is human
basically he not this not not Divine
it's just Jesus the human right but that
always kind of felt a little bit like
avoiding the question to me because you
can't just posit something like the
Trinity and then say Oh but in this
moment that doesn't go right that
doesn't count so but if if we think
about it in that way of like the
difference in the direction of sacrifice
and it seems to me that in the sacrifice
whoever is making the sacrifice sort of
aims toward something so Abraham is sort
of reaching for the Divine when he
sacrifices when he's going to sacrifice
his son and so that would mean maybe God
is reaching toward the human and so that
would make some sense of that
interpretation that Christ is only human
in that moment right that that it's the
sacrific is accomplished and the
reaching down is accomplished but I'm
still up to the question what do I make
of that because that's one inter well I
mean it's useful to have a problem like
that because it gives you something to
think about right and something to study
further and it's it's it's a it's a
major it's a major problem I mean the
whole issue of well we could say well
what's the relationship between the
Divine and the human which is obviously
brought to the Forefront in the idea of
Christ right but it's a personal issue
because part of the issue is what's the
relationship between you as a finite
entity and the Transcendent Infinity
that surrounds you well there's some
relationship because here you are and
the Transcendent Infinity around you
exists so there's a relationship the
question is what is the relationship and
and we don't know that and and and it's
dramatized in that story and so I mean
partly the the the reason that there's
so much conflict and confusion in that
story is because it's trying to bring
opposing things together right how can
something be God and man at the same
time it's just like the genie which is
the root word of Genius by the way the
genie is this incredibly powerful force
that can grant wishes right but it's
constrained in this tiny little space
there's an intimation there that for
something to be real it has to straddle
The Divide between the finite and the
infinite and that's what human beings do
I think to some degree and that's
dramatized in that story but it doesn't
mean that we understand it I mean you
know that sometimes you're going to feel
that way when you're called upon to make
a sacrifice you're going to feel that
you've been betrayed by everything and I
mean the story is set up that way right
Christ is betrayed by tyranny he's
betrayed by his best friends he's
betrayed by his mortality like that's
it's an archetypal story because and
he's innocent so the story can't be any
worse that's why it's archetypal and I
mean the story says to to some degree
that under such conditions even God
himself would have doubts it's something
like that and that's a real that's a
powerful idea it's it's a very powerful
idea so that's the best I can make out
of that for
[Applause]
now we have to stop so we'll so convene
again in a week thank you very much
[Applause]