[Music]
thank you so I look today and these
lectures have now been watched by
they've been viewed a million times so
that's pretty amazing freely or they've
been they've been glanced at a million
times that's right that's also possible
all right so well let's get right into
it so last week I think was mostly
remarkable for the absolute dearth of
content that was actually biblically
related so that was I'll just recap what
I laid out and so that it sets the frame
properly for what we're going to discuss
tonight and I presented you with an
elaborated description of of this
diagram essentially which I spent quite
a lot of time formulating probably about
25 years ago I guess which kind of
accounts for its graphic primitiveness I
suppose I was really pushing the limits
of my 486 computer to produce that I can
tell you so and it's it's it's a it's a
description representation of the
archetypal circumstances of life and and
the archetypical circumstances are the
circumstances that are true under all
conditions for all time and so you can
think about them as descriptively
characteristic of the nature of human
experience that's not exactly the same
as the nature of reality but because you
can you can divide reality into its
subject of an object of elements and and
there's utility in doing that but
these sorts of representations don't
play that game that they consider human
experience as constituted constitutive
of reality and that's how we experience
it and so we'll just go with that the
idea basically is is that we always
exist inside a damaged structure and
that structure is partly biological and
it's it's partly socio-cultural it's
partly what's been handed to us by our
by our ancestors both practically in
terms of infrastructure but also
psychologically in terms of the active
learned content of our of our psyches
and so that would include for example
our ability to utilize language and the
words that we use and the phrases that
we use and the mutual understanding that
we develop as a consequence of
interacting with each other architect
Lee speaking that structures always it's
always dead and corrupt and the reason
it's dead is because it was made by
people who are dead and the reason it's
corrupt is because things fall apart of
their own accord and the fact that
people don't aim properly let's say
speeds along that process of
degeneration and so what that means and
I think this is something worth knowing
maybe I'll try standing back here and
see if that problem goes away what that
means is that young people always have a
reason to be upset and cynical about the
current state of affairs and and it's
that way forever and so it's useful I
think to consider such considerations
sort of such conceptualizations of the
pair of the as the patriarchy in that
light because it's an archetypal truth
that the social structure is corrupt and
incomplete and and what that means is
that it's something that you have to
contend with every moment in some sense
of your life it's a it's a permanent
fact of existence and to be upset that
the
structures of social structures or even
the biological structures within which
we live are incomplete and imperfect is
to and to take that personally that
that's the worst part of it to take that
person out personally is a misreading of
the existential condition of humankind
because it's always the case that what
you have been given and what you live in
is degenerate and corrupt and in need of
repair and it's easier just to accept
that because there's also a positive
development and the pause development as
well you've been granted something
rather than nothing and maybe you
haven't been granted pure hell because
especially in a culture like ours where
many things actually function quite well
so there's room for gratitude there even
if it's a broken machine it's not one
that's completely devastated and it's
not absolutely hell-bent at every second
on your misery and destruction and it
easily could be because many societies
are like that and so the fact that we
happen to live in one that isn't corrupt
beyond imagining is something to be
eternally grateful for well so we live
inside a damaged structure and we also
bear responsibility for that damage
because we don't do everything we can to
constantly repair it and you might say
well that's actually one of the
fundamental you know people say well
what's the meaning of life what they
really mean is what's the positive
meaning of life because as we've already
discussed the negative meanings of life
are more or less self-evident well the
positive meaning of life is to be found
in noting the state of lack of repair of
the of the walled city that you inhabit
and then sallying forth to do something
about that to repair the breaches and to
fix up the walls and to make the
structure that you inhabit as secure and
as productive as it possibly can be and
there's no shortage of opportunities to
do that
you can do that in your own mind you can
do that in your own room you can do that
in your own household in your local
community
you and maybe if you get good at doing
it at all those levels then you can
start to look beyond that and so there's
challenges that's the thing that's kind
of interesting about this insufficient
structure is that it has a set of
challenges built into it because of its
insufficiency and perhaps even because
of its corrupt nature that calls forth
the potential response from you of
heroic adventure and the heroic
adventure is to man the barricades and
repair the city and you can always do
that it doesn't matter what's what your
personal circumstances are there's
always something that isn't right
near you isn't correct isn't laid out
properly that you could just fix if you
wanted to and one of the things that
we're going to talk about tonight is the
idea that if you adopt the attitude an
attitude that's like that that the rule
that you should play is to make things
better wherever you are however you can
that what would actually happen would be
that things would get better wherever
you are in all sorts of ways and that
we've really as a species you might say
or maybe even as singular individuals we
we've explored that rarely it isn't
something that's put forth as a
proposition that often and it's quite
surprising to me and you know I had an
interesting experience the other day I
went to the keg I go there because I
have food allergies and they're very
careful with people who have food
allergies and the waiter took me to the
table and he said that he had been
watching my lectures and that's a very
common experience and he was happy about
that and he said that he had two
promotions at the keg in the last four
months because he'd been watching my
lectures and like I really found that an
affecting experience because you know
you might say well he's working as a
waiter at the keg and there's nothing
particularly heroic about that and and I
disagree with that actually because I
don't care where you're located you can
do a hell of a job and I mean that
literally at whatever job you have you
can you can take whatever job you have
and you can make it a real nice little
piece of absolute misery or you can do
you can act like a civilized human being
and notice that no matter where you are
there's a there's a richness and a
complexity that's completely
inexhaustible right at hand and then you
can take that seriously and you can say
well I happen to be a waiter at the keg
and perhaps that's not what I expected
and he's a young guy and perhaps that
isn't where I want to end up but it's
not nothing that's a rich environment
and I can make it a lot better if I want
to I can get along properly with my
co-workers and not gossip behind their
back and I can treat my customers
properly and if an opportunity comes my
way I can take it and I can see what
happens and so he said that's what he
had started doing and that things were
working out much better for him he was
in a much better job than he was three
months ago in three months that's
nothing right I mean that's a nice
trajectory it's an uphill trajectory and
that's what you want really an uphill
trajectory is actually even better than
being somewhere good as far as I'm
concerned because one of the things that
really makes your life meaningful is the
clear realization that you're headed
somewhere better than you are now and
then it's even better if you also
understand that there's a direct causal
relationship between the things that
you're doing and the steepness of that
incline and so I get a lot of letters
from people like that and they're Marse
most frequently young men although not
always and they say well you know I've
been listening to these lectures and I
decided that I'm going to try to take
responsibility for my life and so I'm
I've started to stop doing all the
stupid things that I know that that are
stupid that I know I shouldn't be doing
and I've started doing some of the
things that aren't stupid that I know I
should be doing which seems pretty
obvious really if you think about it but
it's obvious though it may be that isn't
necessarily what people do and then they
write and say you can't believe what
difference that makes and they're
thrilled about it and so I'm thrilled
about it when I get letters like that
because I really don't experience
anything as better than a letter like
that or a message like that because it's
so good to see things that aren't so
good replaced by something better and I
really do think it's an open question I
truly believe it's an open question to
what degree we could make things better
if that's what we actually aimed at
doing you know in some of the stories
that we've we've come
already the story of Cain and Abel in
particular is really an analysis of that
problem which so remarkable it occurs so
so early in this document it's such a
such a foundational story and it
basically says well there's two modes of
being in the world right there's one
where you adopt the responsibility for
living properly for being properly and
you make the sacrifices necessary for
doing that and then everything will
flourish properly and the other one is a
pathway of resentment and bitterness and
rejection and murder and genocide and
that just seems exactly right to me and
so if the positive path beckons if you
can actually see what it is if you can
if you can lower yourself enough to see
what it is
young Carl Jung said once that modern
people didn't see God because they
didn't look low enough so phrase I
really really like because people
denigrate the opportunities that are
right in front of them and there's no
reason to do that because what's right
in front of you is the majesty of being
that's what's right in front of you it's
inexhaustibly complex and full of
potential and there's no reason to
assume that wherever you happen to be
isn't as good a starting place as
anywhere else now you know I know some
people have terrible terrible lives in
situations that are absolutely
unbearable and but I also do know that
even situations like that can be made a
hell of a lot worse by the bad by by the
worst kind of attitude that's for sure
so so anyway so that's where you are
you're in a damaged structure you're a
damaged structure you're in a damaged
structure but you know at least it's got
some walls you know you're not being fed
to the Lions on a regular basis so
that's a good thing and you can you can
emerge forward you know heroically
magically to confront the chaos that
constantly threatens the structure
within which you live and you can free
something as a consequence of that you
can learn something you can strengthen
yourself that's the other thing because
the way what you're actually made of in
many ways that what informs you what
you're made of is what you encounter
when you voluntarily encounter the
unknown and so the more you voluntarily
encounter the unknown the more you get
may
and the more you get made of the more
there is to you and then the more you're
good at encountering the unknown and
restructuring order and and calling
forth proper order out of the potential
of being and God you got to think why
wouldn't you do that since you can do
that and it's an endless mystery you
know I think part of it is that people
well it's also encapsulated to stump
some degree in the story of Adam and Eve
because what happens to Adam is when he
becomes self conscious right
he becomes ashamed of himself and
regards himself as a lowly sort of
creature and there's endless reasons why
people would do that because of course
we're rife with imperfection and so he
hides from God and I think that's
actually the answer to the conundrum
which is that people don't aspire to the
highest good because they're deeply
ashamed of themselves and their
weaknesses and their insufficiencies and
and so it's it's that's not the only
reason I mean there's the desire to
avoid responsibility and there's all the
negative motivations as well like
resentment and and and hatred and the
desire to make things worse I don't want
to you know give us a give us too much
of a break but but it's something like
that but it's okay then to not be in a
very good place if what you're trying to
do with that not very good place is make
it better and one of the things I really
have learned as a clinical psychologist
is that you just cannot believe how
powerful incremental progress is you
could you can do the calculations like
it's like compound interest you know if
you make your life a tenth of a percent
better a week man in two or three years
you're in such a better place than you
were that it isn't even like the same
domain and if you keep that up for ten
years or twenty years you know
especially if you're young and you start
early you start to straighten yourself
out and and fix the things that you can
fix you can transform your lives in ways
that are completely unimaginable and god
only knows what the upper limit of that
is in terms of human possibility because
we are amazing creatures you know when
we really get our act together and stop
running at 10% of our capacity you know
so so so that's what you do you've got
you know the fact that things aren't
exactly the way they should be at least
gives you something to do
ooh you know and that's that's and and
and maybe something great to do because
there's no shortage of suffering in
trouble that'd be sets the world that
you could conceivably ameliorate in some
way and the utility and meaning the
utility of that and the intrinsic
meaning of that is self-evident so it
also makes me curious about nihilism for
example and despair because I mean I
understand those emotions I understand
them deeply and the intellectual mindset
that goes along with it but they just
seem beside the point to me in some
sense because there are so many things
that need doing that all you really have
to do is open your eyes and look at them
and then decide that you're actually
going to do something about them and you
might think well what's within my scope
of influence is so trivial that it's not
worth doing it's like it won't stay
trivial for long if you do it
not at all and I don't think it's
trivial to begin with I don't think that
any I really don't believe that anything
done right is trivial and my experience
in my life has been that anything I
actually did paid off it didn't pay off
necessarily in the way that I expected
it to pay off that's a whole different
story but if it was genuine commitment
to do something even if it went sideways
and the outcome was really something
other than what I expected
the net consequence over time was
nothing but good so every new frontier
that can be conquered is an advance
forward and there's no shortage of
frontier because we're surrounded by the
unknown we're surrounded by our own
ignorance and we can continually move
into that domain into the domain of
chaos or we can restructure pathological
order and that's that's the secret to
proper being and so then you encounter
chaos that way you know and then you can
regard yourself as the sort of entity
that despite its insufficiency has the
capability to conquer chaos despite the
danger of that that's the other thing
because the fact that you're fragile is
actually a precondition for your heroism
because if you weren't fragile then
there'd be nothing heroic about doing
something difficult right because if you
couldn't be hurt or damaged or defeated
or or end up in failure then where's the
where's the moral courage in the
endeavor it has to be that the
agility is built into the courage and so
it's not it's not a reason not to engage
in it at all in fact quite the contrary
and so well and so then you know what do
you do well you put the city back
together and maybe the way you want it
so that it's functional and efficient
and beautiful and so the people can
flourish there and and and flourish in a
manner that makes them like it makes
them what would you say that makes them
feel that the unbearable catastrophe of
being is worth it for the experience
that's what you're aiming at and it's
not an impossibility it's not an
impossibility and then not only that not
only do you repair the city when you do
that but you make yourself the sort of
thing that continually repairs the city
and that's even better that's the end
goal because it's not the repair of the
city that's the goal it's the
transformation of yourself into the
thing that continually repairs the city
and so there's just no reason for that
not to happen and the more it can happen
the better well there's a there's an
undercurrent to this story and that is
also the story of the flood and that's
the fact that you know the city can
become corrupt because people don't
engage in heroic endeavor or perhaps
because they engage in precisely the
opposite of that which is outright
destructive behavior and this is also
something that's worth considering too
because if you if you if you consider
your your own manner of being you know
you can say things to people like tell
tell the truth and be good and those
aren't those are cliches obviously and
so they lack power because they're
cliches but you can take them apart and
utilize them in a manner that stops
being a cliche and you do that by being
more humble about them I would say
because maybe you can't tell the truth
because you don't know what the truth is
but one thing you can do is you can stop
saying things that you know to be untrue
and you might say well how do I know
that they're untrue and the answer to
that is well you need a whole philosophy
of truth
the elaboration of an entire philosophy
of truth to answer that question and so
we're not going to bother answering that
question because in some sense at the
moment it's beside the point that isn't
the issue the issue is there are times
in your life where you know that the
thing that you're saying is not true
it's a deception it's a lie of some sort
and you're using it to manipulate
yourself or another person or the world
and you're also possessed fully
possessed of the idea that you can get
away with it and there's a satanic
arrogance about that in fact that is the
archetypal arrogance that's portrayed in
the mythological character of Satan
because Satan is precisely the archetype
of the element of the mind that believes
that it can twist and and bend the
structure reality without paying the
price for that and you can't imagine
anything that's more arrogant than not
because really do you really think that
you can twist the structure of a reality
and that that's going to work out for
you without it snapping back it's so
obvious that that can't work that that
everyone knows it but anyways back to
the initial point is that you know by
the rules of the game that you yourself
are playing that some of the times
you're violating the rules of the game
that you're playing and the first issue
with regards to say stating the truth or
behaving in a responsible manner would
be merely stopped cheating at whatever
game it is that you've chosen to play
that's a good start and that'll
straighten that will straighten out your
life it'll start in the straight and
start to straighten out your life and so
well the flood what the hell does the
flood tie into this well you know we
live in a corrupt structure we're
corrupt as individuals we live in a
corrupt structure and part of that
corruption has just happenstance it's
the way things fall apart but the other
part of it is that not only are we not
aiming up we're actually aiming down and
the flood story is a warning and it's a
very clear warning and the warning is if
you aim down enough and then if enough
of you aim down at the same time
everything will degenerate into
something that's indistinguishable from
the chaos from which things emerged at
the beginning of time it's something
like that because the
the cosmos that's presented in
mythological representations is chaos
versus order right the order is on top
you might say and the chaos is always
underneath and the chaos can break
through or the order can crumble and you
can fall into the chaos and that chaos
is intermingle intermingled potential
and the way that you destroy the order
and let the chaos rise back up which is
exactly how its portrayed in the flood
story is by well by inhabiting the
corpse of your father that's one
mythological motif and feeding on the
remains and with no gratitude and no
attempt to replenish what it is that
you're taking from and the warning in
the flood story is don't do that for
very long because things will happen
that are so awful you cannot possibly
imagine it and that will happen to you
personally and it'll happen to your
family and it will happen to your
community and it's happened to people
over and over throughout history and
it's quite interesting you know it's
very soon after the story of Cain and
Abel when you see evil enter the world
in the story of Adam and Eve
along with self-consciousness and evil
there is the ability that's the
knowledge of good and evil that's the
ability to hurt other people
self-consciously to know what you're
doing and then of course instantly Cain
takes that to the absolute extreme and
he uses that capacity to to destroy
really what he loves best he gets as
close as a human being can to destroying
the divine ideal because of course his
brother is able and Abel is favored by
God and Cain destroys them which Cain
tells God at the end of that episode
that his punishment is more than he can
bear and I think the reason for that is
where are you once you destroy your own
ideal what's left for you there's
nowhere to go there's no up and when
there's no up there's a lot of down and
you know there's an idea that was put
forth very nicely in Milton's Paradise
Lost when he was describing from a
psychological perspective essentially
what hell is and hell is you're in hell
to the degree that you're distant from
the good that that might be a good way
of thinking about it and if you destroy
your own ideal which you do with
jealousy and resentment and and the
desire to pull down people who you would
like to be let's say then you end up in
a situation that's indistinguishable
from hell and the way the story the
biblical story unfolds as well it's it's
it's Cain and then it's the flood and so
Cain adopts this mode of being that's
antithetical to being itself at least a
positive being itself he does it
voluntarily does it knowing full well
what he's doing and the net consequence
of this that as it ripples through the
entire social structure is that God
stands back and says this whole thing is
God so bad the only thing we can do is
is wipe it to the ground and that is
that is no joke
that's exactly how things work and one
of the things that's extraordinarily
terrifying about that sequence of
stories and I believe this to be true I
think I realized this independently of
any of the analysis that I was doing of
mythological stories because I looked at
what happened in places like the Soviet
Union and Mao's China and in Nazi
Germany and the most penetrating
observers of those societies the people
who were most interested in how it was
that those absolute catastrophes came
about all said the same thing it was
rooted in the degeneration of the
individuals who made up the society you
know you hear what people will thought
were following orders it's like no that
that explanation doesn't hold water or
that you'd be punished if you resisted
well there is some truth in that but
nowhere near as much as people might
think especially at the beginnings of
the process more it was that people
decided each and every one of them to
turn a blind eye to the catastrophes and
to participate in the lies and that
warped the entire societies and they
went as you know they they feared their
way downward to something as closely
approximating hell as you could hope to
manage especially in places like Nazi
Germany and well in all three of those
places and in Mao is China and in the
Soviet Union and so the thing that's so
frightening about one of the things
that's so frightening about the stories
in Genesis is they say something very
clear which is that your moral
degeneration contributes in no small way
to the degeneration of the entire cosmos
you say well I would like my life to be
meaningful
people say that really would you really
you really would like your life to be
meaningful you think maybe people would
made a little nihilism to not have to
face that particular realization and I
think people do that all the time it's a
terrible way to to to realize but we are
networked together in that that's the
price of or let's say that's the
vulnerability that's associated with our
intense capacity to communicate and it
is certainly possible that the ripples
of our individual actions have
consequences that are far beyond the
limits of our immediate consciousness
and I also think people know that too
they know that in the way that people
know things when they don't want to know
them which means they know them embodied
they can feel them they can sense them
they have an emotional response to them
but there's no damn way they're going to
let them become articulate because they
don't want to know and when you're
feeling guilty and ashamed about the
things you've done or not done and I
know that can get out of hand as well
it's often because there is a crooked
little part of you that's aiming at the
worst possible outcome you know one of
the things you said about the shadow you
know that young famous idea that
everyone has a dark side and that that
dark side needs to be incorporated and
made conscious young said the shadow of
the human being
reaches all the way to hell and he
actually that's the thing that's so
interesting about interesting about
reading Carl Jung is he actually means
what he says it's not a metaphor it's
like the part of you that's twisted
against being is aligned with the part
of the cosmos let's say the conscious
cosmos that's aiming at making
everything as terrible as it can
possibly be and you know it's a terrible
shock to realize that it's partly why
people don't realize that it's it's
something that people keep at an arm's
length it's it's the same as recognizing
yourself as a Nazi concentration camp
camp guard which is a very useful
exercise because there's absolutely no
reason why you couldn't have been or
still could be one so and if you think
otherwise then all the more reason for
assuming that you would be unable to
resist the temptation if it was in fact
offered to you and if you don't think
it's a temptation then the then there's
so much that you don't know about human
beings that
you're not even in the game because if
it wasn't a temptation then people
bloody well wouldn't have done it and
plenty of people did it and it's no
wonder so so things get serious in
Genesis very very rapidly and and the
depth of the seriousness is ultimate
archetypal that's it gets as serious as
it can get the story of Noah and the
flood opens in a fragmentary manner and
I believe that these passages are part
of a longer story that we only have bits
and pieces of and an also one that's
fragmented in its in its it its parts of
more than one story and it starts like
this it came to pass when men began to
multiply on the face of the earth and
and and daughters were born unto them
that the sons of God saw the daughters
of men that they were fair and they took
them wives of all which they chose now
there's an idea there there's two ways
of looking at the past and you can kind
of see that in the political landscape
that we inhabit now on the more
conservative end of the spectrum people
regard the past as the land of giants
right there were the heroes of the past
who established the current conditions
that we exist in and then the people on
the left are more concerned perhaps with
the what would you call it with a
lineage of corruption that's come down
through the centuries and both of those
perspectives are accurate you can say
well there were there there were the
great heroes of the past who established
our modes of being you can think of them
as composite beings if you want that's
fine that's a perfectly reasonable way
of thinking about it and you can also
think of the of the accumulation of
corruption and evil that's come along
the centuries as well and so you see
both of those reflected in these initial
few lines that the sons of gods so those
are the hero's saw the daughters of men
that they were fair and they took them
wives of all of which they chose then
this statement comes in
and somewhat of a non sequitur and the
Lord said my spirit shall not always
strive with man for that he is also
flesh yet his days shall be a hundred
and twenty years and I looked at a
variety of interpretations of that line
because it doesn't seem to follow so
clearly from the previous line and
exactly what it means isn't obvious but
it seems to be the first line talks
about the heroes of the past and and the
second line says wait a second there's
something corrupt about the human mode
of being and one of the consequences of
that as far as God is concerned is that
there are conditions under which the
divine Spirit will not strive with man
what that means is there are conditions
under which let's say the I don't think
there's any other way of putting it is
the divine impulse towards the good will
abandon you because of things that
you've done and then the secondary
consideration here is that perhaps
because of the degeneration of people
it's not so obvious here that our life
spans are limited that the spirit that
inhabits us will only do so for a
limited amount of time and that's
tangled in a strange way in with the
idea of human moral culpability and
that's posed against the notion of the
Giants of the past and then it returns
to the giant idea the narrative returns
to the giant idea and reads there were
giants in the earth in those days and
also after that when the sons of men
came in unto the daughters of men and
they bare children to them and the same
became mighty men which were of old men
of renown and that's the end of that
sequence of fragments it's it's very
broken but you can see a dual narrative
underneath it and and one of the
narratives is that there's the kind of
corruption despite the joy the nature of
the Giants of the past there's the kind
of corruption lurking that would cause
God to with hold his grace and allow men
to deteriorate and and that sets the
stage for Noah and the flood and God saw
that the wickedness of man was great in
the earth and that the
and that every imagination of the
thoughts of his heart was only evil
continually you know one of the things I
really didn't like about going to church
when I was a kid I went to a pretty
moderate church it was the United Church
which has hardly even become a church
now it's so moderate so to speak one of
the things I didn't like was the
constant harping by the Ministry on the
sinful nature of human beings like it
didn't speak to me properly partly
because I really didn't understand what
it meant and partly because it seemed
well sort of what would you say was
self-flagellating in an unattractive way
I don't know if there is an attractive
way to be self-flagellating but it was
it was and there was something about it
there was also wrote and and faked that
I didn't like but you know in later
years I thought about that more and I
started to understand that there was
some real utility in asking people to
keep the evil that they're doing clear
and conscious in the forefront of their
imagination I think I mentioned to you
guys last week this little episode from
what we know of Mesopotamian culture
surrounding the emperor the new year's
festival they would take the emperor
outside of the walled city and strip him
of his garb so that he was reduced to
just an ordinary man and then humiliate
him richly and then ask him how it was
over the last year that he wasn't a
spectacular embodiment of Marduk and
Marduk was the Mesopotamian deity who
made order out of chaos essentially and
the emperor was supposed to sit and
think okay well you know I'm Emperor and
everything I should be doing a good job
maybe I should even be doing a great job
and probably I'm coming up short in a
bunch of ways and that actually happens
to be important since I'm running the
entire show I should be very very
cognizant of how I'm failing to live up
to the ideal and that is what that call
that constant clarion call that's
degenerated I would say an institutional
Christianity that was actually the idea
was
look there's a bunch of ways that you're
not being everything you could be and it
is not supposed to be a whip to knock
you down although maybe it's a whip to
knock down your pride the pride that
stops you from being aware of your
insufficiencies it's more like a call to
the opposite it's like well you should
stop doing those things because you
could be so much more than you are and
that would be so much better for you and
everyone else that it's just it's just
not good that you continue doing these
things continue breaking your own rules
let's say because we could certainly as
I said we can start this game by
assuming that you should at least play
the game that you're playing straight
and so and it is the case that if you
watch yourself it's a terrifying thing
to do but if you watch yourself you'll
see you lie a lot like when I learned
this to begin with I was in my 20s and I
was I'm a smart person and I was very
proud of that because I was also a small
person I was moved ahead one year in
school and I was a small person to begin
with and so I was a very small person in
my classes and also very mouthy which
might not come as much of a surprise and
somewhat provocative and so you know and
I got pushed around a fair bit because P
everybody gets pushed around and my
weapon was to be mouthy and it was a
fairly effective weapon although it
tended to backfire because you know if
you're really effectively mouthy with
large obnoxious people then they tend to
respond in a relatively negative
physical way and so that sort of thing
was happening to me a fair bit and but I
was quite I was quite proud of the fact
that I was that I I was I had some
intellectual power and that it was then
in my 20s when I learned about some of
the danger of that because I started to
read partly Milton's Paradise Lost and I
started to understand the the danger of
the intellect and the danger of the
intellect as far as I can tell is that
it tends towards pride and arrogance and
it also tends to fall in love with its
own productions and so that's actually
Lucifer in Paradise Lost absolu suffer
Lucifer is the intellect that falls in
love with its own productions and then
assumes that there's not
outside of what it thinks that's the
totalitarian mentality right it's like
we have a total system and we know how
everything works and we're going to
implement it and that'll bring about
heaven on earth right that's that's a
that that's the totalitarian mindset and
that's associated with intellectual
arrogance and another at the same time
another thing what was happening to me
so I was noticing that I started to
understand what that meant and I also
started to understand that there was
more to life than the intellect much
more if I smoke too much and I drank too
much and I weighed like 130 pounds I
wasn't in good physical shape and like I
had a lot of things to do when I went to
graduate school to put myself together
and at the same time I was trying to
understand why things had gone so
crazily wrong with the world its
encapsulation in the Cold War and what
role I might be playing in that if any
or what role any of us were playing in
that at the same time I was working out
of prison only a little bit I worked
with this crazy psychologist he he is to
put jokes on his multiple-choice tests
he was a really eccentric guy but I
really liked his courses he and he
taught a course on creativity and he was
also a prison psychologist and he was an
eccentric guy and he for some reason
like me and maybe because I was
eccentric too and he invited me to go
out to the Edmonton maximum-security
prison with him a couple of times which
I did and that was a very interesting
experience because I was trying to
figure out what role each individual's
behavior bore to the pathology of the
group was something like that and I went
out there and I met a little guy smaller
than me I was a little bigger by then
and he was a pretty innocuous guy and
what had happened was I was out in this
gymnasium it looks like a high school
the prison which is really quite telling
in my estimation but and there were all
these like monsters in there
weightlifting and like they were
monsters I remember one guy who was
tattooed everywhere and he had like a
huge scar running down the middle of his
chest it looked like someone had to hit
him with an axe and
you know and and I was in there I had
this weird cape that I used to wear that
I bought in Portugal and some boots that
went along with it and yeah I was like
an 1890s Sherlock Holmes cape and it was
really like it was from the 1890s
because this little village was up on a
hill it was a walled city on a hill and
they sold these things and I don't think
they changed the style since 1890 and so
I thought they were really cool and so I
was wearing that which wasn't perhaps
the most conservative garb to dawn if
you're going to wear if you're going to
go to a maximum-security prison so
anyways I was in the gymnasium and the
car the psychologist left and god only
knows I mean that's what he was like and
all these guys came or all these guys
came around me you know and they were
offering to trade their prison clothes
for my tape and was it was like I was
being made an offer I couldn't refuse
you know and so I didn't I didn't really
know what to do and then this little guy
said something like that the
psychologist sent me to come and take
you away or something like that and so I
thought well better this little guy
banned all these monsters so we went
outside the gym through some doors like
school doors went outside the gym into
the exercise yard I guess and we were
wandering along and he was talking to me
and he seemed like a kind of an
innocuous guy and then the psychologist
showed up at the door and motioned us
back and so which was kind of a relief
and so I went into his office and he
said you know that guy that you walked
out in the yard with and I said yeah he
said he he took two cops one night and
he had them kneel down and while they
were begging for their lives he shot
them both in the back of the head and I
thought hmm
that's see the thing that was so
interesting was that he was so innocuous
right because what you'd hope is that
someone like that would be very much
unlike you let's say and certainly
wouldn't be like someone innocuous that
you'd met what you'd want is that the
guy would be like you know half were
wolf and half vampire so you could just
tell right away that he was a
cold-blooded killer but no he was this
sort of ineffectual little guy who
was certainly not ineffectual if you
gave him a revolver in the upper hand
and so so that made me think that made
me think a lot about the relationship
between being innocuous and and being
dangerous and then another thing
happened I met another guy out there and
then a week or two later I heard that he
and a friend of his had held another guy
down and pulverized his left leg with a
lead pipe like just pulverized it and
the reason for that was that they
thought that he was a snitch and maybe
he was and at that time I did something
different instead of being shocked and
horrified by that although I certainly
was I thought how in the world could you
do that because I didn't think I could
do that I didn't think that I thought
that there was a qualitative distinction
between me and those people and so I
spent about two weeks trying to see if I
could figure out under what conditions I
could do that like what kind of
psychological transformation I would
have to undergo to be able to do that
and so that was a meditative exercise
let's say and it only took about ten
days for me to realize that not only
could I do that it would be a hell of a
lot easier than I thought it would be
and that's sort of where that wall
between me and what being described as
the shadow started to fall apart and
that also was very useful because I
started to wreck I started to treat
myself as somewhat different entity
because I hadn't been aware up to that
point you know because I thought I was a
good guy and there's no reason for me to
think that because you're not a good guy
unless you've really made a bloody
effort to be a good guy
you're just not it's not easy and so
you're probably a moderately bad guy and
that's a long ways from being an
absolutely horrible guy but it's also a
long ways from being a good guy and so
but I had a little more respect for
myself after that because I also
understood that there was a monstrous
element to the human psyche that that
you needed to respect and that was part
of you that you should regard yourself
in some sense as a loaded weapon it's
very useful around children to regard
yourself as a loaded weapon because
around children you are a loaded weapon
and the terrible experiences that many
children have with their parents are
testament to that
anyways about the same time and and I
don't exactly know how these things were
causally related I guess it was because
I was trying to figure out who I was and
how that could be fixed something like
that I started to pay very careful
attention to what I was saying I don't
know if that happened voluntarily or
involuntarily but I could feel a sort of
split developing in my psyche and the
split and I've actually had students
tell me the same thing that has happened
to them after they've listened to some
of the material that that I've been
describing to all of you but it's split
into two let's say and one part was the
let's say the old me that was talking a
lot and that liked to argue and that
liked ideas and there was another part
that was watching that part like just
with its eyes open and neutrally judging
and the part that was neutrally judging
was watching the part that was talking
and going that isn't your idea you don't
really believe that you don't really
know what you're talking about that
isn't true and I thought that's really
interesting so now and that was
happening to like 95% of what I was
saying and so then I didn't really know
what to do I thought okay this is
strange so maybe I've fragmented and
that's just not a good thing at all I
mean it wasn't like I was hearing voices
or anything like that I mean it wasn't
like that it was it was well people have
multiple parts so then I had this weird
conundrum is like well which of those
two things are me is it the part that's
listening and saying no that's rubbish
that's a lie that's you're doing that to
impress people you're just trying to win
the argument you know without me or was
the part that was going about my normal
verbal business me and I didn't know but
I decided I would go with the critic and
then what I'd tried to do what I learned
to do I think was to stop saying things
that made me weak and now that I mean
I'm still trying to do that because I'm
always feeling when I talk
whether or not the words that I'm saying
are either making me align or making me
come apart and I think the alignment I
really do think the alignment is I think
alignment is the right way of
conceptualizing it because I think if
you say things that are as true as you
can say them let's say then they come up
they come out of the depths inside of
you because we don't know where thoughts
come from we don't know how far down
into your sub structure the thoughts
emerge we don't know what processes of
physiological alignment are necessary
for you to speak from the core of your
being we don't understand any of that we
don't even conceptualize that but I
believe that you can feel that and I
learned some of that from reading Carl
Rogers by the way who's a great
clinician because he talked about mental
health in part as a coherence between
the spiritual or the or the abstract and
the physical that the two things were
aligned and and there's a lot of idea of
alignment in psychoanalytic and clinical
thinking but anyways I decided that I
would start practicing not saying things
that would make me weak and what
happened was that I had to stop saying
almost everything that I was saying I
would say 95% of it as a hell of a shark
to wake up and I mean this was over a
few months but the hell of a shark to
wake up and realize that you're mostly
dead would it's a shock you know and you
might think well do you really want all
of that to burn off well there's nothing
left but a little ha sleight of you it's
like well if that 5% is solid then maybe
that's exactly what you want to have
happened also I told you that story is
an elaboration of this line and God saw
that the wickedness of man was great in
the earth and that every imagination of
the thoughts of his heart was only evil
continually
to question worth asking just exactly
what are your motives well you know
maybe they're purer than mine were and
it's certainly possible I don't think
that I'm naturally a particularly good
person I think I have to work at it very
very hard and I don't necessarily think
that everyone is like that but some
people are worse than that
and everyone's like that to some degree
so it's worth thinking about just how
much trouble are you trying to cause you
know and the other thing you might think
about is that if you're not doing
something important with your life by
your own definition because that's the
game that we're playing you get to
define the terms at least initially
maybe you're prone to cause trouble just
because you don't have anything better
to do because at least its trouble is
more interesting than boring you know
that's something you learn if you read
Dostoyevsky does he ask you knew that
extraordinarily well and so if you're
not doing something if you're not
pushing yourself to the limits of your
capacity then you have plenty of left
over what would you say willpower
energy and resources to devote to
causing interesting trouble and so also
I would say this is also an archetypal
scenario God saw that the wickedness of
man was great in the earth and that
every imagination of the thoughts of his
heart was only evil continually that's
something to meditate on and it's not
self-destructive because what it is is
an attempt to it's like the diagnosis of
an illness it's like if that does happen
to be the case for you or to some degree
maybe it's only 10% of you or something
or maybe it's 90% well then coming to
terms of that is excellent because then
maybe you can stop doing it and what
would be the downside to that you'd have
to give up your resentment obviously in
your hatred and all of that and that's
really annoying because those emotions
are very they're easy to engage in and
they're and they're engaging and they
have this feeling of self-righteousness
with them and that goes along with them
but you're not doing this in order to
put yourself down you're doing this in
order to separate the wheat from the
chaff and to leave everything that you
don't have to be behind
and it repented the Lord that he had
made man on the earth and it grieved him
at his heart and the Lord said I will
destroy man whom I have created from the
face of the earth both man and beast and
the creeping thing and the fowls of the
air for it repentance me that I've made
them
what's the idea well the idea is that
the cosmos that God created had become
corrupt and that's a funny thing because
you know this is the other thing about
Genesis that always hits me is that
that's also true I told you that the
Mesopotamians believe that human beings
were made out of the blood of King knew
who was the worst monster monster that
the dragon of chaos could imagine that's
a pretty harsh diagnosis but but the
reason the Mesopotamians believe that is
because they knew as did the authors of
genesis that human beings are the only
creatures in the cosmos let's say the
cosmos of being who are actually capable
of deceit conscious deceit and
malevolence and the question is to what
degree does the expression of that
conscious deceit and malevolence corrupt
things so badly that it would be better
that they didn't exist at all well you
see stories there's a story associated
with this in the epic of gilgamesh
associated with the flood that has
exactly the same underlying narrative
structure in fact some people think the
story of Noah was derived from it where
the gods who created repented of their
creation and determined that erasing it
would be better than allowing it to
propagate and you see the same thing in
the Mesopotamian creation myth you knew
mulisch because the early gods so
they're representatives of the Giants of
humanity I would say make so much noise
and are so careless that the original
creator God timeout and and her consort
time app decides to wipe them from the
face of the earth and so when you read
something like this if you read it from
an informed historical perspective it
starts to have a depth that makes it
transcend this sort of archaic and fairy
tale like
element of the story it's like I've read
some very terrible things about what
happened in Nazi Germany and and what
happened when the Japanese invaded China
and just what happened generally in the
history of mankind and things can get so
bad that it takes the imagination of a
very bad person to conceptualize them
and when they get that bad this is the
only kind of language that works to
describe them you know that's another
thing that I've discovered working with
my clinical clients is that when their
lives are really not going well you know
when they're close to suicide or when
they're close to homicide or when there
are things going on in the family that
are so corrupt and terrible that they
reach back generations and they're aimed
at nothing but misery and destruction
the only language that suffices
has a religious tone because there's
nothing else that's available to
describe what's happening with the
proper level of seriousness and it might
be that you've never encountered a
situation that required that level of
seriousness but that doesn't mean that
those situations don't exist they exist
you generally do everything you can to
avoid being ensconced in them but they
certainly do exist and the probability
that you'll encounter a situation like
that or two at some point in your life
is extraordinarily high you'll tangle
with someone who's malevolent right to
the core and maybe it'll be you that is
and that'll be a big shock and then
these sorts of things these sorts of
poetic descriptors start to become much
more real but Noah found grace in the
eyes of the Lord these are the
generations of Noah Noah was a just man
and perfect in his generations and Noah
walked with God that's an interesting
line because if you remember back in the
story of Adam and Eve what happens to
Adam once he eats the fruit of the tree
of the knowledge of good and evil and
wakes up the scales fall from his eyes
become self-conscious develops the
knowledge of good and evil is he won't
walk with God when God calls him in the
garden and so Noah is Adam without the
fall essentially and there's something
that knows
right that motivates God to spare him or
maybe to show him a pathway through the
emergent chaos something like that and
that's worth thinking about a lot
because there will be situations in your
life where what you face is the emergent
chaos and maybe that'll be some terrible
catastrophe inside your family or maybe
it'll be something that's occurring on a
much broader social level but the chaos
is coming and what you're going to want
to know unless you want to be a denizen
of the chaos or even a contributor to it
and perhaps that is what you want
because many people under those
circumstances choose that what you want
is to know how you build an ark and get
through it that's what you if you're if
you're interested in life if you're
interested in proper being and you're
disinclined to produce any more
suffering than necessary then you want
to know how to conduct yourself when the
catastrophe comes so that you have a
reasonable possibility of of moving
through it and starting anew so when
when this old story says well God's not
happy he's going to wipe everything out
it's like well you might want to take
that seriously and then when it says but
there's one person who had a mode of
being that protected him from that
that's also something you might want to
take seriously because you might want to
know what that mode of being is because
you might need to use it and so these
sorts of things are practical in the
deepest possible sense they're real in
the deepest possible sense and practical
in the deepest possible sense so Noah
walked with God now I'm going to switch
way ahead here because
you know they said at the beginning of
the lecture series that the Bible is a
hyperlinked text and everything refers
to everything else and so there's
utility in reading it in linear order
but it's not a linear document it's a
document that that you can move through
in an infinite number of there's an
infinite number of pathways that you can
use to walk through it and all of the
document expands upon and refers to all
of the rest of the document and so I'm
going to switch to the sermon on the
mount which i think is probably the key
document in the New Testament and I'm
going to switch to it because I think
it's the closest thing we have to a
fully articulated description of what it
would mean to walk with God so that
you're in the ark when the flood comes
it's the it's the most fully articulated
realization of that idea that that leaps
out of the metaphorical because if I say
well you should conduct yourself like
Noah and walk with God and build an ark
obviously those are poetic and
metaphorical suggestions and it's not
that easy to bring them into practice
right it's the distance there's a big
distance between you and the archetype
it isn't obvious how to manifest it in
your own life and what has to happen is
the archetype has to be differentiated
and articulated so that it becomes
sufficiently practical and personal so
that you can actually implement it so
I'm going to take apart some of the
Sermon on the Mount
it starts in Matthew five and I'm not
going to talk about Matthew five I'm
going to talk about the end of Matthew
six and most of Matthew seven consider
the lilies of the field how they grow
they toil not neither do they spin and
yet I say unto you that even Solomon in
all his glory was not arrayed like one
of these wherefore if God so clothes the
grass of the field which today is and
tomorrow is cast into the oven shall he
not much more clothe you O ye of little
faith therefore take no Thought saying
what shall we eat or what shall we drink
or wherewithal shall we be clothed those
are famous lines and that's our
Christ the hippie right it's like hey
let it all hang out
that's an old phrase do your thing and
everything will come to you and these
lines have been interpreted in that
manner many times but that's seriously
not the proper interpretation because
there's a kicker with this injunction
and the kicker is this for your heavenly
Father knows that you have need of all
these things but seek ye first the
kingdom of God and His righteousness and
all these things shall be added unto you
that's a lot different than the hippie
thing right because there's a very very
very interesting idea here it's it's
certainly one of the most profound ideas
that I've ever encountered and the idea
is this is that if you configure your
life so that what you are genuinely
doing is aiming at the highest possible
good then the things that you need to to
survive and to thrive on a day to day
basis will deliver themselves to you
that's a hypothesis and it's not some
simple hypothesis right because it what
it basically says is if you dare to do
the most difficult thing that you can
conceptualize your life will work out
better than it will if you do anything
else well how are you going to find out
if that's true well it's a Kierkegaard
ian's leap of faith there's no way
you're going to find out whether or not
that's true unless you do it so no one
no one can tell you either because just
because it works for someone else I mean
that's interesting and all that but it's
no proof that it'll work for you you
have to be all-in in this game and so
the idea is seek ye first the kingdom of
God and His righteousness it's like
that's actually a fairly important
caution when you're talking about not
having to pay attention to what you're
going to eat or what you're going to
wear it's like what it's essentially
saying is that those problems are
trivial in comparison and the
probability is that if you manifest
yourself properly in the world that
those things will come your way
is extraordinarily high and I believe I
believe that that's exactly right
I mean I've watched people operate in
the world and I would say that there is
no more effective way of operating in
the world than to conceptualize the
highest good that you can and then
strive to attain it there's no more
practical pathway to the kind of success
that you could have if you actually knew
what success was and so that's what this
that's what this sermon is attempting to
to posit it's like in in the story of
Pinocchio you know what happens at the
beginning of the story of Pinocchio is
that Geppetto wishes on a star we talked
about that a little bit and so what you
pedo does is align himself with the
metaphorical manifestation of the
highest good he can conceptualize and
say he says he makes he makes a
commitment let's say he aims at the star
and for him the star is the possibility
that he can take his creation a puppet
right whose strings are being pulled by
unseen forces and have it transformed
into something that's economist and real
well that's a hell of an ambition you
know and we're wise enough to put that
in the children's movie but too foolish
to understand what it means it's such an
interesting juxtaposition that that we
can both know that and not know it at
the same time you can go to the movie
you can watch it and it makes sense but
that doesn't mean that you can go home
and think well I know what that meant
well people are complicated right we
exist at different levels and all the
levels don't communicate with one
another but but the movie is a
hypothesis and the hypothesis is there's
no better pathway to self-realization
and the annulment of being than to posit
the highest good that you can conceive
of and commit yourself to it and then
you might also ask yourself and this is
definitely worth asking is do you really
have anything better to do and if you
don't well why would you do anything
else therefore take no thought for the
morrow for the morrow shall take thought
for the things of itself sufficient
unto the day is the evil thereof I spend
a long time trying to figure out without
man to because it's another one of those
lines that can easily be read as program
offer and anti amped you know you
remember the old fable of the
grasshopper in the end maybe not I'm not
going to tell it but that works in the
grasshopper fiddles and the ant has a
pretty good time in the winter and the
grasshopper dies and so this is like a
pro grasshopper line but it's not
because it says something else it says
that if you orient yourself properly and
then pay attention to what you do every
day that works and I actually think that
that's in accordance with what we have
come to understand about human
perception because what happens is that
the world shifts itself around your aim
is you're a creature that has a name you
have to have a name in order to do
something you're an aiming creature you
look at a point and you move towards it
it's built right into you and so you
have a name well let's say your aim is
the highest possible aim well then so
that sets up the world around you it
organizes all of your perceptions it
organizes what you see and you don't see
it organizes your emotions and your
motivations so you organize yourself
around that aim and then what happens is
the day manifests itself as a set of
challenges and problems and if you solve
them properly then you stay on the
pathway towards that ape and you can
concentrate on the on the ate on the day
and so that way you get to have your
cake and eat it too because you can you
can point into the distance the far
distance and you can live in the day and
it seems to me that that's that makes
every moment of the day super charged
with meaning that that's how because if
everything that you're doing every day
is related to the highest possible aim
that you can conceptualize well that's
the very definition of the meaning that
would sustain you in your life well then
the issue is well back to Noah well all
hell is about to break loose and chaos
is coming it's like when that's
happening in your life you might want to
be doing something that you regard is
truly worthwhile because that's what
will keep you afloat
when when everything is flooded and you
don't want to wait until the flood comes
to start doing that because if your arks
half built and you don't know how to
captain it the probability is very high
that that you'll drown take therefore no
thought for the morale but for the
morale shall take thought for the things
of itself sufficient unto the day is the
evil thereof that's not a particularly
optimistic formulation judge not that ye
be not judged for with what judgment you
judge you shall be judged and with what
measure you mete it shall be measured to
you again it's a sensible piece of it's
a sensible description I wouldn't call
it a piece of advice because I don't
think that any of this is advice it's a
description of the structure of reality
that's not the same as advice and it
basically says that you'll be held
accountable by the rules of the game
that you choose to play and that I also
think is perfectly in keeping with what
we understand about human psychology
because you you are playing you have to
play a game that other people will allow
you to play and that will cooperate with
you while you're playing and it will
compete with you while you're playing it
but you have a fair bit of flexibility
in setting up the parameters of the game
but you don't have any choice about
whether or not you're going to be in a
game you're in a game and you're going
to be held accountable by the rules of
the game because that's how the game
works and so you might want to pick a
game by whose rules you would be willing
to be held accountable and why beholdest
thou the mote that is in thy brother's
eye but considerest not the beam that is
in thine own eye or how will you say to
thy brother let me pull out the mote out
of thine eye and behold a beam is in
thine own eye well you might be
wondering what a beam is and a mote is a
dust speck and a beam is a very large
piece of lumber
and so the issue is not so much the
blindness of others even though there's
as much blindness among others as there
is as there is for you but that issue
here the advice here the description
here is you should be concerned about
what's interfering with your own vision
first and you should leave other people
the hell alone in relationship to that
and so if your mode of being in the
world is if you would just act better
things would improve for me or if you
identify the evil and the catastrophe is
something that's outside that someone
else needs to fix or that someone's
response someone else is responsible for
then then you're not going to fix that
and you're going to remain blind to the
things that you're doing and not doing
that make things not go well and so it's
just better to think all right I'm
probably blind in many many ways
and maybe there are some ways that I
could rectify that because it's highly
probable that you're blind in all sorts
of ways I mean it's in fact it's
virtually certain and so it's just more
useful to think how is it that I'm wrong
in this situation I'll tell you
something that I learned to do when I
was arguing with my wife which happened
quite frequently because when you
actually communicate with people you
find out that there's many things that
you don't agree on and that's because
you're actually different creatures and
so if you're actually going to have a
truthful conversation then you're going
to find out that you don't see things
the same way and then you can either
pretend that that's not the case and
gloss over it and then end up in a 30
year silent war or you can or you can
have the damn fight when you need to
have it and see if you could straighten
it out so now and then we'd get in a
situation where we were at loggerheads
we couldn't move and you know it would
spiral up into hate speech let's say cuz
yeah everyone laughs because they know
they manifest plenty of hate speech
towards those they loved so one of the
things we learned to do was when we
hit an impasse was to separate and to go
our own ways and to go sit and think
okay look we're at this unpleasant
situation can't figure out how to move
forward I'd always think of course it's
her fault obviously it's her fault least
95 percent but maybe there was something
I did that contributed like five percent
to it and so I would sit and think and
ask myself a question which was is there
anything I did in the last six months
that increased the probability that this
impasse would manifest itself and I'll
tell you you have no idea how fast your
mind will generate an answer to a
question like that because there's
undoubtedly some idiotic thing that you
did that you know that you remember that
increase the probability that you're
going to have your hands around the
throat of the person that you love and
then you can go tell them that and then
you can have a conversation especially
if they do the same thing say look you
know here's how I'm an idiot in this
situation now the person says well yeah
here's how I'm an idiot and then you're
two idiots and then maybe you can have a
conversation so thou hypocrite first
cast out the beam of light out of thine
own eye and then shalt thou see clearly
to cast out the mote of thy brother's
eye that's a hard argue with that ask
and it shall be given you seek and ye
shall find knock and it shall be opened
unto you for every one that asketh
receiveth and he that seeketh findeth
and to him that knocketh it shall be
opened have some pretty optimistic again
but but again I think it's a description
of the structure of the existential
reality and and but by by which I mean
when I'm in my clinical practice and I
observe and this is also the case with
my students is let's say people's lives
aren't what they would like them to be
and so then you ask why well forget
about tragedy in catastrophe because
that's self-evident and we're not going
to discuss that although the degree to
which you bring about your own tragedy
is always indeterminate but I would
never say that every terror
thing that is visited on a person is
something they deserved I think that
that's a very dangerous presupposition
especially because everyone gets sick
and everyone dies but one of the main
reasons that people don't get what they
want is because they don't actually
figure out what it is and the
probability that you're going to get
what would be good for you let's say
which would even be better than what you
want right because you know you might be
what wrong about what you want easily
but maybe you could get what would
really be good for you well why don't
you well because you don't try you don't
think okay here's what I would like if I
could have it and I don't mean I don't
mean in a way that you manipulate the
world to force it to deliver you goods
for status or something like that that
isn't what I mean I mean something like
imagine that you are taking care of
yourself like you were someone you
actually cared for and then you thought
okay I'm caring for this person I would
like things to go as well for them as
possible
what would their life have to be like in
order for that to be the case what
people don't do that they don't sit down
and think all right you know let's let's
figure it out you've got a life that's
hard obviously it's like three years
from now you can have what you need
you've got to be careful about it you
can't have everything you can have what
would be good for you but you have to
figure out what it is and then you have
to aim at it well my experience with
people as being is if they figure out
what it is that would be good for them
and then they aim at it then they get it
and it's strange because they don't
necessarily an idea about what would be
good for you and then you take ten steps
towards that and you find out that your
formulation was a bit off and so you
have to reformulate your goal you know
you're kind of going like this as you
move towards the goal but a huge part of
the reason that people fail is because
they don't ever set up the criteria for
success and so since success is a very
narrow line and very unlikely the
probability that you're going to stumble
on it randomly is zero and so there's a
proposition here in
proposition is if you actually want
something you can have it now the
question then would be well what do you
mean by actually want an answer is that
you reorient your life in every possible
way to make the probability that that
will occur as certain as possible and
that's a sacrificial idea right it's
like you don't get everything obviously
you obviously but maybe you can have
what you need and maybe all you have to
do to get it is ask but asking isn't a
whim or today's wish it's like you have
to be deadly serious about it you have
to think okay like I'm taking stock of
myself and if I was going to live
properly in the world and I was going to
set myself up such that being would
justify itself in my estimation and I
don't mean as a harsh judge exactly what
is it that I would aim at well one of
the things I found is that in in tests
of this theory let's say you could try
this this is a form of Prayer knocking
sit on your bed one day and ask yourself
ah what's what remarkably stupid things
am i doing on a regular basis to
absolutely screw up my life and if you
actually asked that question but you
have to want to know the answer right
because that's actually what asking the
question means it doesn't mean just
mouthing the words it means you have to
decide that you want to know you'll
figure that's out so fast it'll make
your hair curl you'll you it's as if you
thought about this he thought you know
he thought that people had two poles of
consciousness and one was the individual
consciousness that we each identify with
in the other was something he called the
self and the self is the you might think
about it as the divine within that's
close enough approximation and to the
universal part of your consciousness
it's your conscience that's another way
of thinking about it whatever your
conscience is but it's something that
you can consult it's like the Socratic
Damon Socrates said that the thing that
made him different than every
in Greece was that he consulted his
Damon his genius he asked himself how it
was that he should conduct himself in
the world and then he did that
whatever it was he didn't try to force a
solution you know he didn't try to force
a solution selfishly he asked I'm going
to manifest myself in the best possible
manner in the world I would like to do
that what would that be well you're
perfectly capable of thinking god only
knows how you're perfectly capable of
men speeds of imagination and and dream
and fantasies god only knows how you do
all of that what would happen if you
consulted yourself about the best
possible outcome for you you might get
an answer well that's what this
proposition is or what man is there of
you whom if his son asks for bread we'll
give him a stone or if he asks for a
fish will give him a serpent if ye then
being evil know how to give good gifts
unto your children how much more shall
your father which is in heaven give good
things to them that ask him well this is
a question about the fundamental nature
of being I suppose and one of the
hypotheses in the New Testament which is
different to different hypotheses in
some sense than the one that structures
the Old Testament is that faith makes
being good it's a very interesting
proposition and so the notion would be
and it's an action-oriented issue as
well you act out the proposition that if
you act properly in the world that being
will reveal itself to you as benevolent
but you will not know you'll never know
unless you do it so this is a call to
that act out the proposition that if you
act properly that being itself is
benevolent
no reason to assume the contrary I mean
to assume the contrary would be to be as
cynical and bitter as possible and it's
not like we don't have reason for that
it's not like I don't understand why
that happens to people therefore all
things whatsoever you would that men
should do to you do you even so to them
for this is the law and the prophets
and that's a reciprocity issue right
it's like well imagine what would be
this is another thing I learned from
Jung because as Jung reversed this
because this is often read it's it's the
golden rule it's often read as be nice
to it be nice to other people it's like
that is not what this rule means it
doesn't mean that even a little bit it
means something like and we'll reverse
it so that will concentrate on you
rather than the other person to begin
with it means something like
conceptualize how things could be great
if they were great for you if you were
taking care of yourself and then work to
make that the case for everyone else you
know you see that in Buddhism because
Buddha reached Nirvana right that's the
theory and then he was tempted with the
offer to stay there and he rejected that
offer and came back to the profane world
because he felt that the attainment of
Nirvana was insufficient unless everyone
attained it simultaneously and so it's
something like that but it's treat
yourself properly that's a hard thing to
do because you're a fallen shameful
cowardly deceitful malevolent mortal
creature and so it's not easy and you
know it and it's not easy to treat
something like that properly and and it
isn't obvious that people treat
themselves better than they treat other
people I don't think that's obvious at
all but maybe you could start with
yourself and think okay I'm going to
take care of myself as if I have value
what would that look like and then I'm
going to work to extend that courtesy to
everyone else and that's well the
hypothesis here is that if you take all
of the moral wisdom that mankind has
generated over its millennia of struggle
evolved and then manifested metaphors
story and then codified into law
articulated law and you pick one
principle that dominated all of that
this would be the principle and it's
interesting too because it's the law and
the prophets and the law is the rules
but the prophets are the process by
which the rules are being updated right
and so the prophets are superordinate in
some sense to the law and the
proposition that's set forth in this
particular statement is that this maxim
which is optimize your own mode of being
and then work to do the same for
everyone around you is not only the
thing that's at the core of the law but
it's at the core of the process that
generates and updates the law to hell of
a thing for someone to say enter ye in
at the narrow gate because that's what
Strait means enter ye and at the
straight gate for wide is the gate and
broad is the way that leadeth to
destruction well who in the world could
possibly argue with that everyone in the
right mind knows that there's a million
ways of doing things wrong and one way
if you're lucky to do things right and
so the notion that it's a very very
narrow pathway that you tread upon if
you're doing things right that's that's
wisdom that's the line between chaos and
order that you're supposed to be on
constantly right it's a very very thin
line because if you're a little bit too
far in one direction then it's too much
chaos and if you're a little too far in
the other direction then it's too much
order and both of those aren't good it
has did the balance have to be exactly
right and you can feel that and I truly
believe you can feel that and I think
it's your deepest instinct it's your
deepest instinct and I mean that I mean
that biologically I don't mean that
metaphorically I think that your psyche
is arranged to exist in a cosmos that's
composed of chaos and order I think
that's why you have the hemispheric
structure that you have this is deeper
than metaphor and then when you feel as
if you're meaningfully engaged in the
world when the terror of your mortality
strips away and you're engaged and it's
timeless
that's the deepest instinct you have
telling you that you're in the right
place at the right time and then what
you do is practice being there practice
being there and that's that that narrow
spot is so difficult to find you wander
around it maybe if you're lucky you can
watch you can watch this as an
experiment
watch yourself for two weeks like you
don't know who you are because you don't
so watch yourself for two weeks and
notice there's going to be times when
things are proper their raid properly
for you yeah it's not easy to notice
because when they're arrayed like that
you're so engaged you don't exactly
notice you know but you'll see oh I'm in
the right place it's like okay how did I
get here what am i doing right you know
how is it that this could happen more
often I'd like this to happen more often
how would I have to conduct myself in
order for that to happen more often and
then you practice that and then maybe
instead of ten minutes a month or ten
minutes a week it's like 15 minutes a
day and then it's half an hour a day and
then it's an hour a day and then it's
four hours a day and maybe if you if
you're extraordinarily careful then you
get to a point where you're like that a
good proportion of the time because
Strait is the gate and narrow is the way
which leadeth unto life and few there be
that find it beware of false prophets
which come to you in sheep's clothing
but inwardly they are ravening wolves
that's particularly good advice for
today's political situation I can tell
you you shall know them by their fruits
do men gather grapes of thorns or figs
of thistles even so every good tree
bringeth forth good fruit but a corrupt
tree bringeth forth evil fruit well
that's what I learned from studying the
history of totalitarianism in the 20th
century is that a corrupt tree brings
forth evil fruit and that's for sure and
so funny you know people who think when
they're thinking about the relationship
with divinity or the relationship with
God they think it's a primitive and
childish way of thinking what if a
miracle just manifests why can't a
miracle just manifest itself and I would
be convinced and the funny thing is is
first of all actually you wouldn't be if
a miracle actually happened you would
actually forget about
about six months that's I mean you'd
think that's not true but it's true you
would actually forget about it because
that's what people are like but there
are negative miracles that are happening
all the time which actually lend some
credence to my supposition and we don't
pay any attention to that if we can't
learn from what happened in the 20th
century then we are absolutely incapable
of learning because what happened in the
20th century was as bitter a set of
lessons as you could possibly imagine
and its associated precisely with this a
corrupt tree bringeth forth evil fruit a
good tree cannot bring forth evil fruit
neither can a corrupt tree bring forth
good fruit every tree that bringeth
forth that bringeth not forth good few
fruit is hewn down and cast into the
fire well that's a flood motif right
there it's like we're constantly the
archetype of the tree that's the
archetype of being it's the archetype of
the self often what's the warning here
that if you're mostly deadwood you're
going to get you're going to burn up and
you can think about that metaphysically
you can you can project that into
eternity and you can think about that as
a form of Hell and the funny thing is is
that when that's happening to you in
real time it is like an eternity in hell
it's a perfectly reasonable way of
thinking about it but you can strip the
metaphysical elements off and you can
say well if you're mostly dead wood then
a spark will light you on fire and
that's also very much worth thinking
about wherefore by their fruits shall
you know them not everyone that saith
unto me Lord shall enter the kingdom of
heaven but he that doeth the will of my
father which is in heaven
that's an interesting line I think I
mean one of the proper critiques of
traditional Christianity maybe this is
the sort of critique that Nietzsche put
forth was that Christianity had
degenerated in its moral mission Jung
was a little bit more sympathetic and
I'll tell you why in a minute but
Nietzsche's idea was that Christianity
had lost its way when it generated the
presupposition that human
nnedi was saved in some final sense by
the sacrifice of Christ it meant that
the work was already done and that and
I'm I'm being I'm being harsh in my
judgment for the purpose of rhetorical
simplification but the idea was that if
you just professed faith that that had
already occurred then you were granted
eternal salvation it's like well it's
not so straightforward and I think that
that's what this line actually
represents it says how you enter into
the kingdom of heaven and and again you
can think about that under the aspect of
eternity or you can think about it as a
psychological statement and the answer
is quite straightforward is that you do
what Noah did to make him immune from
the flood and that's to walk with God
and that's what this sermon is about
it's laying out the practical elements
of that and the practical elements are
aimed at the highest possible good and
play that out in the world and then you
may have the opportunity to inhabit the
highest possible good that you're
positing into existence perhaps not but
you can't think of any more practical
way of going about that I mean if you
build a house then maybe you can live in
it if you don't build a house you're not
going to be able to live in it if you
build a good house then you'll be able
to live in a good house and if you build
a perfect house then maybe you can live
in a perfect house but if you just say
that the house has already been built
for you and that you can just say that
the house is being built for you well
then the probability that you're going
to be able to live where you need to
live is there's no probability that
you're going to be able to live where
you need to live many will say to me in
that day that's the Judgment Day Lord
have we not prophesied in thy name and
in thy name of cast out devils and in
thy name done many wonderful works and
then I will profess unto them I never
knew you depart from me you that work
iniquity
see that's Judgment Day you know that's
an archetypal idea
and partly it's archetypal because
everyday is Judgment Day and the part of
you that the part of you that's
equivalent to the logo say the part of
you that's your own ideal sits in
eternal judgment on your iniquity and
that's the con that's the source of
guilt and shame and and and withdrawal
and then resentment and then murderous
'no sand then genocide it's because you
can intuit the ideal and the problem
with intuiting the ideal is that an
ideal is always a judge there's no
difference between an ideal and the
judge and so you're eternally judged by
your own ideal if you have no idea well
then you've got no direction and no
meaning in your life and then of course
the more extremely ideal the harsher the
judge that's actually why young young
was very curious about why the book of
Revelation was tacked on to the Bible to
the book of Revelation that's a very
weird book and you know in in in the
Gospels Christ is I would say perhaps
primarily merciful there's a maybe a war
in his character between truth and mercy
but it's one of the two perhaps mercy
and Jung's observation was the gospel
Christ was too merciful and that's why
the book of Revelation was tapped on
tacked onto the New Testament because in
the book of Revelation Christ who's the
ideal who's above the pyramid right the
transcendent ideal is nothing but a
judge and everyone fails and of course
the ultimate ideal is the ultimate judge
and so that's the archetypal reality
there and you can say well I don't want
to be judged and so I'll dispense with
the ideal but then you're Cain because
Cain is exactly the person who dispenses
with the ideal and so there's no
escaping from it there's no escaping
from eternal judgment that's the
archetypal story you know people put a
lot of work into these representations
you know and there's thousands of them
they weren't messing around
these are serious pieces of work you
know we don't understand them but that
doesn't mean that the people who created
them didn't know what they were doing
these were geniuses who created these
pieces of work it's not like they
understood in an articulated manner
what they were trying to represent but
what they were representing were the the
metaphor is at the core of our culture
to the degree that our culture is
functional and good these are the
metaphors upon which it's founded and
they're not for the faint of heart you
know you say religion is the opiate of
the masses it's like yeah then how do
you explain this exactly you know
because if it was opiates you're after
you might just get rid of that panel
especially when the other thing that's
so interesting about the proposition if
you look at revelations in Revelation
and you look at the judgment almost
everyone ends up on the right side of
this panel so if you are just conjuring
up some sort of pathetic wish
fulfillment why in the world would you
tilt the scales in that manner you think
that's supposed to make people feel good
I don't think so
there's almost nothing about this
picture that should make people feel
good it should if you understand it
properly it should terrify you to the
depths of your soul that's what the
picture is for therefore whoever heareth
these sayings of mine and doeth them I
will liken him unto a wise man which
built his house upon a rock and the rain
descended and the winds blew and the
floods came and beat upon the house and
it fell not for it was founded upon a
rock and every one that heareth these
sayings of mine and doeth them not shall
be likened unto a foolish man which
built his house upon the sand and the
rain descended and the floods came and
the winds blew had beat upon that house
and it oh I made a mistake and it fell
for it was founded upon the sand and it
came to pass this is a very interesting
line I really I really you know now and
then you run across lines in this
particularly happens in biblical
settings you run across lines that you
cannot believe actually exist you cannot
imagine how someone could have imagined
up and conjured up the line and these
two lines are like that as far as I'm
concerned and it came to pass when Jesus
had ended these sayings that people were
astonished at his doctrine for he taught
them as one having a
authority and not as the scribes and
that's something so interesting you know
because that was another thing that
really I didn't really appreciate about
the churches that I attended to and that
would be that the lessons were taught by
scribes and the words were mouthed but
there was no power in them there was no
meaning in them it was it was as if well
it was like when I was 20 years old and
I was saying all these things I didn't
mean you know they were words that
sounded good they were like like gilded
cloth I suppose that you can that you
can wrap around yourself but there's no
substance to them and there's a big
difference between listening to
something that has substance and
listening to something that is spoken
because it sounds like it should sound
good and this line says that whoever
spoke the lines that we just described
was someone who sounded like he knew
what he was talking about and not
someone who was just repeating something
for the sake of sounding good and it
certainly seems to me that the lines
that we just reviewed have the awesome
impact of authority back to Noah but
Noah found grace in the eyes of the Lord
these are the generations of Noah Noah
was a just man and perfect in his
generations and Noah walked with God and
Noah begat three sons Shem ham and
Japheth
the earth was also corrupt before God
and the earth was full of violence
filled with violence any of you see the
new NRA ad you might want to look that
up I would say that's the most shocking
manifestation of political polarization
in the United States that I've yet seen
most of it I've seen on the left/right
the real what shocked me mostly has been
on the left but the new NRA ad that's a
whole new thing so it's this attractive
woman and doing a voiceover she kind of
looks like Demi Moore well she's kind of
tough looking I guess Demi Moore could
look tough now and then and she has
contempt on her face and that's a
dangerous thing and in the background
there's nothing but images of
anteye far is and Berkeley riots and
fire and protest and she's describing
that as a conspiracy essentially a
conspiracy that involves the
intellectual elite including Hollywood
which is named by name the accusation is
is that there's a cabal of corrupt
intellectuals let's say who are bringing
the country to its knees
and that it's time to get your goddamn
guns and so look up that and see what
you think because there's lots of people
who would be perfectly happy if that was
the direction in which you were headed
and one of the things that I'm hoping is
that we might be able to talk our way
through it but we're in a situation
where every act of idiot individual
idiocy will push us one iota closer to
the brink and that'll make the 15
percent of the population or 30 percent
of the population who would love to see
everything degenerate into chaos
perfectly happy because that's their aim
the earth also was corrupt before God
and the earth was filled with violence
and God looked upon the earth and behold
it was corrupt for all flesh is
corrupted his way upon the earth and
Noah said and God said unto Noah the end
of all flesh has come before me for the
earth is filled with violence through
them and behold I will destroy them with
the earth make the an ark of gopher wood
rooms shalt thou make in the Ark from
that shalt pitch it within and without
with pitch and this is the fashion which
thou shalt make of it the length of the
ark shall be 300 cubits the breadth of
it 50 cubits in the height of it 30
cubits a window shalt thou make to the
ark and in a cubit shalt thou finish it
above and the door of the ark shalt thou
set in the side thereof with lower
second and third stories shalt thou make
it and behold I even I do bring a flood
of waters upon the earth to destroy all
flesh wherein is the breath of life from
under heaven and everything that is in
the earth shall die but with thee I will
establish my covenant and thou shalt
come into the are
thou and thy sons and thy wife and thy
sons wives with thee that's a fairly
optimistic twist on the story because
not only is it Noah but he gets to save
his whole family and down a couple of
generations and so that's a good thing
to think about it's like as things know
I had this client and she had a very
hard upbringing I would say not a lot of
encouragement to say the least let's say
a fair bit of discouraged meant and she
had a son and what was really
interesting about her in relationship to
her son is that all the things that she
could have learned to do to him
given her extensive experience with
being made as miserable as possible by
someone who was hell-bent on bringing
her to her knees
she refused to do to her son right she
learned the opposite lesson from all her
misery and torment which was not to move
that forward down the generations and so
the idea here is that if you walk
properly a name properly and act
properly if you walk with God in this
manner that we've been discussing is
that perhaps that isn't only good for
you perhaps it's also the thing that
will save your family and then by
implication perhaps saves Society
because that's exactly what happens with
Noah right first it's him and then it's
his family but everything else goes and
so by saving himself by acting properly
and by saving his family he actually
saves the world it's interesting you
know it's like the most profound people
that I've read who've meditated deeply
on the problem say of totalitarian
catastrophe and I would put Alexander
Solzhenitsyn at the top of that list
you know the his entire corpus three
volumes 700 pages long each in tiny type
is a long scream about the absolute
necessity of individual the absolute
necessity of individual honesty and
ethical behavior as the only bulwark
against totalitarian catastrophe and
that and I've read many writers who've
attempted to diagnose the problems of
the 20th century and I think
elgyn Edson he came to the same
conclusions that Viktor Frankl came to
as a consequence of his experiences in
the Nazi concentration camps and Frankel
I am also an admirer of Franco but
Solzhenitsyn takes it to an entire
different level of profundity and makes
an extraordinarily strong case that not
only do societies deteriorate because
the people within the societies become
individually corrupt but that the only
way to stave that off is for the
individuals within that society to
reject that corruption in the in the
confines of their own personal lives and
he tells endless stories of people that
he met in the gulag and in the work
camps in the death camps in the Soviet
Union of people and this is what he
learned of people who were so incredibly
tough that even under conditions the
most possible extreme conditions there
wasn't a chance that they were going to
step off that straight and narrow line
there was nothing the authorities could
do to move them and just watching that
was enough to transform Solzhenitsyn
because of course one of the things he
wondered was after spending a good
amount of time in the work camps was
well just exactly how did I get here and
it wasn't well it was Hitler's fault and
it was Stalin's fault although it was
definitely the fault of both of them for
Solzhenitsyn it was well it was also his
fault because he was playing the same
game he just wasn't as good at it and of
every living thing of all flesh two of
every sort shall thou bring into the ark
to keep them alive with thee they shall
be male and female and so there's
another message in this story which is
that it isn't only Noah and his family
and human society that's dependent on
Noah's appropriate actions in the world
it's the entire living planet and in an
era of excessive and extreme and
genuinely disingenuous environmental
catastrophe Singh that's something to
consider very seriously think
perhaps there's nothing better that you
can do for everything all things
considered including those things that
are outside the confines of human
society than to get your act together
and align yourself properly along all of
the dimensions of your being from from
from the tiniest microcosm to the to the
ultimate macrocosm and that's the way
that all of being is redeemed that's
what the story suggests and we read it
you know a cynical modern people we read
it as if it was written by primitive
people who thought that it was really
the case that someone could build a boat
and put two of every kind into it and
thereby saved the world
it's embarrassing to see things
interpreted in a manner that shallow
especially by people who don't have
ignorant as a justification you know
these stories have to appeal to everyone
right and there's lots of people in the
world who aren't very bright and so they
tend to take things concretely like a
child would take things concretely if
you read them a story and this story can
be taken concretely but it has to be
because these stories have to be for
everyone but if you're sophisticated
that doesn't mean that you should
dismiss it as if it's written for a
child it's maybe you have the obligation
to look a bit deeper and think for a
moment that it wouldn't been conserved
for these many thousands of years if
there wasn't something more to it than a
casual intellectual dismissal would
indicate and take thou on to the of all
food that is eaten and thou shalt gather
it to thee and shall be food for the end
for them thus did Noah according to all
that God commanded him so did he and the
Lord said unto Noah come thou and all
thy house into the ark for the I have
seen righteous before me in this
generation of every clean beast thou
shalt take to thee by sevens the male
and his female and a beasts that are
clean but not clean by two the male and
his female of follows also of the air by
sevens the male and the female to keep
seed alive upon the face of all the
earth for yet seven days I will cause it
to rain upon the earth forty days and
forty nights and every living substance
that I've made will I destroy from off
the face of the earth and Noah did
according unto all depth
lord commanded him and though it was 600
years old when the flood of waters was
upon the earth
and Noah went in and his sons and his
wife and his sons wives with him into
the ark because of the waters of the
flood of clean beasts and the beasts
that are not clean enough follows and of
everything that creepeth upon the earth
they went in 2 and 2 unto Noah into the
ark the male and the female as God had
commanded Noah and it came to pass after
seven days that the waters of the flood
were upon the earth in the six hundredth
year of Noah's life in the second month
the seventeenth day of the month the
same day were all the Fountains of the
great deep broken up and the windows of
heaven were opened and the rain was upon
the earth forty days and forty nights
and the self-same day entered Noah and
Shem and ham and Japheth
sons of Noah and Noah's wife and 3 wives
of his sons with them into the ark today
and every beast after his kind and all
of the cattle after their kind and every
creeping thing that creepeth upon the
earth after his kind and every fowl
after his kind every bird of every sort
and they went into Noah unto Noah into
the ark two and two of all flesh wherein
is the breath of life that makes know
where they ultimate Shepherd right
Shepherd of all things tender of the
garden and Shepherd of all things that's
a hell of a roll and maybe that's the
one that keeps you afloat during the
flood and they that went in went in male
and female of all flesh as God had
commanded him and the Lord showed him in
and the flood was forty days upon the
earth and the waters increased and bear
up the ark and it was left up above the
earth and the waters prevailed and were
increased greatly upon the earth 15
cubits upward did the waters prevail and
the mountains were covered and all flesh
died that moved upon the earth both of
fallen of cattle and the beasts and of
every creeping thing that creepeth upon
the earth and every man and all in whose
nostrils was the breath of life of all
that was in the dry land died and every
living substance was destroyed which was
upon the face of the earth
both man and cattle and the creeping
things in the fall of the heaven and
they were destroyed from the earth and
Noah only remained alive and they that
were with him in the ark and the waters
prevailed upon the earth
one hundred and fifty days and God
remembered Noah every living thing and
all the cattle that was with him in the
ark and God made a wind to pass over the
earth and the waters receded the
Fountains also of the deep and the
windows of heaven were stopped in the
rain from heaven was restrained and the
waters returned from off the earth
continually and after the end of a
hundred and fifty days the waters were
abated and the ark rested in the seventh
month on the seventeenth day of the
month upon the mountains of Ararat and
the waters decreased continually until
the tenth month in the tenth month on
the first day of the month were the tops
of the mountains seen and it came to
pass at the end of 40 days that Noah
opened the window of the ark which he
had made and he sent forth a raven which
went to and fro until the waters were
dried up from off the earth and he also
sent forth a dove from him to see if the
water's were abated from off the face of
the ground but the devil found no rest
for the sole of her foot and she
returned unto him in the ark for the
waters were on the face of the whole
earth then he put forth his hand and
took her and pulled her in unto him into
the ark and he stayed yet another seven
days and again he sent forth the dove
out of the ark and the Dove came in to
him in the evening and lo in her mouth
was an olive leaf plucked off so Noah
knew that the waters were abated from
off the earth and he stayed there yet
another seven days and sent forth the
Dove which returned not again unto him
anymore
and it came to pass in the six hundredth
and first year in the first month the
first day of the month the waters were
dried up from off the earth and Noah
removed the covering of the ark had
looked up and behold the face of the
ground was dry and in the second month
on the seventh and twentieth day of the
month was the earth dried and God spake
unto Noah saying go forth of the ark
thou and thy wife and thy sons and thy
sons wives with thee bring forth with
the every living thing that is with thee
of all flesh both of fowl and of cattle
and of every creeping thing that
creepeth upon the earth that they may
breed abundantly in the earth and be
fruitful and multiply upon the earth and
Noah went forth and his sons and his
wife and his sons wives with them
beast creeping thing every fowl and
whatsoever creepeth upon the earth after
their kinds went forth out of the ark
and Noah builded an altar unto the Lord
and took of every clean beast and of
every clean fowl and offered burnt
offerings on the altar immediate returns
the sacrificial motif and the Lord
smelled a sweet savour and that's Noah's
proper sacrifice and the Lord said into
his heart I will not again curse the
ground any more for man's sake for the
imagination of man's heart is evil from
his youth neither will I again smite any
more every living thing as I have done
while the earth remaineth seedtime and
harvest and cold and heat and summer and
winter and day and night shall not cease
and God blessed Noah and his sons and
said unto them be fruitful and multiply
and replenish the earth and the fear of
you and the dread of you shall be upon
every beast of the earth and upon every
fowl of the air upon all that moveth
upon the earth upon all the fishes of
the sea into your hand are they
delivered
you know I've heard commentators David
Suzuki for example who claimed that the
substructure of Western culture in lines
such as this deliver the earth over to
human beings and and justify our
ravaging of the of being but I don't
think that that's a very careful reading
and it seems to me that given such
matters given the importance of such
matters that a very close reading is
actually necessary you know in the story
of Adam and Eve when Adam and Eve are
thrown out of the garden God tells Eve
that she's going to be subordinated to
her husband he doesn't say that that's
what should happened
he says that's what's going to happen
and the same thing as far as I'm
concerned is contained in lines like
this isn't necessarily that this is
something that should happen it's
something that did to happen it's quite
remarkable you know to think about how
long ago these lines were penned it
wasn't obvious until perhaps the 1960s
that we had dominated the earth so
completely that it's very future
existence within our hands and that's a
prophetic element of this tale and the
fear of you and the dread of you shall
be upon every beast of the earth and
upon every fowl of the air and upon all
that moveth upon the earth and upon all
the fishes of the sea into your hand are
they delivered like that's exactly right
every moving thing that liveth shall be
meat for you even as the green herb I've
given you all things have I given you
all things but flesh with the life
thereof which is the blood thereof shall
you not eat and surely your blood of
your lives will I require at the hand of
every beast will I require it at the
hand of man at the hand of every man's
brother will I require the life of man
this is a hard section to interpret but
what it means is something like this God
describes the dominion over the planet
that vilified humanity will have and
note the power that goes along with that
and then puts a limitation on it and the
limitation is maintain the sanctity of
life despite your power and although
it's not easy to extract from the manner
in which this is being translated what
God is telling Noah is that if you kill
yourself if you kill someone else and if
any animal kills a human being that
there will be a price to pay for that so
there's a an opportunity which is that
the descendants of Noah can dominate the
earth but there's a moral limitation
placed on that which is nonetheless life
itself is to be regarded as sanctified
and sacred whoever shared if man's blood
by man shall his blood be shed for in
the image of God made he mad and you be
you fruitful and multiply bring forth
abundantly in the earth and multiply
therein and God spake unto Noah and to
his sons with him saying and I behold I
establish my covenant with you and with
your seed after you and with every
living creature that is with you of the
fowl and the cattle and of every beast
of Earth that is with you for all that
go out of the ark to every beast of the
earth and I will establish my covenant
with you neither shall all flesh be cut
off anymore by the waters of a flood
neither shall there be anymore
a flood to destroy the earth and God
said this is the token of the Covenant
which I make between me and you and
every living creature that is with you
for perpetual generations I do set my
bow in the cloud and it shall be for a
token of a covenant between me and the
earth and shall come to pass when I
bring a cloud over the earth that the
bow shall be seen in the cloud and I
will remember my covenant which is
between me and you and every living
creature of all flesh and the waters
shall no more become a flood to destroy
all flesh there's a negotiated agreement
there of sorts and the negotiated
agreement is as far as I can tell
to the degree that humanity agrees to
act in the manner of Noah then the
threat of catastrophic destruction will
remain at bay and the bow shall be in
the cloud and I will look upon it that I
may remember the everlasting covenant
between God and every living creature of
all flesh that is upon the earth and God
said unto Noah this is the token of the
Covenant which I've established between
me and all flesh that is upon the earth
this is the token of the Covenant which
I've established between me and all
flesh that is upon the earth so that's a
good place to stop and there's no
lecture next week by the way because the
theater was booked so there'll be a
one-week break and then when we get back
we'll finish the story of Noah there's
not much left of it we'll talk about the
Tower of Babel which is a very short
story but a very very interesting one
and then we'll move on to the story of
Abraham and so thank you very much for
coming and we'll see you in two weeks
[Applause]
now is the person who has the
notification for the meetup after this
here and do they have the notification
okay because if you give that to me this
time I'll remember to read it before
everyone leaves so do you want to start
okay so see it let's see if the mic is
working because lots of people will
listen to this question and so okay okay
so you said on a recent livestream that
you were to you didn't have enough
energy to answer this question but you
said it was intriguing so I was
wondering if you had the energy to
answer how someone might help someone
that has borderline personality disorder
by example by example no no no I don't I
don't mean that precisely I mean that
the let's not take borderline
personality disorder precisely as the
example okay I understand the question
the question to some degree is how do
you help someone that's lost and answer
that is if they aren't willing to not be
lost you cannot help them and I would
also say that as a clinician you see I
mean it's an it's a statement that's
informed I would say by mythological
knowledge but also by straight clinical
wisdom not mine particularly I mean one
of the things that Carl Rogers pointed
out was that there were necessary
preconditions for entering into a
therapeutic relationship and that would
be really any relationship where the
mutual flourishing of the two people
involved was the Paramount goal and one
of the preconditions was that both
people had to want that to happen and
Rogers believed he didn't know how to
get the horse to drink when she had
brought it to the water and I thought
about that a lot because when people are
really lost sometimes they're so lost
that that they can't be found and I
think the only thing
that you can do in a situation like that
is get your life together and she and
manifest the reality of an alternative
mode of being that's what you've got and
so that's the only way I know of to
solve an intractable problem and I would
say the reason that I went down that
direction with regards to borderline
personality disorders because it's one
of the most serious of the personality
sort is very difficult to treat and so
I'll generalize from that to situations
that are very difficult to deal with and
you know there's a statement to and this
has nothing to do with borderline
personality disorder per se there's a
statement in the New Testament that's
really vicious in fact there's a number
of them but this is a particularly
vicious one and that is don't cast
pearls before swine and what that means
is if you're trying to help and it
doesn't work then stop helping it's not
helping right it may be just wasting
your time
it might be making things worse no if
you're if you're offering something and
it's not taken then perhaps you should
be offering it somewhere else and
sometimes if you offer hand and the
person won't take it you have to stop
offering the hand and then what you do
is you go off and you have your life and
sometimes that means in people's lives
for example that they have to leave
their family members behind there's a
scene in the New Testament this is
another very harsh scene where Christ is
walking down the road with his disciples
I hope I've got this story right but
I've got it essentially right and his
mother calls to him and says I believe
that he's supposed to come back to the
home because his uncle has died and that
there's going to be a funeral and he
turns to his mother and says something
like let the dead bury their dead I'm
about my father's business it's
something like that and you read that
you think huh that should have been
edited out no but it shouldn't have been
added it out because it's exactly right
because sometimes the thing you do is
walk away because there's no other
solution and if you are trapped in
pathologic
relationships and you see no way out of
them if you if someone who is thinking
has their hands around your neck and is
pulling you down you're not obligated to
drown with them now there's a rule too
if you're a lifeguard you know some of
you have had lifeguard training how do
you approach someone who's drowning and
panicking in the water feed out right
like this it's like I'll save you but
that doesn't mean you get to drown me
while I'm doing it and if it's you drown
or both of us drown it's you drown and
that's wisdom that's not cruelty right
so yeah a couple of questions about
dialog and engaging in dialogue with
people so the first issue that I face is
I have a very high need for intellectual
stimulation and I can't get that with
most people it's something like you can
you can have a dialogue for a time but
then titrate openness yeah and then I
would then they started run out of ideas
they can keep up and it sort of falls
apart
okay this is the problem that
intellectuals have quite frequently is
that they sort of once they start
reading difficult and rewarding stuff
yeah they stopped wanting to talk to
regular people and I think that
contributes to the disconnect that you
see between intellectuals and
working-class people and stuff like that
and the other question I had was about
okay wait I don't know if that's a
question I mean I believe there's a
question in there but I digress tchen is
how did we dress that how should I dress
it and is that something that can be
dressed well part of part of the answer
to that is that's what the universities
were for I mean you know not everybody
is equipped to or interested in engaging
in high-level discussion of abstract and
creative ideas you know you hear this
idea that everyone's creative that's a
lie it's as straightforward as that drew
creativity is very very rare and so and
if you happen to be a creative person or
if you happen to be someone who's
profoundly interested in ideas you are
in a
pronounced minority just as you are if
you happen to be extremely extroverted
or extremely agreeable or extremely
conscientious these are minority issues
and what you do is you find like-minded
people who are capable of engaging that
you know a heavy weight with heavy
weight weight lifters compete with heavy
weight weight lifters for a reason and
everyone thinks that's fine the same
thing applies to intellectual and
creative endeavors so what you do is you
try to find a community where that's
that's the nature of the community and
you likely have to find a relationship
like that as well you know so I don't
think so I think what contributes to the
siloing is the arrogance that goes along
with it because if you're you can be
interested in ideas and you can be
creative well that's the arrogance of
the intellect right that's the thing the
Catholic Church had warned about for
centuries is the arrogance of the
intellect so because if you're if you're
wise as well as smart and there is no
relationship between being smart and
being wise they are not the same thing
there's no quick pathway from smart to
wise and many of the people who I've
known who were very wise were what some
of them were intellectually impaired and
were still wise you know so it's the
arrogance that brings up the block and I
see this for example happening in the
United States in particular because the
last time I went down there for example
I was I had friends down there and and
some of those friends are very very
smart people and some of them were
talking about the Trump voters and they
were talking about the Trump voters with
contempt and I thought you better watch
that because that's 50% of the damn
population and it might be convenient to
think that they're stupid and beneath
you but it's not conducive to a civil
state and there's no evidence that it's
true because there isn't a straight line
between intelligent and wise and so I
think that if you're if your character
is developed and you're intelligent
you can have your siloed creative
community but you develop enough wisdom
so that you can see all the things that
people can do that are of high ethical
utility that are outside the
intellectual domain you know and I think
that's why in the New Testament I think
that's why Christ is a carpenter
right because well first of all
carpenter is one of those jobs that when
you're dishonest it manifests itself
immediately because what you build falls
down and so if you're an honest
carpenter you build a good house so that
there's a nice metaphor there but it's
also it's also a warning in some sense
against the the equation of intellectual
brilliance with moral superiority and so
if the intellects would drop their moral
superiority and fat chance there is of
that then that divide between the
working class say and the elite would
would resolve and there's every reason
to have respect for decent working class
people I mean it's on their labour as
the left wingers at least hypothetically
agree that the entire edifice of the
culture is is resting so you can have
your cake and eat it too but you have to
not assume that your niche makes you
superior and it's very difficult for
smart people especially smart there's a
scene in leeches it seems thus spake
Zarathustra wears arethusa the Prophet
comes down from the mountain and he
comes into a public square and there's
this crowd around this little
who's only about this high who have a
gigantic ear and everyone is marveling
at him well that's what the modern
intellect is like it's a with a
giant well mouth generally not an ear
and the the the being is underdeveloped
but the intellect is hyper activated and
and it makes the person extraordinarily
unbalanced and his part because they
they can't compete outside the
intellectual realm and that makes them
very bitter because they tend to think
well God I'm so smart everything should
just come to me it's like sorry that's
not how the world works and and it also
that that and that that that attitude is
immediately evident to people that
they're talking to when they talk in the
manner that they talk if they are
arrogant intellectuals of that sort
you see that in the Simpsons did a good
job of that with comic book guy right I
mean he
completely useless in every possible
dimension with an IQ of about 160 and
it's very annoying to people who have an
IQ of 160 that they can also be
completely useless but it happens a lot
so yeah hi dr. Peterson long time no see
how are you doing thanks so I was up
first going to ask about your thoughts
on a very popular TV show Rick and Marty
you know someone just recommended that
to me and they said they thought I would
find it funny and that makes me nervous
because I like the Simpsons and I like
the Trailer Park Boys for actually like
the trailer I really liked the Trailer
Park Boys and so someone said I know
it's so sad you know but they said that
I would like Rick and Morty so I'm kind
of afraid to even watch it it does have
a nihilistic theme to it no I would say
so that which is quite telling of the
young population which they flee they
fall in love with it everyone's talking
about it so uh-huh okay well I'll
definitely watch it because I've been
looking for something to watch when I'm
brain dead at night so but I decide to
tell them my question from a different
angle if I may and it's about the case
that governments let's say such as
Russia and Iran they have any more
extreme cases like Isis they do not want
to conform to the nihilistic aspects of
the West as a result they've taken an
anti-western approach as someone with a
Middle Eastern background I've been
trying to figure out where the origins
of this hostility more precisely comes
from and why things are the way they are
I recently found out that certain key
Iranian philosophers and political
activists were partially intuitively
responsible for the 1979 Iranian
Revolution were highly influenced by the
anti Western high daguerreian philosophy
and this is partially why they believed
that an Islamic state would and it'd be
messy and necessary counter position to
the ninth nihilistic Western thought you
I know that you also come there with
Alexander
dooking putting those liza yes except
Dugan doesn't really seem to have a
coherent answer he says that an answer
like that is necessary and that
hypothetically it's something that
Russia might be able to offer but the
details seem to me somewhat obscure I
mean the Russians maybe the Russians are
doing what Solzhenitsyn suggested and
returning to Orthodox Christianity
although Russia is corrupt enough so
that it's very difficult to tell from
the outside if that's mere collusion
between the corrupt church in a corrupt
state or if there's something genuine
going on there now you know the I would
say there's a question under your
question which is tyranny or nihilism
well that's a good question man that's a
good question well lots of people would
pick tyranny over nihilism and so if
that's the only choice that people are
offered then and I also think that
tyranny is stronger than nihilism
because what are you going to do
organize nihilists hardly well look at
look at what happened to what was that
thing in Central Park you know against
the 1% Jesus I mean what a dismal affair
that was we'd like things to be
different how well we don't know like so
you know you can just run over that if
you're tyrannical and organized you can
just run over that like there's nothing
there at all and that I think there is a
danger and I do think that we're
enticing the Islamofascists let's say by
our nihilistic weakness and I think more
than that I think that we're doing
something more than that because one of
the things that I've been curious about
and I'm going way out on a limb here is
I've been really interested in the
alliance between the neo-marxist
nihilistic are the neo-marxist
postmodernists especially the feminists
and the Islamofascists I just don't get
that it's like there's something very
very interesting going on there and I
think part of it is that when you when
you drift too far into the nihilistic
sub structure there's a huge call for
tyrannical order that manifests itself
unconsciously and so that's the dynamic
that I see playing out in that peculiar
relationship between the
modern neo-marxist feminists and
Islamofascists I don't I don't know
that's a very that's very interesting
that that's a very interesting idea that
you brought to mind I had no idea that
there was a relationship between
Heidegger and what happened in Iran in
the 1970s if you could send me a
citation about that or something to read
I'd be very interested in doing that so
okay yep yep
[Applause]
thank you that's that's that's the
closest thing I think I'll experienced
it out to arnold schwarzenegger actually
delivering that line yeah the purrito
distribution yeah yeah yeah not Ross but
yeah do you have to work oh it's a nasty
it's a nasty law yeah it was also known
as prices law yeah yeah yeah yeah great
yeah yeah yeah
hopefully there's fewer of them than
that okay two to two things the first is
it isn't obvious what the population
would be that you would compare this
population to
right because you could say well the
boundary is the four hundred people in
this room but it isn't necessarily the
case the four hundred people in this
room might be the square root of the
broader population we're interested in
this sort of thing but with the purrito
distribution what you also see is that
it's it's self similar and so let's say
there's four hundred people doing
something twenty of them are doing half
the work but if you take twenty four of
them are doing half the work of the
twenty and one of the four is doing half
the work of the four and so it's so why
am I telling you that it's it isn't it
well first of all it isn't that there
isn't useful work to be done at multiple
slices of the purrito distribution but
the other thing is it's also the case
that there's not only one purrito
distribution right because you might say
well if it's just the square root of the
number of people in a domain that are
doing half the work then you know what
do you do with the rest of the people
and the answer that might be well
they're in a prio different preeto
distribution as well where they're doing
something productive so
well I think it's a good question like
we don't exactly end so so the basic
rule is the look the basic rule is for
example if you take a hundred scientists
in a given domain ten of them will have
published half the papers and this works
with everything it works with with every
creative domain the rule applies so now
the question is why and I think the
choir the answer to that seems to be and
I've watched people who become
spectacular ly successful it what
happens is that zero is a really bad
place to be
right it's really hard to get out of
zero and that's often why people are
trapped in poverty because if you have
nothing getting to something is
virtually impossible once you have
something getting to a little more of
something is actually quite a bit easier
and so what seems to happen this is also
called the Mathieu principle right it's
the same principle so that's a New
Testament citation let's say the Mathieu
principle is to those who have
everything more will be given from those
who have nothing everything will be
taken that's another one of those lines
in the New Testament that you'd think
that a good editor would have just got
rid of so but but but I think what it is
is that every time you make a step
forward the probability that you'll be
able to take the next step forward
increases and it seems to increase in a
nonlinear way so the the world that the
Mathieu principle describes is nonlinear
you know so you might say well what's
your trajectory if you're moving upward
well it's not this it's this what's your
trajectory if you're moving downward
it's not this it's this right you fall
you fall you plummet you rise you rise
you transcend it's something like that
and you might say well that's a hell of
a world but whatever it has to be run by
some principle and that's the principle
that it appears to be run by yes
no no no it doesn't mean that at all
what it means is that every truth claim
you make including those that are
implicit in your actions carries with it
an ethic that justifies or doesn't
justify the action so for example let's
say I have a tool and I say it's an axe
and I go to the forest and I cut down I
try to cut down a tree with it and it
doesn't work it's not an axe it's
something else and so what the what
there's a good book on pragmatism called
the metaphysical Club a history of
American ideas it's what I would really
recommend and what the pragmatists I
can't give you a full answer because
this is such a complicated issue but
what the pragmatists were wrestling with
back in the late 1800s the late 1800s
this was William James and his crew in
in Boston
including a philosopher named CS purse
who was perhaps America's greatest
philosopher they were wrestling with the
same issue that the postmodernist would
wrestle with 100 years later which is
things are indefinitely complex and
we're not very bright so how is it that
we can make claims to truth about
anything and what they were what their
their hypothesis essentially was is that
with every action and with every truth
claim you simultaneously demarcate a
territory within which that claim is
valid and you you determine whether the
claim is valid by noting whether your
prediction about the outcome of your
action or your or your belief is
commencer is is in keeping with if the
outcome is in keeping with the
prediction then what you've said or done
is true or good enough and that's as
good as you get and so that's the
pragmatic perspective and then when when
when the pragmatist encountered charles
dark charles darwin's works works they
immediately recognized that darwin had
generated a pragmatic solution to the
problem of the impossibility of being
the impossibility of being is this
there's way more cosmos than there is
you you are going to die you cannot
generate a sufficient solution
to the problem of your being no one can
nothing can it's like the environment is
a snake that moves unpredictably across
time and you're trying to stay on its
back well as how how does the Darwinian
process deal with that it produces
infinite variance roughly speaking
almost all of which die and that's how
it solves the problem across time and
the things that exist is the things that
stay alive are true enough and that's
the best you get that's the argument I
was trying to have with Sam Harris
because Harris doesn't take his
evolutionary cycle is a Volusia nary
theory seriously enough but we get to
kept getting bogged down anyways that's
that's the best answer oh I'd like to
agree with that but it's not true
yeah yep yep yep you really do like to
ask hard questions so you I think it
depends see this is also why like the pH
alien take let's say on on pragmatism
because I think that pragmatism as a
philosophy has the limitation that you
just described but only if you think
about the games as limited if you have
to play the game in an iterative way
then that issue resolves itself and the
game theorists have done a good job of
mapping that out it's like you could say
let's say pragmatically speaking there's
no reason I shouldn't deceive you once
if I can get what I want
it's yeah yeah except that I'm probably
not only going to interact with you once
I'm going to interact with you a lot and
even if it isn't you that I interact
with it's going to be a bunch of beings
that are so much like you that it might
as well be you might as well be you it's
going to be me if nothing else and so
the pragmatic game stretched across time
would include the necessity of
iterability in relationship to the
validations of the truth claims that's
that's how it looks to me
I'm gonna I'm gonna I'm gonna stop you
if we have say that again yes yes thank
you yes but that's not all I am so this
is on behalf of somebody dr. Peterson
having listened to your expositions on
the mythological evolution and
amalgamation of religion and keeping in
mind your working definitions of belief
and truth and despite the obvious
reasons for somebody of your background
to identify most with Christianity my
understanding is that you believe
Christianity to be the most complete and
articulated form of many of the
metaphysical ideas that preceded it and
led up to that keeping that in mind
would it also be accurate to therefore
say that you're not only a believer in
Christianity but also if to a lesser
degree also believer in in Mourdock in
the ancient Egyptian gods and the
subsequent gods that you've spoken up
here that led up and contribute it to
the form of Christianity that you're
discussing and that you identify with
okay I'm going to take that one apart a
little bit I'm bounded in my judgment
with regards to Christianity by my
ignorance I'm no student of Hinduism so
I can't make the claim forthrightly that
there's something intrinsically superior
to the judeo-christian tradition because
I don't know enough to make that claim
the claim I can make is that there's
something that's dreadfully right about
this core elements of the
judeo-christian tradition and I've seen
analogues to that like one of the things
I'd like to do for example is to do a
short series on the Delta H Inc because
that is one remarkable document once you
know especially you might want to read
it you can go online and read it's very
short out etching ta o teh CH ing and
it's the fundamental text of Taoism and
once you know that the world of being is
made of chaos and order and you know
that that's represented
by the yin and the yang all of a sudden
you can understand the DAO de Jing and
it's just it's brilliantly simple and
straightforward in it's exposition but
it also seems to me to be entirely
commensurate with the line of of let's
call it logic it's more like a the the
mode of description of being that's
encapsulated in these stories now with
regards to being a believer people ask
me all the time two things say do you
believe in God and are you a Christian
and they answered without both of those
is actually there's two answers one is
what the hell makes you think it's any
of your business
that's the first answer and the second
is why do you think that you mean the
same thing with those questions that I
would mean with my answer so you know
what because it's such a funny thing
because I spent like three and this is
no accusation with regards to your
questions in the least you know I think
it's more about trying to detract the
development of these ideas and you know
the residual truth and so yeah
psychological significance of all these
other traditions I think well you know I
did I've been there
floored by other mythological structures
like when I first understood or thought
I understood the meaning of the
Mesopotamian creation method just I've
never recovered from that I would say
and the same thing is true of the
investigations I did into the Egyptian
myths of Horus and Isis and Osiris and
Seth it's just a and they're they're so
relevant I mean they're so unbelievably
relevant and how do how do see this is a
problem that none of us really know how
to solve it's like they're our sources
of wisdom all over the world let's say
and they need to be made commensurate
with one another which isn't to say that
they need to be turned into a fast-food
mall you know that's that's like
multiculturalism right it's like all the
food of the world served in the most
terrible possible manner all in one
place
and something like that and you don't
want to do that with comparative
religion it's just water everything down
and say well it's all nice it's like no
it is not nice yeah or that it's all the
same because it's not all the same so
the the job of communicating between
those domains of wisdom is really
continuing right it's been a problem
ever since the beginning of civilization
but it's continuing and I would say the
psychoanalyst Jung in particular was
took to huge huge steps in in the
direction of doing that an
extraordinarily positive way and not a
simple minded way at all and not just
hand waving that oh well it's everyone
has one and all shall have prizes not
that so yeah last question I choose it
kind of in the same vein but it's in
regards to another kind of mythology so
yeah in terms of I guess Carl Jung's own
with us sorry I'm extremely tall but a
lot of the I achieved I found some kind
of archetypes like for example in my own
life but also I've noticed in European
life so for example in regards to Odin
and Norse mythology yeah with Corleone
si I've only been able to actually skim
it because I've been like trying to find
something like because I felt like
there's always this kind of psyche that
was almost underneath I guess Western
civilization and we see it really like
embodied in this specific figure this
deity the wanderer the knowledge
gatherer the seeker but he's also a war
goddess these all these different
aspects that are an accumulation of what
seems to be something that's distinctly
Western mm-hm
and I feel this is like almost like this
symbol in a way of course it's not
always followed there seems to be
something maybe there seems to be
something I do think that the idea of
the individual has been articulated most
fully in the West I don't think that's
really a I don't think that's a
contentious claim actually that doesn't
mean that the latent structures from
which that idea might emerge weren't
also many other places simultaneously
and the other thing from let's say from
a biological perspective is that we're
only talking about differences of a few
hundred years in terms of the
manifestation of these ideas right from
from an evolutionary perspective that's
it's instantaneous
it's like well a new idea has to arise
somewhere so
is going to be somewhere first and but
it's spreading I mean Christianity for
example spread so rapidly that it's
absolutely beyond belief and it is
actually spreading more rapidly in China
now than it did in ancient Rome
so well in regards to that it's also
been seen like almost in the wake of a
dying Christianity I've noted that like
there's been a tendency to go towards I
guess paganism right yes I understand
the like some people laugh at all yes we
have Wicca which was mainly a
manifestation of Aleister Crowley in his
works which were then ended off to
whoever actually made the actual
ideology and then next thing you know
we're finding something almost more
stable in I guess Norse mythology and it
seems like it's acting almost as a
pendulum school swing from something
that well people are good like the thing
is is when one when one mythological
structure collapses it's going to
collapse into another mythological
structure or another set of mythological
structures and and because you can't get
out of the mythological structures
there's no possible way of doing that
what and so I wouldn't say necessarily
that the fact that other belief systems
emerge in the aftermath of the collapse
of the overarching belief system I don't
think that that's necessarily a bad idea
I think that it has its attendant
dangers and so I should stop because I'm
starting to get tired and I'm not going
to be able to formulate any clearer
answers than that and it's also 10
o'clock so we also do have to stop
oh yes there is an unofficial Meetup and
discussion group at Hemingway's
restaurant second floor 142 Cumberland
Street just say you're with the Jordan
Peterson discussion group yes everyone
is invited if you say you're with the
Jordan Peterson discussion group
please don't misbehave too badly
[Applause]