[Music]
thank you very much
hahahaha thank you very much for showing
up again that's a really good to see
everybody here so one of the things that
I've been realizing as a consequence of
going through these stories is that the
degree to which they're about
individuals is quite remarkable and I
think that's really telling you know one
of the reasons I prefer Dostoevsky to
Tolstoy is because Tolstoy is more of a
sociologist he's more interested in the
relationship between groups of people
this is an oversimplification because
obviously Tolstoy is a great author but
I like dusty husky better because he
really delves into the souls of
individuals and I think it's remarkable
the degree to which all of the stories
that we've covered so far in Genesis are
about individuals and they're quite
realistic which is quite remarkable -
they're not really romanticized to any
great degree because all of the people
that are regard as regarded let's say as
patriarchal or matriarchal figures in
Genesis have no shortage of ethical if
no shortage of ethical flaws and also no
shortage of difficulties in their life
and the difficulties are realistic there
they're major-league problems you know
like familial catastrophes and famine
and war and revenge and hatred and all
those things it's not a it's not a
pretty it's not a pretty book and that's
one of the things that makes it great I
mean that's one of the things that
characterizes great literature right is
that it doesn't present you with a
whitewashed view of humanity or of
existence and that's really a relief I
think because as you all know because
you're alive there's no such thing as a
whitewash existence like you're to be
alive is to be in trouble
ethically and existentially I've been
reading this book recently
I'll talk about it a little bit later
it's called better never to have a bean
and it was written by a philosopher
in South Africa in Cape Town name
Benatar that's his last name and he
basically argues I think it's a specious
argument and I think it's artificially
constructed but he basically argues that
because life is so full of suffering
even good lives are very much full of
suffering that it's wrong to bring
children into the world because the
suffering outweighs the good even in
good lives and it's actually wrong it
would also be better not to exist for
exactly the same reason and my sense in
reading the book is that he came to that
conclusion and then wrote the book to
justify it which is actually the reverse
of the way that you should write a book
what you should do when you're writing a
book is you should have a question and
you should it should be a real question
right it should be one you don't know
the answer to and then you should be
studying and writing like mad and
reading everything you can get your
hands on to see if you can actually
grapple with the problem and come to
some solution and you should walk the
reader as well through your process of
thinking so that they can come to the
well not necessary to the same
conclusion but at least track what
you're doing and I don't think that's
what he did I think he wrote it
backwards but then and so I was thinking
about it a lot because that's actually a
question that I've contended with in my
writing there are Memphis da Philly and
our satanic figures for example in girth
is Faust and also Ivan in in that in the
brothers karamasoff who basically make
the same case you know that existence is
so rife with trouble and suffering that
it would be better if it didn't exist at
all and the problem I've had with that
there's a variety of them but one of the
problems I've had with that is what
happens if you start to think that way
because what I've observed is that
people who begin to think that way that
isn't where they stop like that they get
angry at existence which is what
happened to Cain as we saw in the Cain
and Abel story and then the next step is
to start taking revenge against
existence and that cascades until it's
revenge against well I think the best
way of thinking about it is revenge
against God for the crime of being which
is I think the deepest sort of hatred
that
can entertain and and and when you're in
the grip of a really deep emotion like a
really profound emotion right at the
bottom of emotions you're in something
that's like a quasi-religious state and
that's more or less independent of your
belief saying a transcendent deity I
mean you can be in a profoundly
emotional state that's as deep as it can
be and it can have religious
significance without that necessarily
signifying anything about a transcendent
being you know but but then I was
thinking you see the problem with that
argument is you can gerrymander it
endlessly you know because first of all
how do you measure suffering and how do
you measure happiness it's like how do
you assign weights to them and god
there's just no way of doing that you
have to do it arbitrarily and so you can
make an argument that the suffering
outweighs the happiness you just wait
the suffering more heavily than you wait
the happiness and that's the end of that
you know and so that's that's a problem
but I think there's a deeper problem and
I was reading this other book while back
as well which was written by the guy who
ran the human genome project and I don't
remember exactly what it was called but
it was something like a scientists case
for God is something like that and one
of the things he referred to which
didn't strike me as hard as it should
have to begin with was the he thought
that one of the phenomena say that
justified a belief in a transcendent
being was something like the moral
intuition of human beings that you know
we have a sense of right and wrong and
you know it's certainly in what happens
in Genesis in the story of Adam and Eve
is that that that story announces the
coming of the sense of right and wrong
right the knowledge of good and evil and
it isn't something we ascribe to animals
it's something that's unique to human
beings animals can be predators and you
know and they can be gentle and and you
can have a relationship with them but
you never think of an evil cat or you
know or an evil wolf even though they're
you know they're predatory about human
beings we have this capacity to judge
between good and evil right and wrong
and it's really an integral part of our
being and I think you can make an
evolutionary case for that a biological
case for that as you can
make a biological case for most of what
is relevant about human beings because
we're biological creatures but we don't
really understand the significance of
that like what happens in the story of
Adam and Eve is that that's that
realization not coming to the knowledge
of good and evil is actually represented
as a shift of cosmic significance right
it puts a it puts a permanent fracture
in the structure of being and you know
if you think of human beings as
insignificant ants on a tiny dust mote
in the middle of an infinite cosmos
cosmos that cares less for us then who
cares fundamentally if human beings have
the knowledge to distinguish between
good and evil but if you give
consciousness a central role in being
and you can make a perfectly reasonable
case for that because without
consciousness there's no being as far as
anyone can determine so it may be much
more central than we think and and I
really don't think there's a
counter-argument to that like not a
solid one you can state that
consciousness is epiphenomena land and
that the world is fundamentally
materialistic and it doesn't matter that
there's consciousness you can state that
but you can make an equally credible
case the other way and certainly our
lived experience is that consciousness
is crucial obviously and we treat each
other as if most of the time we're
valuable conscious beings and we
wouldn't give up our consciousness even
though it's often consciousness of
suffering and so then I think another
problem with the book is that it's it's
sort of predicated on the idea that life
is for happiness and I don't think
that's right and I don't think that's
how people experience life and I might
be wrong but it seems to me that people
experience life as something like a
series of crucial ethical decisions it's
something like that I mean when I just
can't imagine maybe I'm being naive
about this but I can't imagine that I
can't imagine another being that's like
me in in most senses that isn't
constantly wrestling in some sense with
what the next proper thing to do is it's
not like it's obvious it's not bloody
obvious and it
doesn't mean you'll do the right thing
because you don't law lots of times and
you know that by your own judgement
right because you're making mistakes all
the time
sometimes you don't know what you're
doing and maybe it's a mistake and maybe
it isn't and who's to say that isn't
what I'm talking and what I'm talking
about when you know that what you're
doing is wrong and you go ahead and do
it anyways people do that all the time
and that's also extremely peculiar you
bloody well think that if you knew it
was wrong and you told yourself that it
was wrong that that would be sufficient
so that you just wouldn't do it but that
isn't what you're like at all you know
and you can tell yourself something is
wrong a fifty times and you'll do it the
51st time and then you'll feel you know
like like you deserve to feel probably
and but it doesn't stop you and so so
then I think the other problem with the
viewpoint the idea that the suffering of
life eradicate sits utility is that it's
predicated on the idea that happiness or
lack of suffering even is is the right
criteria by which to judge life and I
don't think that's how we actually
experience life I think what we do
instead is put ourselves through a
series of excruciating moral choices you
know when one of the things that that's
really significant about the biblical
stories and I think about the the entire
implicit philosophy you know that's
embedded in the stories is that that's
how life is presented in in the stories
is all of these individuals first
they're individuals - not groups and
second they're agonizing over their
moral choices all the time all the time
and they have a relationship with God
and but it's not a it's not a directive
relationship exactly even for the people
to whom God speaks directly which I
suspect is not something you'd exactly
want to have happen is it's there's
still even the fact that they have a
direct relationship with God doesn't
stop them from being tormented
continually by their moral choices and
so the world is presented as a moral
landscape not as a not as a place that
justifies itself by happiness it's
presented as a moral landscape and
people are presented as
preachers who traverse through the moral
landscape making ethical decisions that
determine the course of the world and
that seems to me to be right and that's
not a that's not the same as happiness
by any stretch of the imagination it's a
whole different category of being and
you know and then I thought that through
a lot and I think well we do make
choices and what we do is contend with
the future you know and that the future
seems to appear to us as a realm of
possibility that's a more accurate way
of thinking about it then then that the
future presents itself to it to us as a
realm of determined things it's it's
presents itself as a realm of
possibility and there's good choices in
that realm and there's poor choices or
even evil choices in that realm and
we're negotiating continually deciding
which of those choices we're going to
bring into being that seems to me to be
phenomenologically indisputable and we
certainly treat each other as if that's
what we're doing because we hold each
other responsible for our actions you
know with some exceptions and that we're
deciding each moment whether to make
things better or worse and that seems to
me to be correct and I think that that's
what these stories illustrate they don't
say that directly you know although I
think it gets more and more explicit as
the narrative unfolds but and then part
of the realism of the stories is that
the people aren't the people that are
being presented are by no means good I
mean maybe with the exception of Noah no
one seemed to be a pretty good guile
they did he did get drunk and you know
and and end up naked exposed to his sons
and so forth and but I mean he isn't
talked about a lot as a character it's a
pretty compressed story but Abraham I
mean Abraham had plenty of problems not
least of which was in his inability to
leave home and then you know his lying
about his wife and their there's all
sorts of mistakes and then Jacob who
were going to talk about tonight is an
even more morally ambivalent character
he's especially at the beginning of the
story he's
it's it's he isn't the sort of person
that you would pick out especially if
you were a hack writer you wouldn't pick
him out as the hero of the story he does
a lot of things that are really pretty
reprehensible
and takes him an awful long time to
learn better and yet he's the person
who's put forward as the father of the
12 tribes of Israel it's from this
flawed person that the people that that
may be that whose story you might say is
that the fundamental constitutes the
fundamental underpinning of our culture
it's it's from this deeply flawed
individual that that group emerges and
so you might think of that as a relief
to because you know you're no knight in
shining armor you know with with a with
a pure moral past I mean people make
mistakes of catastrophic proportions
non-stop you know and that also means
that these stories put forward something
approximating hope because in their
realism in their moral realism they
present heroes I suppose the heroes of
renown right the patriarchs of old let's
say who are realistic people who have
fits of anger and rage and who are
murderous at times and who are deeply
deeply embroiled with family dispute and
and who who have adulterous affairs and
and like they do all the terrible things
that people do and the weird thing is is
that God is still with them and you know
it isn't obvious what that means or even
if it means anything but it's very it's
not disputable as far as I can tell that
a were conscious and that consciousness
is a transcendent phenomena which which
we do not understand and that the
landscape that we traverse through is
moral like every story you ever watch
anything that grips your imagination on
the screen or in the theater like any
story that grabs you is a story of moral
striving it's just not interesting
otherwise right the person has to be
confronted with complex moral choices
and then you see the outcome and you
know the good guy doesn't
and the bad guy does it badly and things
don't go so well for the bad guy
generally and if it's a bit more
sophisticated than good and the bad are
in the same individual and that's you
know that's a more compelling story but
so we could say well let's we could make
the assumption that it might be
worthwhile thinking of the world as a as
it has been thought of classically as a
theater upon which the forces of good
and evil continually strive for
dominance and I for the life of me
especially after I started reading
deeply into 20th century history and all
the terrible things that happened in the
20th century and all the terrible
unbelievably incomprehensible things
that people did to one another
I just couldn't see seeing things any
other way is realistic you know because
I don't think that you can immerse
yourself in 20th century history without
coming to the conclusion that evil is a
reality and if it's a reality that it
depends on what you mean by reality but
it's fundamental enough reality for me
and if it's a reality then I don't see
how you can escape from the conclusion
that the cosmos as we experience it at
least is a place of moral striving and
well that's one of the things that's
really illustrated in the story of Jacob
and and I found that quite striking so
so the last time last lecture I ended
with the Abrahamic stories with the
death of Sarah and that was Abraham's
wife and so we're gonna continue from
from there remember Abraham had a son
Isaac and he was asked by God to
sacrifice his son which we talked about
in in some depth and I was attempting to
make the case that you know the idea of
sacrifice was one of humankind's great
discoveries because it meant the
discovery of the future essentially but
it also meant the discovery that the
future was something that you could make
a bargain with and that you could give
up something now something impulsive
some pleasure even a deep pleasure in
the moment and you could strive and
hypothetically you could make a covenant
a bargain with the future and if your
sacrifices were acceptable and that
seemed to mean an ethically acceptable
you had to sacrifice the right thing
that that vastly increased the
probability that not only you would be
successful let's say but that your
descendants would be too and I don't
think that that's an irrational
proposition I mean you have to leave in
it a bit with the realization that
sometimes you know you get sliced off at
the knees no matter what right because
life has an arbitrary element and and
that can't be tossed out but building in
the arbitrary element will say you still
want to think well what's your best bet
given a certain amount of randomness and
it seems to me that conscious self-aware
sacrifice and proper ethical striving is
your best bet and you know there's
another idea that well I've always
explained it when I've explained it to
people I've always used the movie
Pinocchio as an example you know that
when Geppetto was trying to make his
puppet into a self-aware and autonomous
moral agent which is what he wants above
all else you know he aims at the highest
good that he can conceive which is the
star that he prays to essentially and
hopes for the transformation and there's
also something in that that's
unutterably profound and maybe that is
somewhat independent of the idea that
you
have to believe in God I would also say
that what it means to believe in God in
the old testament is by no means clear
and that's something I also really want
to talk about tonight it's not obvious
what it means and well Gepetto what he
does at least is aim at the highest good
of which he can conceive you know and
that that's actually in a philosophical
definition of God upon occasion that God
is the highest good of which you
conceive and you know that's different
than the idea of a transcendent being
precisely but it's in line with it's in
line with certain interesting
psychoanalytic speculations this is one
of the things I really liked about Carl
Jung you know
Jung was so radical a thinker it's just
beyond belief like I've read a lot of
critics of you and I've always I've
always got too kicked out of them
because the things they accused Jung of
are so trivial compared to the things
that Jung actually did that it's like
accusing a murderer of jaywalking like
because Jung was unbelievably radical
like here's one of his ideas you know he
thought that it was necessary he
believed that psychotherapy could be
replaced by a supreme moral effort and
so the moral effort would be something
like aiming after good and then trying
to integrate yourself around that and
that the the good at which you aimed
would be something approximating what
you would be like if you manifested your
full potential and that you have a
glimmering of what that full potential
was so that would be the potential
future you and he thought of that he
thought of people as four dimensional
entities especially essentially that
were stretched across time and that you
as a totality across time including your
potential manifested yourself also in
the here and now and that part of what
your potential manifested itself was
something like the voice of conscious
conscience or intuition
it's amazing idea it's an amazing idea
right because it's like what you could
be in the future beckons to you in the
present and helps you determine the
difference between good and evil
it's a mind-boggling idea and you know I
think that it's an idea you have to
contend with and then he went further
than that and this is this is also
remarkable idea you know he was
interested in this symbolic
representation of Christ and I mean
psychologically speaking and he thought
of Christ as the representation of the
ideal potential human it's something
like that so it was a symbolic rip thats
what Christ was is a symbolic
representation of the ideal potential of
a human being and so for young there was
no difference between there was no
psychological difference between who you
could be in the future beckoning to you
and the prey in the present and
orienting yourself in relationship to
Christ
psychologically those were the same
thing and then so that's a pretty
mind-boggling idea like seriously that's
a mind-boggling idea you know especially
when you add the psychological idea that
the one of the things that characterizes
your ideal future self is the ability to
make sacrifices right and the deeper the
sacrifice the better and then also to
recover from the sacrifice right so
that's the death and rebirth so the part
of you that's most essential to your
full flowering as a as a being is your
ability to let things go and then spring
back from that so to die in some sense
and to be reborn in the service of a
higher good and then well then the next
part of that is that the direction of
the world depends on you doing that so
not only your own life but your family's
life and and because we're networked so
intently together you know that the
whole panoply of humankind that may be
the structure of the of the cosmos and
you know you might think well no but you
know it's not so simple it's not so
simple first of all one person can wreak
an awful lot of havoc there's absolutely
no doubt about that and as we get more
technologically powerful that becomes
even more relevant and important and and
and crucial you know one of the things
that Young said was that we had to wake
up because we are too technologically
powerful to be as morally asleep as we
are and that seems to me just to be
self-evident that's yeah for sure that's
true we're we're we're half asleep with
nuclear bombs it's not a good idea it's
seriously not a good idea and so
well and then you might ask yourself -
you don't well like what is the ultimate
potential of a fully developed human
being and well we certainly know that
you have admiration for people who are
more developed rather than less
developed that's that just happens
automatic or resentment that but that's
okay it's the same thing it doesn't
matter but it's not like you can't
identify them you can identify them you
know and and they're put forward to you
in in in drama and fiction and all of
that constantly so that's another form
of moral intuition you know you can
write you can discern the wheat from the
chaff let's say and and so the other
thing that I was thinking about that's
worth consideration too is that you know
and maybe this is maybe this is petty
but I don't think it is somebody asked
me the other day if I believed in
miracles and I hate being asked
questions like that you know and you
know it's also people ask me do I
believe in God and like I don't know
what they mean when they say that and so
I don't know what the answer because I
don't think we're talking necessarily
going to talk about the same thing but
in any case I said yes and I have a
variety of reasons for that but one of
them is that you know the consensus
among physicists is that we can track
the origin of the cosmos to something
like a hundred millionth of a millionth
of a second after the Big Bang it's like
it's so close to the Big Bang that the
difference is literally infinitesimal
but the consensus is that before that
whatever that is the laws of physics
themselves break down well what what do
you call an event that exists outside
the laws of physics that by definition
that's a miracle now that doesn't
necessarily mean that there's a
transcendent Adi
that caused the event that's a separate
issue but it does imply a barrier of
some sort beyond which we can't go where
some other set of rules apply
and so I find that interesting as well
so all right so Sarah dies and Abraham
makes a bargain with the Hittites to
purchase a burial place for her and they
offer it as a gift and he insists upon
paying for it it's a little story that
basically indicates two things that
Abraham was the kind of guy that you
trust pretty much when you see him and
that even if something is offered to him
as a gift he's going to do everything to
be reciprocal about it and and so it's
not a massively important part of the
story but it's it's in keeping with the
same narrative flow and so Efron who's a
hit I'd offer Zabar you'll place as a
gift and Abraham says no you know you
have to let me pay for it and Efrain
says he will and that works out very
well and so he has a good burial place
for his wife and then Abraham decides
that Isaac needs a wife and so he sends
his eldest servant to Mesopotamia to
find a wife for Isaac and there's a
strange ritual that's performed so it
says in the story that the servant
places his hand under Abraham's thigh to
to swear but that isn't really what it
means it means that he places his hand I
don't know exactly how to say this
properly well use your imagination how
about that and the idea is that as far
as I can tell that he's swearing on the
future he's swearing on future people
it's something like that so that's
that's sort of what testified means
right think about the route well I'm not
kidding I'm not kidding that is what it
that's that is the derivation right it
is the derivation so so so anyways this
is a serious issue and so that servant
has to go and find Isaac a good wife and
he wants him to find Isaac wife who
is willing to accept the same
fundamental belief system which is
something like the belief in a god
that's a unity rather than a plurality
you know the other thing that Jung was
very insistent upon was that there was a
relationship between polytheism and
psychological confusion and monotheism
and psychological unification I really
like that idea too that you know that
what you're trying to do because you are
a plurality that that's one of the
things the psychoanalysts we're really
good at figuring out that the cognitive
scientists haven't touched yet as far as
I could tell they're way behind the
psychoanalysts in that element of
thinking is that you are composed of sub
personalities which all have their own
desires and their own viewpoint their
own thoughts and their own perceptions
and they're in a war with each other
constantly
maybe even a Darwinian war it's been
it's been portrayed that way by certain
neuroscientists and that that one of the
goals of life is to integrate all of
that plurality into a hierarchical
ethical structure that has some
canonical ethic at the pinnacle right
we've talked a little bit about that and
it's not obvious what should be at the
pinnacle but we can guess at it it's
it's that which we admire that's one way
of thinking about it it's that that
describes fair play across a sequence of
games that's another good way of
thinking about it it's it's the heroic
ideal that's another way of thinking
about it but it's it's combined with
generosity you know because the hero the
mythological hero goes out into the
unknown and slays the dragon and gets
the gold but then comes back to the
community and distributes what's found
and so it's courage plus generosity and
and so all of your all of that interior
struggling that you're doing is an
attempt to bang yourself against the
world with challenge constantly to hit
everything together like you're beating
on a piece of iron to to to cure it
let's say so that you don't you're not
an internal contradiction you're not
massive competing gods something like
that because it's just too
psychologically stressful and
hard on everyone else and impossible for
them to get along with you if you're one
thing one moment and another thing
another moment and so so anyways Abraham
insists that Isaac find a wife from
among people who are likely to carry off
forward the monotheistic tradition and
I'm not sure that the monotheistic
tradition is actually indistinguishable
is actually distinguishable from the
individualistic tradition I think they
might be the same thing at different
levels of analysis you know so because
individual means undivided in some sense
right to be an individual means to be
one thing and the other thing that
mitigates against the idea of life as
happiness is it isn't obvious to me that
it's happiness that is what molds you
and shapes you you know it's something
more like optimal challenge voluntarily
undertaken it's something like that
right and I think that's echoed in the
idea that everyone has a moral
obligation to raise their cross
something like that to accept the fact
of their mortality voluntarily I believe
that that's the case and I do actually
think that that's a prerequisite to
proper psychological development because
if you're not willing to take your
mortality on voluntarily like if you're
kicking and fighting about it constantly
and you have every reason to don't get
me wrong then you can't act forthrightly
in the world right you're going to be
afraid and when you're afraid then you
can't voluntarily take on a challenge
and then if you can't take voluntarily
take on a challenge then you can't
develop and so again the life seems to
be something like if it's a proper life
is the voluntarily voluntary taking on
of great challenges and maybe that's
better than happiness like it's
certainly more noble you know it's not a
word we use very much anymore the idea
of nobility because we're so obsessed
with happiness but I think happiness is
a like if it comes along man great you
know wonderful don't don't take it
lightly or for granted because it's
fleeting but the idea that that's what
you should be for in some sense - seems
to me if that's what life is for then
maybe it shouldn't be maybe that's
correct because that isn't what life is
but
so doesn't it isn't obvious to me that
that's what life should be you know I
mean if you really loved someone like
like your son let's say what do you say
well I hope he has a happy life or would
you say I hope he accomplishes great
things it seems to me that that's better
the accomplishing of great things and
because that's admirable you know it's
like a happy person is a happy person
but a noble person is an admirable
person and and that's that's better man
and so maybe there are better things
than happiness and so you can't judge
being on the basis of the ratio of
suffering to pleasure something like
that it's and I don't think we do that I
don't believe we do that I mean
comedians are happy right but everyone
doesn't aspire to be a comedian and you
don't watch comedy all the time even
though you could laugh non-stop more or
less if the comedian's funny you want to
get your teeth into something it also
seems to me that this is one of the
reasons I like the existential
philosophy was that you know the
existentialist believed it's sort of an
original sin idea they believed that we
came into the world with an ethical
burden already laden upon us something
like something like that and that we had
a felt sense that it was necessary for
us to justify our being and if we didn't
do that then we weren't authentic to
ourselves we weren't moving towards
individuality
we weren't sustaining the community we
weren't living properly and that and
that that idea was deeply embedded in
people as part of their ordinary
experience and that also seems to me to
be accurate and you know I've dealt with
lots of people say in my clinical
practice and they don't really cut they
are they will come and say I wish I
wasn't so unhappy but they don't usually
come and say I wish I was happier and
those things aren't the same and and
then when we when you talk to people who
are having trouble you know they want to
straighten things out and figure out how
to do them right it's something like
that and and that that's the primary
that's their primary goal and
so anyways Abraham sends his eldest
servant off to his the place that God
has granted him to find a wife and
interestingly the borders of the
promised land are quite similar to the
current borders of Israel in these are
estimates right based on on the biblical
and I mean that's not a fluke obviously
but it's it's interesting to see the
concordance between these ancient
stories and the present-day world so I
thought that was very interesting and it
shows once again that the past you think
the past is the past but it's not it's
it's still here it's embedded in the
present you know just like the future
and somehow in some ways is folded up
inside the present waiting to unfold the
past is all folded up inside the present
too so anyways the servant goes to the
land that he's been charged to go to and
and he's trying to figure out how in the
world am I going to find a good wife for
Isaac I mean I don't know any of these
people and so he has this little
dialogue that's presented in the form of
a prayer I suppose and he thinks well
I'm gonna go to the place where you
water where people get water and water
the animals and because that's a place
where everyone gathers so that's a good
place to find someone and and it's it's
not a place of fun and lightness and
relaxation and impulsivity it's a place
of life-sustaining work and and he
thinks something like well what would a
decent girl do at a watering place and
he thought well maybe she would offer a
stranger some water and also offer to
water the camels because that would be
brave to approach the stranger and then
generous and then indicative of the
willingness to make an effort and when
you know that a camel I think he took
ten camels was quite a few camels
anyways
just one and that a camel can drink 20
gallons of water and Rebecca who was
drawing water from the wet turns out to
be Rebecca I was drawing water from the
well which is hard right because water
is heavy and you have to lift it up and
it's ten camels and so that's like 200
gallons of waters so you know she has to
put herself out a fair a bit in order to
make this stranger happy and so that's
what happens and then the servant has
brought along gifts and that sort of
thing and anyways to make a long story
short Rebecca
agrees to come back to come back with
the servant and huh marry Isaac and so
then she has she gets pregnant and she
has twins and this is an interesting
thing the twins fight inside her she can
tell that that they're not getting along
and this is an echo right it's an echo
of Cain and Abel and there's a
mythological motif that the unions have
called the hostile brothers the hostile
brothers and you see them all the time
Batman and the Joker are hostile
brothers and Thor and Loki or hostile
brothers and it's an unbelievably common
motif and you know the ultimate hostile
brothers are Christ and Satan so that's
the that's the archetypal representation
of the hostile brothers right the
ultimate good and the ultimate evil and
so and so it's an echo of the cain and
abel story although it's a little more
complex I would say from a literary
point of view because it isn't obvious
which of these brothers is Cain and
which of them is Abel they have parts of
both in each of them so Esau who turns
out to be one of the brothers in Jacob
movie turns out to be the other both
have their admirable qualities and their
faults anyways Esau comes is born first
but Jacob has him by the heel and so
there was a fight within the womb to see
who would emerge first now that's
relevant because the firstborn had a
special status well has a special status
in many communities especially
agricultural communities and there's a
reason all these people were more herds
people but if you divide your
property equally among all your children
then in like three generations everybody
has one goat and everybody starves to
death you know or the same thing happens
with lands so one of the ways that that
traditional communities solve that is
they just give them almost everything to
the firstborn and then the everyone else
knows well you go out and do whatever
you can and it's kind of arbitrary and
unfair but you know at least it's
predictably arbitrary and unfair
instead of doom over for generations you
know so it actually mattered to be the
firstborn and and God generally favors
the firstborn and then you might think
well what is it about being born first
that's so relevant apart from the the
cultural practice of abort generous
inheritance and I would say well the
firstborn is something like the model
for the leader of the family right
because the firstborn child should be if
there's a number of siblings they should
take care of the siblings at least to
some degree but also should be a role
model for them so it's like a natural
position of leadership but there's a
site there's a cycle psychologize ation
of the idea of the firstborn in these
stories because god often passes over
the firstborn in favor of a later born
child he seems to do that on the basis
of moral character essentially and so
there's this idea that well there's a
natural proclivity towards leadership
that's just a biological fact that would
be associated with being a firstborn but
there's a element of characterological
development that transcends that and so
that you it's more important to be
spiritually a firstborn let's say than
to be biologically a firstborn and God
recognizes that continually in these
stories and inverts the natural order
and favors a later born who's who's done
more work with regards to
characterological development and that's
also interesting to you know I've talked
to lots of business people about
leadership and there's a literature on
leadership but it's not a good
literature it's it's pretty shallow
partly because it's not that easy to
define leadership and partly because
there are different you know you people
have different temperaments
and different temperaments can be
leaders they just do it in different
ways
now there's something in common about
being a leader though and I would say
one is that if you're an actual leader
you actually know where you're going
right because what are you gonna do lead
people in circles it's like maybe
they'll follow you but you're not a
leader you're just a charlatan so you
have to know where you're going and then
you have to be able to communicate that
and then people have to trust you so you
actually have to be honest because
people are at that stupid at least not
for a long period of time and then where
you're going has to have some value
because otherwise why would anyone want
to go along with you so and then you
might say well what what are the
attributes then that make you a leader
and I would say well they're
characterological fundamentally and this
is not naive optimism or or or casual
moralizing it has nothing to do with
that you know we know for example that
conscientiousness that the personality
trait is a good predictor of long-term
success in in most occupations not all
but most and that one of the things
that's associated with conscientiousness
is that people keep their word they're
trustworthy and that's certainly one
element of a leader especially across
any reasonable amount of time you have
to be able to trust the person they can
even be harsh right it doesn't matter
because you can see harsh leaders and
kind leaders but as long as they do what
they say they will do then then you can
follow them and you know that the future
payoff is is is secure something like
that so the idea that character logical
development is more important to
leadership than primogenitor I think
that's the right word primal Genesis
anyways being a firstborn that's a very
crucial psychological realization that
it's character logical development that
makes you favored of God you know and I
do think we've forgotten this in many
ways because there isn't a lot of
emphasis in our education system on
characterological development and that's
very very surprising to me I think maybe
it's partly because in our fractured
society we can't agree on what
constitutes a reasonable
characterological goal so we just throw
up our hands and don't educate our kids
to any degree at all especially in
schools about what an admirable person
is like or even let them know that well
maybe you should actually try to be one
you know that that's actually the most
important possible thing that you could
learn right
[Applause]
so and I also think and I think this is
laid out very thoroughly in the biblical
stories as well is that if there are
enough people who are admirable then
things work and if there aren't and
things things are terrible
you get wiped out you remember when
Abraham is bargaining with God with
regards to Sodom and Gomorrah he asks
God to save the city if there's like 40
admirable people right respectable but
let's say admirable right I don't want I
don't want to say good because good is
being corrupted in some sense by casual
usage I mean admirable noble people
right I think Abraham bargains got down
to like ten if there's ten of them in
the city the city won't be destroyed and
that that's not very many in this city
so there's an interesting idea there
which is that there there doesn't have
to be that many people in a group who
have their act together but zero is the
wrong number and if it's zero then then
we're seriously in trouble
and I think that goes along with the
idea of the Pareto principle in
economics too which is that it's a small
minority of people who do most of the
productive work in any given domain but
so so a small number of properly
behaving people might have enough of an
impact to keep everything moving and
that might also that might actually be
true but it can't fall below some
crucial level and I do think that we're
in some danger of allowing it to fall
below some crucial level because our
society seems to be at war in some ways
against the idea of the individual and
individual character per se and I think
that's absolutely I think that's
absolutely catastrophic and that's part
of the reason that I'm doing these
biblical lectures you know because I
think that I've known for a long time
that the moral presuppositions of a
culture are instantiated in its stories
they're not instantiated in its explicit
philosophy there might be a layer of
explicit philosophy and of course there
is in the West and a layer of explicit
law but underneath that there are
stories and there isn't anything under
the stories except maybe behavior you
know and
that's so implicit it doesn't even
actually count it's not a cognitive
operation and so this is the story these
are the stories that are underneath our
culture and so there better be something
to them that's what we hope and but more
importantly maybe we shouldn't toss them
away without knowing what they mean
because if we toss them away then we're
throwing everything that we depend on
away as far as I can tell and we'll we
will pay for it we'll pay for it
individually because we'll be weak you
know because if you're not firm in your
convictions then someone else who's firm
in their convictions can you're their
puppet like instantly and then you're
also the puppet of your own doubts right
because unless you have convictions
you're gonna generate doubts like mad
because everyone does and then the
doubts win and and you'll be paralyzed
because there'll be you know 50% of you
moving forward and 50% of you frozen
stiff and that'll be enough just to
lodge you in place and so okay so
there's a psychologize ation of the idea
of leadership which is very important
and then it's associated with the idea
of character or logical development and
it's associated with the idea of
struggle not happiness and it's also
associated with this Abrahamic idea
which I really liked and which was
something that's been very useful to me
as a consequence of doing these lectures
because remember at the beginning of the
Abrahamic stories abraham's like a
stay-at-home guy right he's like the guy
who's 40 years old living in his in his
in his mother's basement and god says
like get the hell out of there you know
get out in the world where you belong go
do something difficult because what
you're doing isn't acceptable and you
know the first thing he does is go
somewhere there's a terrible famine and
then he goes somewhere there's a tyranny
so you know it's it's pretty funny he
follows God's call and it's not like
sweetness and light and paradise
immediately it's nothing like that it's
it's instantaneous combat you know of
the most difficult kind so but but
Abraham does in fact follow that impulse
and you know it's interesting too I mean
I don't know here's another thing that
made me a really an advocate of
psychoanalytic thinking and it was the
sort of thing that started to terrify me
about what the human psyche was out
like I started to understand that not
only were we like an amalgam of
relatively autonomous subpersonalities
each of which had the possibility of
gaining control but that we were also
victim you might say or beneficiary of
impulses that were beyond our conscious
formulation or or or understanding or
capacity to resist so here's this here's
a funny story so I was talking to one of
my patreon people online this week and
he said he was a committed atheist and
that's fine you know lots of atheists
are very honest people and they're
atheists because they don't know how to
reconcile what they know with
traditional claims let's say and they're
not willing to just mangle them together
you know and there might be cynicism all
that associated with it as well but he
said he was he said he was entranced by
these biblical lectures you know which
is pretty weird and he said if someone
would have told him a year ago that he
was going to like be obsessed with the
sequence of biblical lectures he would
have told them that they were mad and so
we had a bit of a discussion about that
and because this is an interesting thing
you know and he mentioned this he said
it was something like you don't choose
your interests they choose you and
that's really worth thinking about to
man because you know it's really hard to
get interested in something you're not
interested in even if you know there's a
good reason for it you know you're
studying for an exam you find the
material boring you know anything will
be more interesting than than the
studying even though you know that
that's what you need to do you can't
voluntarily grab yourself by the scruff
of the neck let's say and shake yourself
and say sit down and concentrate your
mind will just go everywhere but then if
you're interested in something and even
if it's something you shouldn't be
interested in because that happens all
the time
then it's like you're a laser focus man
you can pay attention forever you can
work until you're exhausted you won't
even notice it then you remember
everything it's like okay if you can't
control your interest
what does and man I tell you you can
think about that for a very long time so
Jung talked about the spirit mercurius
you know Mercury's the winged messenger
of the gods and and here's how he
conceptualized it psychologically he
thought
is what the ancient people who thought
about mercury has the winged messenger
of the gods were trying to state
psychologically you know your your
interest Flitz around it's like there's
something that captures it and that
moves your interest from place to place
you know like if you walk into a
bookstore you'll get interested in a
particular book it's as if the book
grips you is you don't know why you're
interested in that you might but often
you don't know why you're interested in
that book and you know your interest is
flitting around and so that's mercury
the thing that makes your interests like
flicker around is mercury the winged
messenger of the gods and mercury is the
messenger of the gods because it's the
things behind the scenes psychologically
that are manipulating your attention and
for Jung those were equivalent in some
sense to the lost gods and so for Jung
your your interest was being manipulated
behind the scenes by unseen forces that
were associated with your character
illogical development across time that
was the manifestation of the self so the
self is this the the potential you let's
say and the way it operates in the
present is by gripping your interest in
directing it somewhere and that's part
of the instinct of self-realization
it's a mind-boggling idea man really
it's I think it's correct I can't see
how it can't be correct it doesn't mean
I understand it completely but it
certainly seems phenomenologically
correct and I mean the potential that
you are has to manifest itself somehow
in in the here and now it has to and
what better way than by directing your
attention you know it's like it seems
like this might be useful for you or
maybe you get attracted to this person
or maybe you admire this person that
happens with kids a lot they'll admire
someone and then copy them and you can
see that that's obviously part of their
developmental progression right it's a
form of hero worship but kids are very
imitative and they hero worship at the
drop of a hat and so they're they're
entranced by the the next stage of
development and if they see someone who
embodies that especially if it's in the
zone of proximal development it's it's
um it's something they could achieve
stretching a bit they find someone who
embodies that next stage of development
and then they start to imitate them and
act like them
well we're adults are no different we're
no different we're just we do it at a
perhaps more abstract and sophisticated
level so okay
so Jacob and Esau are hostile brothers
there they're like Cain and Abel except
the mixture of Cain and Abel and they're
very different Esau was red and covered
with hair he was a hunter and a man of
the field so he's like your basic jock
right he's extroverted he's outgoing
he's really tough he's like
extraordinarily masculine he hunts and
he's a real favorite of his father and
so and and Jacob isn't he's a dweller in
tents and yeah right exactly exactly
exactly right and it says Isaac loved
Esau but Rebekah loved Jacob now that's
a problem right that that's a big
problem and that there's a Freudian
element to this it's like this family is
now divided because one child is the
favorite of the mother and that's Jacob
and one child is the favorite of the
father and so Jacob is kind of a
mother's boy I guess to use an rather
archaic phrase and certainly not as
admirable from his father's perspective
as Esau who's a tough guy who goes out
with a bow and arrow and like you know
wanders around in the plains and brings
animals home and and he's tough he's a
tough guy so and but but there's this
discord in the family because one parent
prefers one child and the other parent
prefers the other and it's obvious from
the story that the parents do not
communicate about this because they
really take sides and so there's a split
in the family and that's I think very
realistic because one of the things that
you do learn if you have a family and of
course most of you do but if you also
think about families is that there's
there's deep divisions within families
very very frequently that no one will
ever talk about and or even think about
often because it's too painful to think
about you know and Freud himself said
Freud was clearly his mother's favorite
and the family sacrificed a lot
including some of the potential
ambitions of the other children in order
to kind of put Sigmund Freud up on a
pedestal and and advance his education
and it worked I mean you know he turned
into a great man but there was a cost to
his siblings and Freud himself said that
there was something about being the
favorite of the mother that gave a
person additional confidence throughout
their life and you know there's there's
something to be said about that even
someone like Eric Erickson you know he
noted that very interested in child
development that that first bonding with
the mother was the it was the place
where trust was established maybe trust
even in the goodness of existence was
established and so anyways Jacob is
Rachel's favorite and he saw his Isaac's
favorite now he saw being extroverted
let's say is also a bit impulsive and
maybe he's not he's a man of action he's
not a forward thinker and but he's also
doing hard work and so you know he goes
out and he's hunting and he's worn out
and he comes home and he's faint with
hunger and Jacob is at home cooking
he's boiling up lentils red lentils and
you know Esau comes in from the hunt and
he's like half starved to death and he's
sitting there in the aroma of these red
lentils reaches them and he's exhausted
and and and he tells Jacob that he wants
some of this stew and Jacob who's being
a pain in the neck fundamentally they
basically says no there's a there's a
teasing thing going on here and and we
won't give him any and and and there's
you have to imagine this because it's
not laid out explicitly in the story but
there's some dispute about whether Esau
gets to have lunch and Jacob finally
says well I'll give you some but you
have to you have to give me your
birthright
and he saw you think he must say
something like you know well to hell
with it take it you know you son of a
take it just give me some damn
stew it's something like that so that's
what happens but you know with these
archaic people once he made a statement
like that that was you were done that
was it and so Esau sells his birthright
and this turns out to be incredibly
significant Manson who wrote biblical
commentary said oh there's a bit of a
twist to it so Esau eats the the red
lentils and then from then on his name
is red and you've got to use your
imagine
in a bit I mean people are making fun of
him right that's why they're calling him
red I mean he's already red because we
established that but no one was calling
him red before this and so for the rest
of his life you know every time he goes
out amongst his friends and family they
call him red and sort of snicker because
he's the you know half famished idiot
who sold his birthright for a bowl of
lentils and so it's it's not it's not
that funny actually
and so Esau is not happy about this and
and it actually turns out that this so
what does it mean it means don't sell
the future for the desires of the
present and don't be casual about what
you have and then there's an archetypal
element to this too and Benson says
various have been the opinions what this
birthright was which Esau sold but the
most probable is that together with the
right of sacrificing so determining what
should be sacrificed and when and being
the priest of the family it included the
peculiar blessing promised to the seed
of Abraham that of being the progenitor
of the Messiah and the error of the
special promises of God respecting
Christ's Kingdom it was at least typical
of spiritual privileges those of the
firstborn that are written in heaven
well that's a lot harsher than meets the
eye to begin with and so there's a very
interesting deep moral story there which
is it's sort of Esau does the opposite
of a sacrifice it's the reverse right he
sacrifices the future for the present
and so the story basically says the way
it's laid out across stories is that if
you're the sort of person that
sacrifices the future to the present
then that eradicate the possibility that
you will bring the the most noble being
into existence that's what it means and
you can again this is the psychological
significance of the biblical story so
that's a bad thing to do if you want to
realize your potential let's say you
don't do reverse sacrifices that's a
very bad idea
and so Esau really did himself in by
being too attached to the present
without a vision of the future so he's -
in the moment you know
and and he pays a heavy price for it I
mean he's the first of all he loses his
birthright and and his double
inheritance so there's a practical
consequence and then there's a spiritual
consequence and then he's well he's been
made a fool of by his brother Jacob
means supplanter by the way that's what
the name means and Jacob is always
trying to usurp Esau as we see and so
Jacob gets one over on him and you know
that's not doesn't make an older brother
happy when a younger brother gets
something over on him that's for sure
and then he loses the opportunity to be
the progenitor of the Messiah which is
like people already didn't realize that
precisely but it seems to be you know
it's kind of rough that so and then
there's there's a statement in Matthew
16:26 for what is a man profited if he
shall gain the whole world and lose his
own soul or what shall a man give in
exchange for a saw it's an echo of the
same idea you know when you think well
what is this idea of soul mean and it's
not intellect it said it's something
like it's something like consciousness
allied with character I think and I
think the reason that it's valued so
much is that because you got to ask
yourself well what do you really have
when it comes down to it so life is
suffering let's say and you know you can
you can pile up worldly goods and the
God in the Old Testament doesn't seem to
have anything against that really right
the people who he favors seem to prosper
quite nicely in the world but they also
have to make a choice between whether
they're going to fundamentally sustain
their character or whether they're going
to prosper in the world when push comes
to shove and the idea constantly is that
really what you have in the world that
allows you the best possible defense
against the suffering that's intrinsic
to being is your character that's what
you have period and I don't think there
is anything that's more psychologically
true than that you know because
everything else well first of all your
relationships with others depend on your
character and certainly this is part of
the story of Noah's Ark you know because
his generations were perfect so he had a
very tight familial arrangement everyone
trusted each other that's a big deal if
you hit a rocky patch in your life right
and it's character that it's character
that determines that you know if you're
generous and honor
and all of those things and people know
they can rely on you assuming they're
not resentful that's a whole different
story then they're gonna come to your
aid when when it's necessary they're
gonna pull together with you and you
know when people are really after you
for one reason or another and they're
accusing you of all sorts of things and
you're guilty because you you have a
past it's laden with characterological
errors then it's very easy for people to
take you down because they'll poke until
they hit a place where you're guilty and
then you're done because you'll do
yourself in with your own judgment and
so well so ESO makes a very big mistake
and there's a sacrificial idea here too
which is you know now and then you're
going to be faced with a situation where
it's something you really want or your
character maybe you'll have to lie about
something you know and you'll think what
difference does it make you know a lie
about it Jacob does this but the problem
there's a bunch of problems with that
one is that well now you know that
you're the sort of person that will in
fact deceive yourself about the nature
of reality if something shiny is dangled
in front of you and that's not good
because it undermines your faith in
yourself and when you're really in
trouble they call that the dark night of
the soul when you're really in trouble
that's what you've got you've got
whether or not you can trust yourself
and that's it you know when things are
really harsh and so if you've betrayed
yourself in that manner then you weaken
yourself under the worst possible
circumstances and that's just that's
really not a good thing
so this is very practical advice it's
not casual moralizing there's very
little casual moralizing in these
stories in the next part of this story
there's some parallels with Abraham and
that's built into the narrative I think
because Isaac is Abraham's descendants
and so we have to keep the narrative
echoing forward otherwise it loses its
its continuity and there's a famine in
the land that Isaac sin and God tells
him to stay the course
anyways repeating the promise he he gave
to Abraham
although Isaac goes to AB Emelec also
telling the King and people that Rebecca
was his sister
exactly what Abraham did when he went to
Egypt and so there's another echo there
of the same the same it's as if the
story is being told for a second time
essentially and that's supposed to
remind you of the of the previous story
but they're careless the King sees that
Rebekah and Isaac are intimate together
and luckily he doesn't have them put to
death he just tells everybody in the
kingdom that they're to be left the hell
alone
and then Isaac prospers in that land
just like Abraham did in Egypt until the
Philistines asked him to leave he's just
getting too rich and powerful things are
going too well for him so he's asked to
he's asked to leave now in the meantime
Esau gets married Hannah this is a funny
little story he says he marries two
women who give grief to Isaac and
Rebekah so they who every so marries
they're not popular with his with their
in-laws not in the least that actually
becomes relevant a little later because
they drive Rebekah quite mad so I get a
kick out of that because that's very
common you know it's not easy to
integrate new people into your family
and and hope that that will go smoothly
it's actually one of the real
catastrophes in life right you have a
kid maybe you get along with them and
maybe you don't but let's assume you do
but then they marry someone that you
just don't like and or maybe you think
is wrong for them I mean that's really
rough that's what are you gonna do about
that you know because you're you're
basically screwed both ways if you have
the person you love around then you have
to put up with this Prentis creature
that they allied themselves with and if
you if you get rid of them completely
well then you know you don't have your
child anymore so it's a very very
difficult position and so that's another
example of the realism I think of the
stories now Isaac who's hypothetically
on his deathbed asks Esau to hunt for
venison because he likes venison and
he's happy that his son is a hunter and
Rebekah over here is this
and so she conspires with Jacob to to
slaughter two small goats and make his
father some stew because he wants Esau
to make him stew out of venison but
Rebecca who's being I would say let's
say slightly deceitful or
probably lying that would be more
accurate she conspires with Jacob so
Jacob kills two little goats kids and
boils up a stew and then he puts on some
goat skins because Esau is a hairy
character and and Rebecca dresses Isaac
in Esau is clothing because Isaac can't
see very well at this point and so then
Jacob goes into his father with the stew
and he's trying to disguise his voice
but it doesn't work very well and so
Isaac asks him to come close and Jacob
puts out his arm with the goat skin on
it and and Isaac smells him too and he
smells like he's oh and which maybe
wasn't the best thing but and feels like
him and and so because Isaac thinks he's
on his deathbed he decides to deliver a
blessing - hypothetically - Esau and so
but it's Jacob and so that's a big deal
- because the blessing is actually as I
said before with these ancient people it
appeared as though once you said
something you didn't get to take it back
you couldn't say well look you've you
deceived me so it doesn't count
it was like they weren't maybe as as
what week might be one way of thinking
about it but another way is they weren't
quite as attentive to context you know
because if I make you a deal and then it
turns out that you've betrayed me I may
feel that the deal is no longer valid
because the assumption was you were
being honest to be giveth in that you
know violates the whole spirit but that
isn't how these people thought they said
once he promised man you promised and
that was that so Isaac blessed Jacob he
says that God give you the dew of heaven
and the fatness of the earth and plenty
of corn and wine let let people serve
you and nations bow down to you be lord
over thy brethren that's gonna be rough
on e so let thy mother's sons bow down
to the cursed be everyone that curseth
thee and blessed be he the blesseth thee
and so there's a quite a remarkable
painting of that so there's Rebekah
she's looking pretty old and Isaac's
looking pretty blind and Jacobs taking
directions from his mother and we might
say he's perhaps a little old to be
taking
moral lessons from his mother especially
given how she's acting and so it's a
pretty ugly scene altogether especially
that we also know that Jacob already
tricked Esau out of his birthright and
so now he's like taking the birthright
and he's taken the blessing and so as I
said that Jacob he turns out to be the
father of Israel it's like he's a
reprehensible character these are
major-league betrayals that he's
engaging and it's not trivial he really
really pulls the rug out from under his
brother and you know you could say well
Esau is not as awake as he might be you
know he's kind of a wild man and fair
enough but it certainly seems to me that
the the predominant moral error falls on
Jacobs shoulders it's very treacherous
behavior what he's doing so then he saw
shows up and he's got a nice stag for
his dad and it's like little late for
that and he states that his brother was
rightly named Jacob which means
supplanter because he's been deceived
twice and Isaac says Isaac answered he's
asking funny I was asking fundamentally
if there's anything at all left over for
him and Isaac can't give him the same
blessing because that's already been
given so he has to think of something
else and Isaac says behold I've made him
thy Lord and all his brothers I've given
to him for servants which includes you
and with corn and wine have I sustained
him and what shall I now do unto thee my
son and Esau said unto his father have
you even one blessing for me my father
and blessed me also and an e so lifted
up his voice and wept and you know we
already know that Esau is a pretty tough
guy by all appearances and you know he's
out there hunting on his own and camping
and it's like he's no pushover and the
fact that this reduces him to tears is
an indication of the magnitude of the
betrayal and Isaac says behold thy
dwelling shall be the fatness of the
earth and of the dew of heaven from
above and by thy sword thou shalt live
and thou shalt serve your brother and it
shall come to pass when you will have
the Dominion and you'll break the yoke
his yoke off from thy neck and Esau
hated Jacob because of the blessing
wherewith his father blessed him and
Esau said in his heart the days of
mourning for my father are at hand then
I will slay my
Jakub so fundamentally you know if Isaac
dies or when he dies then we'll mourn
for him and then Jacob better look the
hell out because it's like it's it's
serious death coming his way and you
know he's got a he's got a point he's in
in Dante's Inferno I think I mentioned
this at one point so Dante's Inferno
it's a very interesting story it's a
descent into hell
and it's it's actually one of the places
that we sort of derive the popular
conception of Hell was partly based on
Dante's on Dante's imagination on his
work and what Dante was trying to do was
to discover the hierarchical structure
of evil and you know you might think
there's a hierarchical structure of good
some things are better than other things
but there's also a hierarchical
structure of evil some evils are greater
than other evils and he put betrayal in
the in the in the lowest part of health
right so if you were betraying people
you were right besides Satan himself and
so and I think that's good that's very
smart well Dante was a genius after all
and I think the reason for that is that
you see if someone trusts you they're
laying their vulnerability open to you
now they might just be naive let's say
and that's we won't think about that
because you're just a child if you're
naive you can still be betrayed but if
you're an adult and you trust it's often
because you if you're an actual adult
its you willingly open yourself up
knowing that you could be hurt right
because you're not naive anymore so you
decide to trust and you see all open
myself up and I know that I'm laying
myself open to you if you choose to use
that power and then that's a good thing
to know you know if you've been hurt as
a child or hurt as a naive person you
might say well why should I ever trust
again which is a really good question
and the answer is the reason you trust
again once you're an adult is because
you're courageous you're courageous
it's an act of courage to trust and the
reason it's useful is because if you
trust someone you open the door to
reciprocity and negotiation and
cooperation and you entice the best part
of the person forward and so it's a it's
a courageous act but then if you betray
someone then what you've done is you've
taken the best part
them which is the part that will
courageously trust you know with open
eyes right and you've stuck a dagger in
that and so you've purposefully damaged
the best part of them and so that's why
it's such a egregious fault and and it's
often people don't recover from that
sort of playing at you if you betray
someone badly enough you can you can
damage them like you can give them
post-traumatic stress disorder if you
really if you really put your mind to it
and you know that's not just a
psychological disorder if you have
post-traumatic stress disorder it
produces permanent neurological
alterations that make you more neurotic
more sensitive to negative emotion
really for the rest of your life like
you can you can recover from it to some
degree but stress will tend to reinstate
the PTSD so you you hurt someone and
it's not merely cycled not not that
psychological is merely but it's not
merely psychological right it's it's
fundamental physiological damage
so anyways Jacobs smart enough to get
out of there and which is also not
really a testament to his integrity
right I mean he's done these terrible
things at the behest of his mother
because he wants power and and he wants
to get it without deserving it and then
you know he finally goes too far and he
hightailed it out of there to his to
another family member to his mother's
brother and so it's not exactly the
world's most heroic story that's for
sure and so now there's an interlude
here and this is a really interesting
interlude it's the story of Jacob's
Ladder so he's off to visit Lebon or lab
and who's his his mother's brother and
on the way he he has asleep and he
lighted upon a certain place and tarried
there all night because the Sun was set
and he took of the stones of that place
and put them for his pillows which seems
to indicate very bad planning on on his
part and and lay down in that place to
sleep and he dreamed and beheld a ladder
set up on the earth and the top of it
reached to heaven and beheld the angels
of God ascending and descending on it
and behold the Lord stood above it and
said I am the Lord God of Abraham thy
far
and the guard of Isaac the land were on
thou liest to thee I will give it and to
thy seed and so this story of Jacob's
Ladder has really possessed the
imagination of the West and there's a
reason for that it's because it's an
archetypal story because the idea of a
ladder that reaches to heaven is one of
the oldest ideas of mankind so you find
it widely distributed among the shamanic
cultures for example and it's a hallmark
of psychedelic experience that's another
way of thinking about it which is a very
peculiar thing so there's one
representation of of the ladder you see
god up at the top there peeking out from
the clouds now you know that's sort of
where we get the idea that God is in in
heaven and then heavens up in the sky
and and that's an easy story to make fun
of because you know we've gone up to the
moon and there's no God there and and
but but this this is not a reasonable
way of conceptualizing what these
experiences are about these experiences
what this is the opening up there that's
more like an opening into an alternate
dimension that's a better way of
thinking about it's beyond like from
from the judeo-christian perspective one
of the things you have to understand is
that God is beyond space and time he's
not in the universe he's outside the
universe in some manner and so the idea
that that you have an experience of God
and it's up isn't the OP is the best
that the human imagination can do with
what's essentially a form of extra
dimensional experience or that's the
best way to conceptualize it and these
experiences aren't rare you know they
they make the they make up the core of
of the shamanic tradition and so there's
an intrusion of the ancient shamanic
tradition which is tens of thousands of
years old
into the biblical stories at this point
now why Jacob had a essentially shamanic
experience is very difficult to tell
because we don't know what these old
people were up to right and we don't
know how much of the archaic tradition
archaic religious tradition was still
extant about at that point in time but
we certainly do know that our ancient
forebears were using psychedelic
substances constantly like Amanita
muscaria mushrooms for example which
were
widely used in India before they became
extinct that's the theory anyways that
seemed to be the basis of the chemical
soma which much has been written about
and so we here ever this as a dream that
were as a vision and perhaps that's what
it was but perhaps that wasn't what it
was either and perhaps it was an
experience that was induced by or by the
same processes that shamanic people have
always induced these experiences and so
we're gonna go through this a little bit
so anyways there's a there's a
connection between heaven and earth that
opens up that's that's that's the that's
the vision and there's messengers moving
up and down now one way you can
conceptualize that is psychologically as
we already discussed that you know there
there are forces within you that are
active and alive and you can think of
them in some sense as messengers of the
higher self and so you could think about
this as an image of a psychological
reality but and so we can stick with
that but but here's some of the
representations that have been made I
really like the one on the right that's
William Blake I like the helix idea and
I don't think that that's that's fluke
there are helixes and double helixes and
all sorts of imaging imagery very
ancient and very modern that are
associated with both healing and with
this kind of vision so and you see it in
the Blake representation God is
associated with well really with the Sun
and with light and and you see that on
the left as well that wherever God is is
where light is and so that's a very
interesting idea as far as I'm concerned
as well there's some other
representations one by Chanel
so now there's this idea that there's a
there's the possibility of opening up a
line of communication between the human
psyche and the transcendent divine and
there's a there's a great image of
Christ as Pam - they're so creator of
the world that is one of the first
mosaics if I remember correctly and I
wish I knew remember where it was but I
don't but it's a very interesting image
I'm having a carving of it made at the
moment by a friend of mine but you see
Christ's face portrayed in a medieval
manner and he's holding a book so it
symbolizes the importance of the book
you know as a means of transmitting
wisdom and his face is very asymmetrical
and that the eyes are different one side
and the other and one half of the face
represents the human part and the other
side of the face represents the divine
part and you know I also think about
that psychologically because I do think
that that's the right way to
conceptualize human beings is that
there's an aspect of us that's mortal
and human and limited but there's an
aspect of us that's transcendent and
divine as well and it's latent in some
sense but there are times when it
manifests itself and this is not
speculation right this is like the
oldest experience of human beings now
it's not necessarily an easy experience
to have but it's reported everywhere and
it can be reliably induced as we've
discussed before by chemical means which
and I don't know what that means exactly
we've talked a little bit about
psilocybin mushrooms for example and you
could say that the mystical experiences
that have been invoked in the newest
experiments down it Johns Hopkins are
arrangements or forms of psychosis you
know because they have some similarity
to psycho psychotic experiences although
psychotic people were given LSD in the
60s and they always said that that was
something different than what they were
having and if you give psychotic people
amphetamines you could make them worse
so their bio chemically separate and we
know that and but also the thing that's
so interesting about the psilocybin
experience is is that they reliably
produce mystical experiences that the
people rate as among the most important
experiences of their life and among
those who have
the psychedelic experience positive
things happen to them and so that kind
of messes with the whole psychosis
theory right because what are you gonna
do you got a claim that you give someone
a pill and they have a psychotic break
and then they're healthier it's like no
that isn't how psychotic breaks work
you're not healthy or after having one
you're like you're a broken egg and it's
not easy to put you back together so and
we know that people all over the world
have discovered every manner of
psychedelic substance that you could
possibly while you imagine there's lots
of hungry people wandering the earth for
a long time and they eat every damn
thing they could get their hands on and
now and then something very peculiar
happened as a consequence so so I'm
gonna tell you a little bit about the
shamanic tradition because it's
associated with Jacob's Ladder so
according to le a de murcia le odd it
was a great historian of religion a
comparative Jung's and and and they
influenced each other quite
substantially le otta believed that
shamanism that used psychedelics was a
degeneration from the original more pure
shamanism but I think later scholarship
has demonstrated that that's incorrect
that that the shamanic ritual per se was
a direct consequence of the use
discovery of an and ritualistic use of
psychedelic substances but anyways
Eliana identified three pathways to
shamanism and the shaman in it in a
tribe was more educated than the typical
person with a larger vocabulary and was
the repository of the oral tradition and
so learned all the stories that had been
passed down word to mouth and people by
the way are very very can very very
accurately tell the same story across
generations that's been quite well
documented so and and people who can't
read really can remember because what
else are they going to do their memories
are far greater than modern people's
memories because we can forget
everything because we can just look it
up but they remembered things because
they had no choice my father knew
someone who was illiterate and and and
and couldn't use numbers either when he
grew up in Saskatchewan
you know sixty years ago and he was a he
had a sheep if I remember correctly and
although he couldn't count he knew if
one of his sheep was missing because he
knew all the sheep and so he could tell
just by looking if one of the sheep was
missing but he couldn't count and so
well so people who don't have our
particular set of skills first of all
they're not stupid and second they have
other skills that we don't understand to
fill in the gaps so le ah de identified
spontaneous vocation so you were just
you have this spirit of a shaman let's
say so you're probably extremely high in
openness let's say from a modern
perspective hereditary transmission so
you know your father was a shaman and
your grandfather was a shaman and so
forth and you got initiated into that
process or a personal quest in Siberia
this is from Ileana in Siberia the youth
who is called to be a shaman attracts
attention by his strange behavior for
example he seeks solitude becomes
absent-minded loves to roam in the woods
or unfrequented places has visions and
sings in his sleep you know if you put
someone in a place that's deprived
that's where you're you're deprived from
a sensory perspective it normal people
will hallucinate quite quickly so it
seems what happens is that if you dampen
down the sensory input then you start to
become aware of the background processes
of your mind it's something like that
it's like the signal-to-noise ratio I
got to get this right as the noise
decreases some of the noise becomes
signal the background noise become
signal and you start to become aware of
your own internal psychological process
is it something like that he has visions
and sings in his sleep in some instances
this period of incubation is marked by
quite serious symptoms among the accout
young man sometimes has fits of fury and
easily loses consciousness hides in the
forest feeds on the bark of trees throws
himself into water and fire and cuts
themselves with knives we went to a part
lash in northern northern Vancouver
Island about a year ago and they had
this one dance
it was the croc Wakulla natives and they
had this interesting dance that was the
dance of the wild man and so the person
who invited us was the wild man and he
was dressed up and in tree branches and
so forth and so he was the person who'd
been in
Bush too long and he came in as a
cannibal and there there was genuine
cannibalistic rights among these people
not so long ago he came in as a cannibal
and everybody had to wear this like
cedar headdress because if you had a
cedar headdress on then the cannibal
wouldn't take a bite out of you and they
actually took this rather seriously so
you should have your cedar headdress on
and so he's looking around the crowd and
there's like 400 people in this place
and he could really act - so he's doing
this wild man dance and then all the
women stood up and started to kind of
dance in place and sing and they were
taming him so that was really cool you
know it was really interesting to see
that because those people are about
they've had an unbroken culture for
about 13,000 years say that's how long
they've been out there and it was very
interesting to see that dramatization of
the domestication of of man by women
laid out in that dance in that way but
it was also interesting in relationship
to the shamanic tradition because he
came in as a wild man right and he had
to be re civilized in some sense and
brought back down to earth so but by
whatever method he may have been
designated as shaman is recognized as
such only after having received two
methods of instruction the first is
ecstatic dreams trances visions the
other thing that this guy told me and I
have no reason to doubt him he's also
not a literate person and so has a great
memory he does carving traditional
carving and he's very good at it he
carved a 53-foot totem pole that's now
in front of the Museum of Art in
downtown Montreal so if you ever go
there you can go see it I won't be there
forever but it's there right now and he
was taught to carve by his grandparents
and he said that he dreamed in you know
you know what the Haida images look like
so the Crocker walks are kind of like
the high that same sort of imagery he
told me that he dreamed in those images
so when he dreams that's the form that
the things he dreams about takes and he
also said that he would talk to his
grandparents in his dream so if he was
working on a piece of wood and trying to
figure out how to carve it and he ran
into a particularly difficult problem
he'd dream and his great he'd have a
conversation with his grandparents and
they'd help him figure
to solve the problem and then he wake up
and he could go Karva and the thing is
he told me these things sort of
matter-of-factly
right like you don't you know what I
mean it wasn't like he was telling me
these weird things that happened to him
although he was doing that to some
degree he I asked him a lot of questions
about what he carved and what it all
meant and you know that was just part of
his explanation of how he did it and he
he carved me a couple of doors that I
have in my house and one of them is
quite interesting well the to make a
panel and they're an underwater scene
and under the water there's a bunch of
you know mythical monsters some of them
are killer whales and I think there's an
octopus down there and carved in this
particular style and he said that the
other thing that happens to him when he
dreams is he goes down to the bottom of
the water where these mythical creatures
are and he gets inspiration from them
and so I thought that was extremely
interesting too
you know we we don't know what a mind
that isn't hyper civilized let's say
hyper literate like like our minds are
cuz we're so bombarded by external
stimuli we have no idea what the natural
mind is like really and so it was quite
interesting to to to listen to that and
also to see the consequences cuz he's
quite a great he's quite a great carver
so the first is ecstatic dreams trances
visions the second is traditional
shamanic techniques names and functions
of the spirits mythology and genealogy
of the clan a secret language this
twofold teaching imparted by the spirits
and the old master shamans constitutes
initiation well so you know modern
people have a problem with that because
we don't really get initiated but I
would say that you know let's say that
we reach out a quest of some sort you
wouldn't be here I don't think if you
weren't because why else would you be
here and so you're on a quest of some
sort to figure out to struggle with the
meaning of life let's say and you don't
want to do that alone because you only
last like 70 years and good luck
figuring it out on your on your own it's
just not gonna happen it's too
complicated and you'll be too isolated
right if it's just you that's insanity
that's no one can stand that and so you
hope that other people have things to
tell you and that your culture has
something to tell you you know so you're
on a quest maybe not with the same
intensity as a shamanic initiate but you
know let's give you some credit and then
you're also trying to understand the
wisdom of the past and that's the second
part of this it's like okay well you're
a human being and human beings have been
telling stories for a long period of
time trying to figure out what's going
on trying to figure out how to orient
themselves in the world and so you know
partly what you're doing here is exactly
what the shamanic initiatives in the
second part of the process which is to
expose yourself to the degree that you
can - names and functions of the spirits
mythology and genealogy of the clan and
the secret language this twofold
teaching imparted by the spirits and the
old master shamans constitutes
initiation so it's that's the rebirth
right yeah that's that's what a nation
is it's being born again and and that's
a birth of the spirit rather than over
the body it's something like that and so
it's the rebirth of an integrated psyche
that's one way of thinking about it and
a psyche that's that's individual but
also grounded in common humanity and the
wisdom of common humanity and that makes
you strong or at least it makes you
stronger because there's a limit to your
strength but God Only Knows to some
degree what that limit is you know
people can be unbelievably tough
unbelievably tough and I think it's even
the more admirable for human beings to
be tough because we're so conscious of
how we can be hurt and we're so
conscious of what that hurt can lead to
you know you can have your family taken
away from you and you can be destroyed
and the fact that you can be courageous
in the face of that at all is something
that is absolutely unbelievable right
and people deserve a lot more credit I
think then people give themselves
because the fact that we can be
honorable under conditions of life and
death right of suffering that's that's a
testament to the human spirit and
there's a profound anti human ethos I
think that pervades our culture you know
that considers human beings cancers on
the planet something like that you know
and that there should be less of us it's
the same
spirit that motivated the guy who wrote
the book about it better to have never
been it's like I don't see it that way
you know I mean I think people do pretty
well for you know for having their leg
caught in a bear trap and their head
caught in a vise they're actually doing
pretty well because life is really hard
and the fact that we're not absolutely
brutal and murderous all the time is
really something remarkable given what
we actually have to contend with that we
can go out of our way to be honest and
generous and altruistic and to care for
each other under unbelievably dire
circumstances and to act nobly sometimes
under the most trying conditions you
know in Solzhenitsyn's Gulag Archipelago
he tells story after story of people who
acted abysmally but also people who
under the worst threats imaginable never
sacrificed their character you know in
reading about that is really well it
really makes you wonder that's that's
what it does the future shamans among
the Tungus as they approach maturity go
through a hysterical or a history would
crisis but sometimes their vocation
manifests itself at an earlier age the
boy runs away into the mountains and
remains there for a week or more feeding
on animals which he tears to pieces with
his teeth he returns to the village
filthy blood-stained and it's only after
10 or more days that have passed that he
begins to babble incoherent words the
strange behavior of future shamans has
not failed to attract the attention of
scholars and from the middle of the past
century several attempts have been made
to explain the phenomena as a mental
disorder but the problem was wrongly put
from the one hand it is not true that
shamans always are always have to be
neuropathic in mentally deranged on the
other hand and this is the critical
issue those among them who had been ill
become shamans precisely because they
had succeeded in becoming cured so it
was it's not the descent into this
strange subterranean psychological state
that constitutes the transformation that
makes the shaman but it's the emergence
back out of it and that's a journey to
the underworld in a and a rebirth right
and so and there's this great book this
is a great book by a guy named Henry
Ellen birch a and he was an existential
psychoanalyst and philosopher and he
wrote a book called the Discoverer
of the unconscious which I would highly
recommend it's on my list of recommended
readings it is a great book if you want
to know about the psychoanalytic
tradition it's the best introduction
there is and he discusses Adler and Jung
and Freud and there's a very credible
job of all three but also takes the
history of psychoanalytic thought back
three or four hundred years before Freud
and so it's it's very engaging reading
and and and and very interesting and one
of the things alan burridge a points out
quite clearly is and he associates this
to some degree with this shamanic
tradition that both Freud and Jung Jung
in particular underwent very intense
periods of psychological disturbance
let's say and I would say what was
happening is that because they were
questioning their axioms at the most
fundamental level they were deranging
their cognitive and perceptual
structures right and Jung was also
experimenting with imaginative
techniques with visionary techniques
which he which he did a lot and there is
a period of his life where he was having
constant a constant stream of visions
which he wrote down in a book called the
red book but at the same time he was
still functioning as a psychiatrist and
operating normally in the world and so
you know people have suggested that what
he had was a psychotic break but that's
ridiculous because you don't know that's
not how it works man if you're having a
psychotic break you you know I've been
an effective psychiatrist those things
do not go together especially not for a
long period of time and so there there's
the possibility of extreme experience
without psycho psychopathology and so
and Allen Burgess he says much the same
thing about Freud and about Charles
Darwin as well who underwent a terrible
period of of mental confusion I would
say as a consequence of formulating his
theory of evolution which was really
hard on him because he was a he was a
die-hard Christian and he knew what he
knew what the implications of his theory
word he didn't know what to do about
that you know so it was very very hard
on him so it's quite common for people
of genius to go through an intense
crisis psychological crisis but then
resolve it and the genius is in the
resolution right
the
precondition for the genius is the
dissolution in some sense because you
have to be obsessed with the problem it
has to grip you completely before you're
going to concentrate it on it's so
obsessively that you might come up with
a solution but it's the people who come
up with a solution that are the prophets
in the shaman and so forth and so on and
and and so that's not this isn't
something that only characterizes
archaic cultures we just don't recognize
it in our own culture properly and and
that's a problem well sometimes we do
right you remember that in the Lion King
right that Rafiki shows up he's the
shaman he brings he brings Simba down
that tunnel dark tunnel that's the dark
night of the soul he has him reflect
upon himself in a pool when he reflects
upon himself deeply he sees the
reflection of his father then that
becomes a car thing of cosmic
significance and his father appears in
the sky just like God appears to jacob
and basically tells them that it's time
for him to grow the hell up and to
return to the devastated kingdom and to
set it right you know and so and that's
right that's exactly right I mean we
live in the devastated Kingdom that's an
eternal truth and it's the
responsibility of the individual to grow
the hell up and to set it right because
when it's devastated and when things are
not in place then everyone suffers too
much and that's not good
and there's no excuse for not doing
something about it because you don't
have anything better to do so and even
like children's movies tell you this so
[Music]
this is a fun one this is from the Eid
wine Psalter 9th to 12th century and
that's Adam and Eve but the there is
speculation that the fruit that they're
eating there you see it is psilocybin
mushrooms right because they're the only
kind of mushroom that grow like that so
that's pretty wild
you might say and then this is the I
think it's called Bannister realign if I
remember correctly and it's what
ayahuasca is made out of and it has this
double helix form which is very very
interesting and they the people the
natives nobody could figure out how the
hell they made this ayahuasca we
which transports people spiritually in a
very intense manner and there's a whole
religion based on it like a modern
religion as well as the archaic religion
and to make this stuff they had to take
two plants that don't grow anywhere near
each other and like there's like a
million plants in the Amazon so like how
do you figure that out nobody knows and
then you have to cook them in this very
particular way for a particular amount
of time before you produce this stuff so
one of the plants has DMT in it which is
a very intense psychedelic but it's very
short acting and the other has an MAO
inhibitor so if you take the DMT and you
take the MAO inhibitor then the DMT trip
lasts for much longer and so that's what
these Amazonian natives figured out and
no one has any idea how they managed it
and if you ask them they tell you that
the plants told them how to do it which
isn't much of an explanation as far as
modern people are concerned but then
when modern people take the ayahuasca
and the plant so to speak starts to talk
to them there are a little less leery of
the whole theory that the plants had
something to do with this so you know
and these things that these I'm loathe
to talk about this because I'm not an
advocate for drug use but by the same
token you can't ignore empirical data
it's not reasonable and the empirical
data that psychedelic substances can
produce mystical experiences and that
those often have a transformative effect
I mean one of the latest studies showed
that if you took people who are dying of
cancer and you and you gave them
psilocybin in a sufficient dose to
produce a mystical experience that you
radically it decreased their their fear
of death it's like you go to think about
that man that's that's tough that's a
tough experiment you you just wouldn't
expect that that you think you take
someone you'd arranged them intensely
and then when they come back they're not
even though they're dying they're not
nearly as afraid of dying you know you
got to kind of wake up and smell the
roses when you see something like that
and the people who are doing this
research are very reliable people so
there's the Amanita muscaria you know
there's this old idea it's quite a funny
idea
toadstools so flies like Amanita
muscaria and there's some this is
ridiculous there's some evidence that
they actually like getting stoned
so cuz animals will eat these like
reindeer will eat these things too and
they get pretty tripped out by them and
so I have this book on psychedelic use
among animals which is a small book but
and so so there's there's this idea that
toads used to sit around the they have
any NamUs carry and wait for the stone
flies to like buzz badly around them and
then snap them up so that's pretty funny
I think and so and you know there are
mushrooms in in the u.s. that are the
oldest the oldest organisms on the
planet a there's one mushroom I can't
remember where it is but it covers
something like oh god I don't know like
square hundreds of square miles it's
like this huge thing because it's all
underground right and they have these
very complex networks of my Celia
they're called and they think the thing
is like a hundred and fifty thousand
years old something like that so there's
plenty of things about the world that we
don't know that's for sure there's the
chemical makeup of the classic
psychedelics you see they all have the
same fundamental structure this is
serotonin that's the one of the major
brain neurotransmitters and so what
happens with the psychedelics is that
they they alter the they alter the brain
function by altering the neuro chemical
utilization of serotonin
they changed the manner in which the
serotonergic systems worked and the
serotonin system is very basic system
because when you're an embryo and your
brain is developing it's the serotonin
projections that basically orchestrate
the development of your brain so they're
and they're very archaic circuits very
very archaic circuits so and this is the
paper I think I stole this from
psilocybin Griffiths who's been doing a
lot of this research psilocybin can
occasion mystical type experiences
having substantial and sustained
personal meaning and spiritual
significance
so why that's a good question right like
so so here's a question for you it is
beyond dispute that human beings are
capable of religious experience why why
is that exactly and like you can
associate it with psychosis but that
doesn't work if the theory doesn't hold
theory
hold water it's not the same thing so
why is it there exactly and it's not an
easy thing to figure out like I've been
trying to figure I'm always trying to
figure out a biological explanation for
everything right because if you want to
find something to stand on you want to
make sure that it can resist a challenge
and so if I can find an explanation for
something that's reductionistic and
materialistic and biological then I'm
going for that that's a tough one
consciousness is a tough one the moral
sense is a tough one they're not easy
things to crack the Big Bang is a tough
one so you know I mean a cynic might say
that maybe sometimes when people are
close to suicide they'll have a mystical
experience you know and you maybe you
say well it's a last-ditch attempt of
your brain to delude you into thinking
that your life has some significance you
know and that's a plausible theory but I
don't think it counts for the generality
of the phenomena so so I don't buy it
what happens in the shamanic experience
is that the shaman has the experience of
being reduced to a skeleton first so
death a deaf experience very realistic
death experience and then the next thing
that happens is that he finds himself in
a place where he's communing with his
ancestor or the ancestral spirits and
then after that there's the climbing of
something like the ladder Jacob's Ladder
se and an encounter with God for all
intents and purposes and it's very
widespread phenomena it's the World Tree
and I've thought about this a lot trying
to figure out what this what this
represents according to a yeah coot
informant that's in Siberia the spirits
carry the future shaman to hell and shut
him in a house for three years here he
undergoes his initiation the spirits cut
off his head which they set off to one
side for the novice must watch his own
dismemberment with his own eyes
dissolution to the primary elements in
some
and hack his body to bits which are
later distributed among the spirits of
various sicknesses it's only on this
condition that the future shaman will
obtain the power of healing his bones
are then covered with new flesh and in
some case he is also given new blood so
there's a death and resurrection
experience that's associated with the
shamanic ritual we're here in the
presence of a very ancient religious
idea which belongs to the hunter culture
bone symbolizes the final route of
animal life the mould from which the
flesh continually rises it is from the
bone that men and animals are reborn for
a time they maintain themselves in an
existence of the flesh then they die and
their life is reduced to the essence
concentrated in the skeleton from which
they will be born again that's a good
graphic representation of the experience
that's an old painting by I think it's
her own amis Bosch if I remember
correctly and I really like that because
it's it's reminiscent of the near-death
experiences that you hear people
describe and they're quite common as
well and and I had that very weird
experience once I don't think I've told
you this story
I was I was assessing someone who had
gone through a car windshield and he was
very depressed it had happened a long
time before but he was very depressed
and the insurance company was basically
accusing him of malingering because he'd
been depressed for so long and you know
he'd sort of healed up and everything
but if your left hemisphere is damaged
especially the frontal part of your left
hemisphere then you can be in a chronic
state of depression because the left
hemisphere generally speaking is
responsible for positive emotion and so
if it isn't there then it's like
negative emotion for you and so I
wouldn't assess him and I was giving him
this I think it was called the MMPI the
Minnesota multiphasic personality
inventory which is a kind of a standard
path personality test half
psychopathology test and he was filling
it out he was a very serious guy
middle-aged guy nothing about him was
new agey in the least he was like an
accountant I think I think in fact he
was an accountant if I remember
correctly and there was one question and
it said my spirit has left my
I think that's right it's very close and
he stopped and he asked me well he said
I'm not sure how to answer this and so I
said well why and he said well after I
went through the car windshield I was in
a coma for three weeks something like
that and I died I think he said he died
three times and he said that he could
remember he couldn't remember anything
during that period of time and he
couldn't remember the car accident
that's retrograde amnesia it's quite
corn common with head injuries and he
said that during one of those
experiences and this is all he
remembered from the hospital was that he
came out of his body and went down the
long tunnel of light you've heard these
near-death experiences and then saw his
family members there and saw the
heavenly light and then realized that it
wasn't his time and came back to his
body now what was interesting about this
guy was that well first of all I didn't
ask him about this right he basically
volunteered this story and it was
instigated by this question and and he
didn't know that anybody else at any
ever had an experience like that cuz I
asked him if he'd ever heard anything
about like that he said no so that was
interesting but what really was
interesting is how the hell did he
remember that right because he had
amnesia during that entire period of
time he was in a bloody coma so he
didn't remember anything they remembered
that and so well those experiences are
more common than you think and then
there's a you know there's a painting of
one which is quite interesting and
that's like a tunnel to heaven it's the
same basic idea it's a little bit more
suffering going on in this one I think
but that's pretty much typical of
Hieronymous Bosch I mean I don't know
what was up with that guy but he was he
was one strange character now the
Scandinavians have this idea that the
world is a tree and I've been thinking
about that a lot I think that the tree
idea tree is something that is grounded
in in matter let's say and that reaches
up to heaven in the Scandinavian tree at
the bottom there's quite a cool idea at
the bottom of that see this tree is
constantly being gnawed by snakes you
can sort of see the snakes at the bottom
and at the same time it's being watered
and the water makes the tree grow at the
same rate that the snakes gnaw on its
roots so it's like a yin-yang idea you
know that there's continual chaotic
destruction and replacement at the basis
of whatever this process is but the tree
seems to me to be a representation not
so much of its it's like a different
dimensional space that's that's what's
trying to be represented so imagine that
you know you're structured if you take
powers of ten magnification say human
beings are about in the middle of the
tiniest thing and the largest thing if
you do it by my powers of 10 and so you
know you have a subatomic level in an
atomic level a molecular level and you
know then that may be a level of organs
and then there's you and then there's
your family and so on all the way up the
the tree fundamentally and so I think
that what this tree represents and this
is the things that thing that the shaman
moves up and down I think that's what it
represents it's this it's this different
view of of its dimensionality it's
something like that and I think that
what happens in the psychedelic
experience is that consciousness can
travel up and down that structure it's
something like that and maybe not only
up and down it but maybe right through
it and I know that's a radical claim
it's a really radical claim and it might
be wrong but it's probably wrong even
because most radical claims are wrong
but but but I'm not so sure it's wrong
and here's something cool so that's the
Scandinavian world tree and that was
drawn by an anthropologist who visited
the tribes in the Amazon who use
ayahuasca now you see it's a snake it's
a tree with snakes well you know that's
reminiscent of the story in Adam and Eve
obviously but it's also reminiscent of
our primate dwelling place right because
that was basically our ancestral home a
tree surrounded by snakes and the snakes
like to eat us and this is a long time
ago this is like 50 million years ago
it's really a long time ago and so we
don't know where these images come from
precisely but I do have the suspicion
that we use the circuitry that we
developed to detect snakes to represent
the unknown as such because like a snake
is something that comes out of the
unknown and like we evolved right we all
evolved out of an animal sub structure
and so we had to get our our biological
cognitive structure from somewhere and
we have this capacity of thinking about
the absolute unknown and the terrors
that are involved in that that the
horrors that can emerge from what we
don't understand and it stands perfectly
to reason that we would use circuits
that were already pre developed for that
and that this is a reasonable
representation of the existential
structure of the world so I think I
might have showed you this before but it
never ceases to amaze me this this
picture so my son drew this when he was
nine eight and so on the right you see
mushroom houses and they have the names
of all his friends on them and so that's
order right and then on the left side
you see chaos there and that little
orange thing is a bug and then there's a
river that runs right down the middle
and so that's like the you know the
yin-yang symbol with the divide in the
middle that's quite cool and then
there's there it is there's Jacob's
Ladder
it's like Jack and the Beanstalk which
is by the way another variant of the
same shamanic story
and there are bugs going up and down it
they're taking messages from heaven
and then up there in heaven it's got the
Sun and there's st. Peter and I don't
know where in the world he got this it's
not like he had a lot of religious
education I mean despite me and you know
there's the pearly gates up there and
then that was the world as far as his he
had a very well ordered psyche I would
say and and still does but when he drew
that it just absolutely blew me away and
so I had it laminated and it's in my
office because well I don't know because
like what the hell do you make of that
you know that's that's why so well you
sort of get the picture there you know
the cathedrals the great cathedrals of
Europe are there like the forests in
stone right and they try to represent
the light coming through the leaves and
so it's sort of our ancestral forest
home but it's it's transformed into
these great sculptures of stone and you
know they produce all because of the
combination of light and darkness and
color but also I think for the same
reason that huge trees produce awe and
people you know and we don't want them
cut down they seem sacred in some sense
and perhaps they are but you know it
also seemed to me this is an intuition
that the the architects of these great
cathedrals were trying to get they're
trying to express something that's deep
and structural they're trying time
trying to express the idea that if being
was constituted properly then it would
be organized from the subatomic level
all the way up to the highest cosmic
level perfectly so every layer stacked
on top of each other without any
contradictions now that would be an
ideal mode of being and everything would
come together under those circumstances
and that's what's being expressed in
these cathedrals it's not all that's
being expressed because they're also
shaped like a cross and you know the
idea is that the center of the cross
which is the center of suffering is also
the place of the individual the place
where the transformation takes place
that's all built into the architect
as well and so then there's the tree
like structures that make us up it
stretched down to the tiniest realities
the microcosm and there's this this idea
it's all represented in the same way
again it's this idea especially the
Mandela up in the top-right it's the
idea of is perfection of crystalline
structure and that's what the Yogi's are
trying to attain when they organize
their bodies they're trying to get every
single layer of their being aligned
properly and it's something like and you
can kind of see an echo of that in the I
think that's a Tibetan sand painting if
I remember correctly left the idea is
that if you get yourself a line properly
then information can flow along that
tree that that's you without without
impediment something like that and that
would be like a state of optimal health
and that both physical and spiritual
exercises can put you in that state and
that's well those are all clouds of
ideas that surround this idea of a
ladder to heaven so Jacob is talking to
God and God says behold I am with thee
and I will keep thee in all places where
you go and bring you again into this
land for I won't leave you until I have
done that which I have spoken to you of
and Jacob awakened out of his sleep and
he said surely the Lord is in this place
and I knew it not and he was afraid and
said how dreadful is this place this is
none other but the house of God and this
is the gate of heaven when Jacob rose up
early in the morning and took the stone
that he had put for his pillows and set
it up for a pillar and poured oil on top
of it that's a sacrifice and he called
the name of that place Bethel but the
name of the city was called l-'izzat the
first and Jacob vowed a vow saying if
God will be with me and will keep me in
this way that I go and will give me
bread to eat and raiment to put on so
that I come again to my father's house
in peace then shall the Lord be my god
and this stone which I have set for a
pillar shall be God's house and of all
of that that is given to me I will
surely give the tenth unto thee and
that's a pretty good place to stop so
now I'll just conclude so you have this
very morally ambivalent character right
who's so far pretty much everything he's
done that we're familiar with is not
good so he's he's betrayed his brother
horribly twice badly enough so that he
his brother wants to kill him and
everyone can kind of sympathize with his
brother so and then he runs away
essentially because his mother tells him
to which is not exactly a testament to
his character and despite that strangely
enough he has this experience you know
and that's heartening I guess and that's
the point is that people are predisposed
to terrible error there's no doubt about
that and yet when I was writing my
latest book I had a friend of mine
Norman Doidge wrote the foreword and
Norma's written a couple of great books
and he's Jewish and he read some of what
I'd written and he took me to task for
making the god of the Old Testament you
know from a Christian perspective too
harsh and unforgiving and I rewrote a
fair bit of it because of his criticism
and because of what I've learned doing
these lectures it's like it's not
exactly right you know I mean what
happens in the Old Testament is if you
screw up especially if you know you do
and you decide that you're not going to
do anything about it so it's conscious
and deliberate then like look the hell
out you are in serious trouble and I
actually think that's also
psychologically accurate one of the
things young pointed out and this always
struck me was that if you don't know
what you're doing this is actually in
the Gospel of Thomas as well
interestingly enough as one of the
caustic Gospels Christ tells his
followers something like if you make a
mistake and you don't know what you're
doing then you'll be forgiven for it but
if you make a mistake knowing what
you're doing and you do it anyways then
like good luck to you
and and and I think that's I think
that's that's psychologically accurate I
mean one of the things that's very
interesting about the judgmental God in
the Old Testament however is that he can
be bargained with and even if you make
mistakes especially if you're
unconscious of them if you haven't
learned yet let's say then you always
have the opportunity to return to the
proper path and that's people get
cynical about that because there's no
this mostly Christian idea that you
could live a terribly sinful life but if
you repented on your deathbed it's like
heaven for you and it's like oh that's
that sounds like a great deal right it's
like you can do whatever the hell you
want until just before you die of course
you might not know when that is so
that's a problem you then you can just
say well I'm sorry and you know
everything's forgiven but the problem
with being cynical about that sort of
thing is that it's no trivial matter to
repent you know because to repent means
a figure out what you actually did and
the worst things that you did the more
horrible it is to figure it out it's no
joke right and there's no genuine
repentance without understanding of the
depth of your depravity and so if you
lived a particularly reprehensible life
and you come to understand it I think
that in and of itself could kill you you
know it's a terrible thing to wake up
and see what you've done if what you've
done is truly terrible so there's no
easy out it's not an easy out it's it's
just pure cynicism to associate that
idea with with an easy oh it's not but
there is that positive idea that it's
continually represented is that the
individual is the source of moral choice
and the individual is prone to genuine
error and temptation in a believable and
realistic way but that that doesn't
sever the relationship between the
individual and the divine and the
possibility of further growth and then I
would say well thank God for that
because without that like who would have
a chance right who would have a chance
and so the idea that
the daddy has presented the infinite
let's say as presented in the Old
Testament is merely judgmental is
definitely wrong and and is in fact
something that you can contend with and
Argan with oh I'll close with one thing
one of the things that I learned that
while I was going through this was the
meaning of the name Israel because Jacob
eventually gets named Israel and and I'm
jumping ahead a little bit to the next
lecture but Israel and so he's also the
father of Israel and the father of the
twelve sons who make up the twelve
tribes of Israel
but what Israel means is he who
struggles with God and that's such an
interesting idea because it's again a
psychological idea and that's why I said
earlier that it isn't obvious in the Old
Testament what it means to believe in
God because what Jacob does is struggle
with God and I think that that's a
really good characterization of an
ethical life because if you're trying to
lead an ethical life that's what you're
doing is you're struggling like blind
belief isn't helpful because you don't
know what you're believing in like it's
just not that helpful but if you're
possessed by by the desire to orient
yourself properly but also confused by
the by the existential structure of the
world which we all are then then what
you're doing when you're trying to
orient yourself properly in life is
struggling ethically and Jacob actually
gets quite hurt he wrestles with God
literally and God dislocates his his his
thigh and so you know the idea there is
watch the hell out right the thing that
you're contending with is powerful
although you can contend with it that's
the thing that's so interesting but you
know you do it at some genuine peril
which i think is exactly right but the
idea that Israel so there's Israel the
state let's say it Israel the promised
land and all of that but there's this
more important idea which is again a
psychological idea which is the State of
Israel which is the promised land is the
state that everyone who wrestles with
God exists in and that's not happy naive
belief in you know an eternally blessed
afterlife it's not that it's not a wish
fulfillment it's it's it's to be
actively engaged in life in the
difficulties of life
right and trying to find the path
because that's what wrestling with God
is is trying to find the path and that
seems to me what belief means
fundamentally in the Old Testament
perhaps in the New Testament as well is
that belief is expressed in trying to
find the path and that's an ethical
struggle and it's a real struggle it's
the struggle of life so as long as
you're willing to engage in that
struggle then hypothetically you have
the divine behind you and so I believe
that I think that's true because the
other thing I see is that the people who
set things right
so that yeah the the horrible forces of
cosmic destruction don't do us in the
people who are trying to set things
right are the ones that are struggling
ethically and so and that there is a
redemptive element to that and I don't
think there's any way of being cynical
about that so well so thank you will
[Applause]
so remember to speak right into the mic
because there are all these other people
watching that will hear it will hear us
so okay
hi dr. Peterson so with the story of
Jacob today there was a theme of
betrayal and you can see that from the
beginning because he was very angry and
jealous at his brother
I was thinking are there new stories or
we can say about betrayal that does come
from a loved one right where it's not
from a place of so black and white of
anger resentment and bitter and how do
the parties kind of recover from that or
is there any way to redeem that or is it
as black and white as if you betray
someone then there it's like Jacob where
hatred no and in fact in this story it's
not black and white because we know
we're only halfway through it and one of
the things I've noticed as a clinician
let's say is that and as an observer of
people in general is that I've never
ever seen anyone get away with anything
and Jacob doesn't get away with any of
this and so you know he's humbled by his
eventual experiences and he learns that
he did it wrong and there's
reconciliation that happens throughout
the story of Jacob so and there's minor
betrayals and major betrayals you know
that some of them have tremendously
serious consequences and some of them
have lesser consequences but there is an
underlying idea that things can still be
set right even though it's well I think
it takes Jacob some 20 years something
like that
to set things right and even then it's
like touch and go so if I answer your
question okay yeah hey you speak
frequently in your lectures about I
guess the war between good and evil or
the struggle of life really is a
struggle between good and evil being at
the core of a conscious lived existence
and I guess on that note if you were
100% certain that there was no afterlife
would you still
be able to preach that there's a
positive meaning in life if you were a
hundred percent certain some atheists
seem to be 100 percent certain and yet
they still preach that there's some
positive meaning to life would you be
one of those or would you turn into Cain
you know so cynical I think that well as
far as I'm concerned one of the things I
learned from studying 20th century
history is that like even if the idea
that even if you take the most cynical
of ideas let's say that life is
irredeemable suffering and and perhaps
isn't even justified because of that it
still seems to me that you have an
ethical duty let's say to live in a
manner that reduces that to the degree
part that that's possible and so and I
think that that can be experienced as
meaningful in some sense independently
of the transcendent context now I don't
exactly know how to strip off the
transcendent context because one of the
things I would say that's happened to me
is because I've spent so much time
looking at the horrible things that
people have done is that it's like Jung
said that he when this is one of his
famous quotes he said no tree can reach
up to heaven unless its roots reach down
to hell and so as I've dug deeper into
the depravity of human beings my sense
of the possibility of human beings has
also grown what would you say in
proportion and until I've become
convinced actually that good is a more
powerful force than evil even though
evil is an unbelievably powerful force
and so I can't really strip the
transcendent away now whether what
bearing that has on eternity say on an
afterlife i mean i i i I can't say
anything about that the only thing I
guess I can say is that there are many
things about being that we don't
understand in the least and we don't
understand the nature of consciousness
or the nature of time so I I'm not I
wouldn't despair about that but yes I
think that life can still be meaningful
without without there being a necessity
of an afterlife
no no no no hi dr. Pederson
so since studying your work one of the
things that I found most fascinating is
your analysis of the story of Cain and
Abel and my question is if if Cain got
to the point that he did right before
killing his brother murdering his ideal
and decided that that was something he
didn't want to do what advice or
guidance would you would you give a
person that got to that point
well there's a story I read called the
cocktail party I've mentioned this
before by TS Eliot and in the cocktail
party there's a scene it's a play where
this woman approaches a psychiatrist and
and starts talking to him about her
problems and she says something that
surprises him she says I hope that I'm
the problem he says well why would you
hope that and she says well I thought
about it a lot and if the world is the
problem then I'm done because I can't
change the world but if I'm the problem
then maybe there's something about
myself I can change and I can undo this
terrible situation that I'm in and so I
would say that's repentance
fundamentally it's like there if and I
say this carefully because I understand
that people are susceptible to bad
fortune sin and ignorance can make that
worse but independently of that like
good people suffer make no mistake about
it
but if things aren't right for you if
you're resentful about being because
that's the right way of because that's
the deepest way of thinking about if you
read the writings of the people who do
the mass killings for example that's
what you see over and over it's cain
it's like they're angry beyond
comprehension at the in tolerability of
being and they're angry at God
even if they don't say it exactly like
that they come so close to saying it
like that that it's there's no
difference you know what God says to
Cain is look to yourself first before
you criticize being and that strikes me
as right it's because to not do that is
arrogant beyond belief that's satanic
arrogance literally if something like
that can be literal it's like don't make
yourself the judge of being before you
clean up your your room let's say and
because the other thing to it this is
something I learned in some part from
Solzhenitsyn when he was in the prison
camps and trying to understand how these
heroic people he saw could possibly
manage it one of the exercises he
undertook and he really viewed this
within a Christian Orthodox context of
repentance and redemption is he said he
went over his life with a fine-tooth
comb and tried to imagine all of the
ethical mistakes he made in his entire
life that he knew were mistakes it was
it was this was the soul searched not he
wasn't relying on external standards of
morality except insofar as we're
inevitably influenced by those and then
his idea was is there something I could
do right now to put that right and
that's the right question like if things
aren't going your way and I think that
means that you're resentful and arrogant
and deceitful those are the three things
that clump together I think that
constitute the core of evil it's
something like that and so if you're
possessed by that which is a hell then
its repentance that's the right answer
and what that means is you have to
figure out what you did wrong and you
have to pay for it and then at least you
could think well look I can try that
with all of my soul let's say and see
what happens right it can at least be an
experiment and then I would also say
that that's an act of faith it's an act
of faith to conduct that experiment
because you put yourself on the line
right and that's what an active faith is
you don't know the outcome but you don't
know the outcome of your life so live in
some sense is an act of faith you're
putting faith in something that that's
why you're moving forward you couldn't
move forward without an act of faith you
know and people say well I own
move forward on the basis of the facts
it's like yeah but you select the facts
and there's an infinity of facts and
they don't just tell you what to do so
it's not a credible answer so if you're
in that situation it's like look to
yourself you know and one of the things
about Solzhenitsyn that's so bloody
amazing is that's what he did and then
he wrote the Gulag Archipelago and you
know he took an axe to the intellectual
and moral substructure of of the
totalitarian communist states so while
he was redeeming himself let's say he
was simultaneously redeeming the world
and you know you see something like that
like you you gotta wake up man that's
that was really something so yeah dr.
Peterson I have a lot of questions that
arise from your comments at the Bell for
one hundred event your m103 video your
recent discussion with ayaan Hirsi Ali
and your comments on Islam in the West
in general and in your comments there's
this common theme that one of these
things is not like the other you put the
judeo-christian tradition on the one
side and Islam on the other specifically
the quote complex problem of Islam in
the quote as a quote totalizing system
and before I go further let me state
that if hypothetically a final analysis
of Islam resulted in as total of
denunciation as your analysis of
post-modernism or near Marxism I
wouldn't be personally offended at all
this isn't a a personal question in your
recent interview with ayaan Hirsi Ali
she said Western values are superior to
Islamic law and Islamic values I agree
with that
basically certainly in the context of
let's say current global affairs I'll
skip the quotes from a recent magazine
interview but you should read them
because hers is a worldview which is
very much the West versus Islam not
radical Islam but Islam including
necessarily the military option so my
question is at the level of
psychological significance of these
stories at the level of mythology and
archetype how is Islam so different from
the Jo Christian tradition you know
because Adam Adam Eve of Shaitaan
Shaitaan so on and so forth everything
from the fault of the flood a lot of
what you've discussed in this lecture
series is necessarily part of Islam as
well and in fact I think one of the
strongest criticism of Islam
that it's perhaps pretty unoriginal you
know tonight you said that the moral
presuppositions of a culture are
instantiated in its stories I see a lot
of the same stories so current global
affairs aside I'm asking at the deepest
levels how different are these stories
in the morals presuppositions ok well
that's that's a killer question well ok
so the first thing I would say is
fundamentally I don't know and so part
of the reason that I'm one of the things
I'm planning to do is to have a series
of discussions and plenty of people have
contacted me about discussing with ayaan
Hirsi Ali as you know she has powerful
and serious folks and they're not happy
with her black and white distinction and
so now I read infidel and I really liked
that book like I my sense was that she
she was a heroine now what that means in
relationship to Islam that's a different
story because she came out of a like a
totalitarian let's say family structure
in a relatively totalitarian society and
you could make the case that there's a
correspondence between that and his
lemon you could make the case that there
isn't and and of course that's the
critical issue and so there's a couple
of things that I can't wrap my head
around with we have wrap my head around
easily in relationship to Islam and so
one is what I see as the failure to
separate church from state and that's a
problem now it may not be a problem as
such but it's certainly a problem in
relationship to the relation between
Islam and the West because we separate
church from state
now there's fundamentalists in the
United States Christian fundamentalists
who think that that separation is a
mistake so it's not only it's not only
an idea that's rooted in Islam that
those should be United but it's
definitely a problem with regards to our
coexistence because that's a
fundamentally different presumption okay
so that's problem number one problem
number two
for me and again this may be a
consequence of my ignorance which I'm
trying to rectify Muhammad was a warlord
and I I don't know what to do about that
fact like one thing you can say about
Christ hypothetically let's say I'm not
talking about a historical reality
necessarily although I'm not denying it
either is that of all the things he was
warlord was definitely not one of them
and I don't know what to do about that
and so I don't know how to reconcile
that and I don't know how to reconcile
like not only was Muhammad a warlord
which I don't think is an unreasonable
thing to proclaim the expansion that he
initiated was unbelievably successful I
mean within six hundred years it was the
biggest empire of the world had ever
seen and a demolished Byzantine
Christianity which is something that
Western people don't even know you know
I've read thinkers who said that the
West was so traumatized culturally let's
say by the demolition of Byzantine
Christianity that we can't even study it
now and so I don't know if that's true
but I don't know that it's not true
either
and the Buddhists were wiped out of
Afghanistan and we saw that echoed in
talibans destruction of those great
Buddhist monuments and so so what I'm
hoping is that there's a bridge there
better be a bridge and that's why I want
to have these discussions because I'd
like to understand if there's a bridge
and so lots of people have sent me
people who I should talk to who who they
think represent Islam far better than
ayaan Hirsi Ali and perhaps they're
correct and hopefully I'll get an
opportunity to talk to them because I
would like to know why I would like to
know if what I think is wrong because if
it's wrong it's important that I know
it's wrong but
at the moment I don't a I don't know
it's wrong and B I don't see I'm not
sure what it signifies so and I don't
think anyone is sure right because we
have this entangled entangling of the
civilizations you know when there's
other things too like I'm not very happy
with the Saudi Arabs and the Wahabis I
don't think they're our allies I don't
see how any Western woman can possibly
think that they're our allies and I'm
not happy with the fact that the petrol
dollars that we send them are
transformed in substantial part into the
kind of propaganda that's definitely a
threat to the West and I'm not very
happy with the fact that our politicians
appear stupidly blind to that now that
may again be a consequence of my
ignorance it's certainly possible but
those are the sorts of things that that
I can't reconcile and so you know I've
seen that I've also seen parallels
between the ideas that I'm presenting
here and other religious traditions
Taoism and Buddhism Hinduism it's harder
for me to bridge the gap with Islam and
I'm not sure why that is I think it has
something to do with the things that I
just laid out now what I don't know
about Islam would feel very many volumes
many of which I have sitting on my
shelves at home right now because I want
to do the reading you know as I progress
through this but
good evening dr. Pearson thanks for
continuing this series even as atheists
appreciate the interaction and the the
conversation I wanted to ask you
something that is both emotional and
analytical because oftentimes you're
basically pegged as seeing things very
analytically so you were talking earlier
about you were talking about the the the
juxtaposition between happiness and
honor even though I don't think they're
mutually exclusive personally but if
there's a situation let's say where
someone is truly in love with someone
else and they love them for many years
and decades they have a whole history
together and then someone and then one
of the people in this grouping start
falling in love with someone else so
it's not that there's less love for the
original partner how analytically and
emotionally do you take care of a
situation like that when you feel that
you want to stay honorable and be happy
okay so the first thing I would say is
the devil is always in the details right
so one of the things that I'm not happy
about with much modern moral theorizing
is that it takes a story like that you
know and then tries to extract out a
general moral principle and often that's
impossible because the particulars of
the situation are very important but
having said that all right so let me
think about that for a minute I'm not
sure that it's possible to be honorable
in a situation like that because I think
that you've acted out the violation
already and having acted out the
violation to confess it might be the
right thing to do although perhaps not
you know because if you it isn't obvious
to me that if you betray someone then
you get to have the right to tell them
about it I know I know you're not
yeah yeah I understand I understand my
observation has been that if there's a
tight relationship and if one party is
betrayed by the other in that matter
that it's almost always irreconcilable
it breaks it and you know I've helped
people try to struggle through that but
on both sides of it the person who was
betrayed and the person who did the
betrayal
I've seen people grow up and not do it
again and this was in situations where
their partner didn't know and in a
couple of those situations it seemed to
me that it might have even been a
necessary learning experience for the
person who did it you know it it helped
them develop and that doesn't mean I'm
justifying it but life is complicated
but but I think that society works
better all things considered when you
make a promise and you stick to it and
one of the things I learned from reading
young which which I really liked was you
know he believed that and he had his
affairs too so you might think about it
as somewhat hypocritical but but I think
that people can make mistakes without
having what they think necessarily be
wrong you know he said that there are
things in a marriage that you can't have
unless you're all-in and I believe that
I believe that and so if there's a back
door open or though like to begin with
or a back door opens then I think that
there's something about the relationship
that is lacking at least and I think you
pay a big price for that so I mean it
depends on whether you regard a marriage
as a practical arrangement or a
spiritual arrangement now really it's
both you know and both are important but
if it's a spiritual arrangement or a
psychological arrangement above all then
I do think that you don't get the
transformation without being all-in and
if you violate it then even if you can
work it out with your partner there's
something that you will never get as a
consequence
so
[Applause]
last question okay I hope I'll make this
good thanks also for a continuing the
lecture series I haven't listened to all
of the lectures but it seems like you
focus very much on the appeal of the
bible-- of stories to the individual
psychology you have any thoughts on the
relative importance of crowd psychology
to the appeal and staying power of the
bible and also the the reason why the
Bible or the biblical stories took
precedence over other ideologies which
could have taken its place okay well
let's go to the second one first I think
it's the same thing that happens when
someone both creates and edits a great
movie it's no one knows like imagine how
many choices are there in a great movie
let's say it's an animated movie because
absolutely everything in an animated
movie is constructed everything there's
God only knows how many choices like
maybe there's millions of choices you
know and each choice is guided by some
intuition of narrative suitability or
beauty or there's some higher ideal
motivating it right the desire to
produce a masterpiece maybe that's it
that was certainly the case with the
Disney movies for example and so that
that aspiration then then makes the
decisions and so I would say well
something like that guided the writing
and the selection of the stories in in
the biblical canon now could have there
been other stories included well the
Catholics and the Protestants don't have
the same biblical tradition and neither
do the Jews and the Christians and so it
isn't exactly clear what to make of that
you know I mean that's akin in some
sense to the discussion we just had
about Islam and Christianity in some
sense I've left that aside that specific
question except insofar as I've just
answered because I'm trying to take what
we have which I know is that their route
of our culture and to figure out what it
is that we have
why it is that we have it well I've made
some attempt to explain that in the
manner that I just described but I don't
have a final answer I could it have been
different it could have been different
at some levels but the same at others
you know I mean one of the things it's
the scholars of comparative religion who
haven't been infected fatally with
post-modernism have definitely realized
so young for example in Le ah de people
who are interested in grand narratives
one of the things they pointed out quite
clearly is that there's there's there's
a set of common mythological themes
across many cultures and I tried to
outline that in maps of meaning and that
worked out quite nicely for me at least
as far as I was concerned because once I
had the basic archetypal structure
mapped out it opened up all sorts of
stories to me from all sorts of
different cultures and that's been
unbelievably useful like the
Mesopotamian story of it the Anu mulisch
when I figured out what that meant as
far as I was concerned like I've never
forgotten that it just seared itself
into my memory and the same with the
Egyptian stories and you know some
Buddhist writings that I've read in some
the daodejing is also very powerful so I
think that things can be different on
one level and the same at another but
that humanity kind of coalesce is on
what's the same over a reasonable period
of time because there isn't that many
ways that human beings can live properly
as individuals and as groups together
and so there's this constant force that
makes our ethical presuppositions
converge and then that's automatically
expressed in the stories it's something
like that now it's an imperfect process
and it's full of error so
so just one announcement well two
announcements the next lecture I believe
is November 14th so I'll hopefully
finish off the story of Jacob looks like
it and then I'm also appearing on a
panel with God's odd and or an Amity on
November 11th and there's still quite a
few tickets available for that so if
you're interested you could go to my
website and pick up those tickets huh it
should be well hopefully it'll be
interesting I think it will be and might
be too interesting that's one
possibility so we'll see but I'm gonna
do two more of these this year and I
hope I get through the story of Joseph
and then I can start in the New Year
with it with Exodus and that's a story
that I know quite well and that the
Exodus and Leviticus and what's the one
after that yes thank you so I'm very
much looking forward to that because
that is one killer story that so and
I've got some surprises for that as well
so anyways thank you very much for
coming and hopefully we'll see you
November 14th