[Music]
so I've been thinking this week about
doing this once a once a month on a
continuing basis
so so I I think if I do that I think
it'll be here although it's harder to
rent this theater during the academic
year but if it isn't here it'll be
somewhere else and because I'd like to
continue doing this I'm learning an
awful lot from doing it and and uh once
a month would really be good because
then I could really do the background
work and and uh and I could probably do
that for a couple of years because
obviously this isn't going very quickly
but that's okay you know I mean it
shouldn't go any faster than it can go
and that's how it that's how it seems to
me anyways
so uh
this has been this has
been a a very steep learning curve for
me with regards to these stories because
I didn't understand them very well and
I've I've got better at using the
resources online to help me do my
background investigation I have a lot of
books and some of you may have noticed
that um online I posted a conversation I
had with Jonathan pasio and his and his
brother Matthew um I hope it's Matthew I
named escaped me so badly but I believe
that's right he just finished a book on
the on the Bible and so I've been doing
a lot of thinking and talking about
these stories trying to understand what
they're about and and then there's all
these commentaries there's a a great
site I think it's called Bible Hub that
has every single verse of the Bible is
listed there and
then with each verse there are like
they've aggregated 10 commentaries from
about 10 commentaries from over the last
400 years and so there's like a dense
page on every line and that's one of the
things that's really interesting about
this book too is that it's it's
aggregated so much commentary that it's
that it's it's much bigger than it looks
the book is much bigger than it looks
and so it's been very interesting to
become familiar with those too and the
fact that this site is set up with all
the commentaries split up by verses
means you can rapidly compare the
commentaries and get a sense of you know
how people have interpreted this over
well at least several hundred years but
of course much longer than that because
the people who wrote the commentaries
were of course reading things that were
older than that so that's been very very
interesting
um so last week we talked about a couple
of things we talked about how you might
understand the idea of a Divine
encounter and then we also paralleled
that with the idea that God disappears
in the Old Testament he he bows out as
the stories progress and that seems to
be a an emergent property of the
sequencing of the the stories right
because all the books were written by
independent people different people and
then they were aggregated by other
people and so the narrative continuity
is some kind of emergent property that's
that's a consequence of this interaction
between people readers and and writers
over centuries and it's it's strange
that given that there are also multiple
coherent narratives that unite it you
know it's really it's really not that
easy to understand that but it does at
least seem to be the case and so and the
third thing we talked about was that as
God bows out so to speak the the the the
individual personality seems of the of
the characters that are involved the
human characters that are involved seems
to become more and more developed and it
isn't exactly clear what that I mean
what it means is that God steps away and
man steps forward that's what it means
but why it's arranged like that or the
or the say ultimate significance of that
is by no means clear and so so Abraham
who we're going to concentrate on today
is quite a well-developed character um
and I would say there are two there are
multiple endings and Beginnings in the
biblical Stories the most important
ending I suppose is the ending of the of
the garden of paradise and and the the
disenchantment of the world and the and
the sending forth of Adam and Eve into
history right into the future into into
a motive being that has a future as part
of it and that has history as part of it
and that has
the necessity of sacrifice and toil as
part of it that's obviously crucial and
then that's that is replayed with the
story of Noah because everything is
destroyed and then the world is created
a new and then sacrifices have to be
made in order for the world to begin and
then you see the same thing happen again
after the Noah story in the Tower of
Babel because history as we really
understand history seems to start with
Abraham because the stories of Abraham
sound like historical stories and you
know Scholars debate about the
historical accuracy of the Bible and I
suppose there's there's no way of ever
determining once and for all the degree
to which you might regard the the
accounts as equivalent to Modern
empirical history but this is a
psychological interpretation of the
biblical story is not a historical
interpretation and it certainly does
seem to be the case that from a
psychological perspective we enter
something like the domain of the modern
conceptualization relatively modern
conceptualization of history with
Abraham beyond the of divine commands
that Abraham carries out this is from
fredman the man I mentioned in the last
lecture who wrote The Disappearance of
God and a variety of other books um that
are well worth reading the narrative
also includes a variety of stories in
which Abraham acts on his own initiative
he divides land with his nephew lot he
battles Kings he takes concubines he
argues with his wife Sarah on two
occasion he tells kings that Sarah is
his sister out of fear that they will
kill him to get his wife he arranges his
son's marriage in the place of the
single story of Noah drunkenness there
are in the case of Abraham the stories
of a man's life and one of the things I
was really struck by reading this in
depth and reading the commentary is how
much like a story about a person it is
you know Abraham isn't a Divine figure
in in any in in any archetypal sense
precisely I mean he has archetypal
elements because he's
also obviously the founder of a Nation
but fundamentally he's a human being and
and he makes he has the adventures and
he makes the mistakes of a human being
and that's it's the mistake part that
really struck me you know
because I was talking with a friend of
mine this week Norman dege uh who's a
very remarkable person in many ways and
he was taking me to task he was reading
my book which I'm going to publish or
which will be out in January and in in
the book I I in one section I contrasted
the god of the Old Testament with the
god of the New Testament and made the
case sort of based on northr Fry's ideas
that the god of the Old Testament was
really harsh and judgmental you know and
that the god of the New Testament was
more merciful and you know at least to
some degree more sweetness and light and
Norman took me to task about that saying
that that was a an overly christianized
interpretation which would make sense
because I derived it in part from northr
fry and I really have come to understand
that more that that he's right because
that he's right about that because the
god in the Old Testament is actually far
more merciful than he's generally made
out to be and you really see see this
with it's good news fundamentally if you
regard the representation of God as
somehow key to the description of being
itself I mean Abraham makes a lot of
mistakes you know serious mistakes and
and yet he has a life and he's and he's
blessed by God despite the fact that
he's pretty deeply flawed and engages in
deceptive practice I mean he's a good
man but he's not a perfect man by any
stretch of the imagination and and
things work out really well for him and
he's the founder of a nation and all of
that and that's good news for everyone
because perfect people are very very
hard to find and if the the the the the
only Pathway to having a rich and
meaningful life was through Perfection
then we would all be in deep trouble and
so that that's very satisfying to read
that and um the the other other thing
that I've been struck by is that you
know Abraham and I think this is
actually absolutely key to the
interpretation of the story Abraham goes
out and does things that's the thing and
so one of the things that I've noticed
in my life is that
nothing I've ever done was wasted and by
done I mean put my heart and soul into
you know like like attempted with with
all of my effort that that always worked
now it didn't always work the way I
expected it to work that's a whole
different issue but the payoff from it
was always positive I always something
always something of value always accured
to me when I made the sacrifice is
necessary to do something worthwhile and
so I think part of the message in in
this in the story of in the abrahamic
stories is go do something and and I've
I've thought about this in a variety of
ways outside of the interpretation of
this story because I have this program
some of you might be familiar with which
is called future authoring program and
it's it's designed to help people make a
plan for 3 to five years into the future
you know and we so what you do is you
you answer some questions it's a writing
program you answer some questions about
how you would like your life to be and
what you would like your character to be
3 to 5 years down the road if you were
taking care of yourself like you were
taking care of someone that you actually
cared about so you kind of have to split
yourself into two people and treat
yourself like you like someone you have
respect for and that you want the best
for that's not easy because people don't
necessarily have respect for themselves
and they don't necessarily want what's
the best for themselves because they
they have a lot of self-contempt and a
lot of self-hatred a lot of guilt and a
lot of existential angst and and a lot
of self-consciousness and all of that
and and so people don't necessarily take
care of themselves very well and and I
think it's I think it's I think you have
an obligation it's one of the highest
moral obligations to treat yourself as
if you're a creature of value and and
that is in some sense it's in some sense
that's independent of your actions and
you might think about that
metaphorically as a recognition of your
Divine worth in the biblical sense
regardless of your of your sin so to
speak and I think that's that's that's
powerful language as far as I'm
concerned once you understand it anyways
with the self-authoring program the
future authoring program you you ask you
answer questions about what what how you
would like your friendships to be
conducted because it's useful to
surround yourself with people who are
trying to move forward and and more
importantly who are happy when you move
forward and not happy when you move back
backwards not when you fall that isn't
what I mean but when you're doing
self-destructive things your friends
shouldn't be there to cheer you on and
because then they're really not acting
like friends obviously you know I know
it's obvious but it still happens all
the time and people allow it to happen
it's not a good idea and you know how
would you like to sort your family out
and I was thinking about this this week
too because I was thinking about Noah's
Arc and there was a phrase in that story
that I didn't understand which was that
Noah was perfect in his Generations I
thought I don't know what that means and
you know when you're when you're going
through a book like the Bible if you
don't understand a phrase that actually
means you've missed something it doesn't
mean that that's just not you know
that's not gerine to the story it means
you're stupid you didn't get it man you
didn't get it you didn't understand it
and
so the idea that Noah was perfect in his
generations and that's why he could
build an ark that would sustain him and
him and and Humanity itself through the
flood it meant that he not only did he
walk with God which was something that
we talked about in in the context of The
Sermon on the Mount but that he
established proper relationships with
his family with his children and so what
that meant was that his Not only was he
well integrated as a person but his
level of integration had reached the
point where it stretched out Beyond him
and encompassed his family and so it was
Noah and the family that was in the ark
and I can tell you and I really
understood this this year because I had
a very tumultuous year you could think
about it from a personal perspective I
could think about it as a year that had
no shortage of floods and my and part of
the reason that I was able to get
through it I also had terrible health
problems and the only one of the reasons
I was able to get through it was because
my family really came together around me
my kids my wife my parents and and and
my friends as well and particularly a
certain group of friends and that's
partly all of that came together in my
mind this week and I thought oh that's
what it means to be perfect in his
Generations meant that he hadn't just
straightened himself out he'd also
straightened out his relationships with
his family and I can tell you that when
crisis strikes you which it will it will
the flood will come right that's why the
apocalypse is always upon us the flood
will definitely come in your life and to
the degree that you've organized
yourself psychologically and also healed
the relationships between you and your
family that could be the critical
element that that determines whether you
live or die when a crisis comes or or
whether someone in your family lives or
dies and so the idea of the the ark
containing the man who's who walks with
God and whose Generations are perfect
and that that's what sustains Humanity
through the crisis it's like you
couldn't be more psychologically
accurate than that you know the other
thing I was thinking about this week I
I was thinking about another line in the
New Testament I think it's from The
Sermon on the Mount but I'm not
absolutely sure Christ
compares the Kingdom of Heaven to a
mustard seed and so I was thinking about
a mustard seed is a very tiny seed and
it grows into quite a spectacular
complex plant and I was thinking about
how you should operate in the world in
order to make it a better place assuming
that that's what you should be doing and
that that is what you should be doing
and there there's lots in the world to
fix everything that bothers you about
the world and about yourself should be
fixed and you can do that and my Dawning
realization I have a friend he lives in
Montreal his name is James Simon he's a
great painter and he's taught me a lot
of things help he's helped me design my
house and beautify it and I bought some
paintings from him a couple of years ago
um and he did this series of paintings
where he went around North America and
and stood in different places and then
he painted the view from here down and
so it's his feet planted in different
places on roads in the desert on the
ocean I have one actually hanging over
my toilet which is him standing at a
urinal um yeah well you know he was
trying to make a point and the point was
that wherever you are it's worth paying
attention and that's because you know so
all these places that he visited he
looked exactly where he was standing by
the side of the road in the desert sort
of mundane in some sense but then maybe
he put 40 hours into that that painting
you know and it's it's very very
realistic painting with really good
light and what he's telling you as a
painter is everything is worth paying
attention to an infinite amount but you
don't have enough time and so the artist
does that for you right the artist looks
and looks and looks and looks and looks
and then gives you that vision and so
then you can look at the painting and it
reminds you that right where you are is
there's every everything that there is
is right where you are and that's a hard
thing to realize but it's actually true
and so I've I've been telling people
online in various ways and in lectures
that they should start fixing up the
World by cleaning up their room and I
wanted to just elaborate on that a
little bit before I get back to the
lecture itself so as it's become this
internet weird internet meme you know uh
and and and and and it's a joke and good
it's a joke I good I'm really happy
about the fact that so much of this has
got like the leave-in of humor and it's
really important because that's what
stops things from degenerating into into
conflict to humor and I was thinking
about this idea of cleaning up your room
in relationship to the Mustard Seed idea
and you see the thing about cleaning up
your room this is also something I
learned from Carl Jung and his studies
on Alchemy because for Yung when The
Alchemist was attempting to make the
philosopher stone he was not only
engaged in the transformation of the
material world but he was engaged in a
process of self- transformation that
occurred at the same time as the as the
chemical trans as the chemical
transformation so it's a psychological
work in some sense let's say you want to
sort out your room and beautify it
because the beauty is also important and
let's say that all you have is just a
little room like you're not rich you're
you're poor and and you don't have any
power that's another thing but you've
got your damn room and you've got this
space right in front of you you know
that that that's a part of the cosmos
that you can come to grips with and you
might think well what's there in front
of you right in front of you and the
answer to that is it depends on how open
your eyes are that's the proper answer
because you could say and William Blake
said this for example and eldis Huxley
made comments that were very similar
that in a Transcendent State you can see
Infinity in the finite and you might say
well you can say in you can see infinity
and what you have within your grasp if
you look and you could say maybe that's
the case with your room and so you want
to clean up your room well okay how do
you do that exactly well a room is a
room is a place to sleep and so if you
set your room up properly then you
figure out how to sleep and when you
should sleep and you should sleep and
then you figure out when you should wake
up and then you figure out well what
clothes you should wear because they
have to be arranged properly in your
dresser and then you have to have some
place to put your clothes if you're
going to have some clothes you have to
figure out what you're going to wear
those clothes to do right and then that
means you have to figure out what you're
going to do and then your room has to
serve that purpose because otherwise it
isn't set up properly and if it doesn't
set up if it doesn't serve your per
purposes you will be unhappy and not
happy in the room because the way that
we perceive the world is as a place to
move from point A to point B in and then
if the place that we're in facilitates
that movement then we're happy to be
there and if the place that we're in
serves as an obstacle to that movement
then we're unhappy to be there and so
what it means to set up your room is
that you have to have somewhere to go
that's worthwhile or you can't set up
your room and then your room has to be
set up to facilitate that and then the
next thing is well maybe you have to
make it beautiful but that's not easy
right that means you have to have some
taste and that doesn't mean you have to
have money it doesn't because you can be
garish with money and you can be
tasteful with nothing all you need is
taste and taste beats money when it
comes to beautifying things you know I
mean not that money is Trivial because
it's not but taste is crucial and people
who are very artistically oriented can
make beautiful things out of virtually
nothing and not only that the literature
suggests that if you're going to make
beautiful things putting real
constraints on on what you allow
yourself to do facilitates creativity
instead of inter interfering with it
because let's say you have to make
something out of nothing right which I
suppose would be a Godly act right you
have to make something out of nothing it
you have to be creative in order to do
that and so then to to beautify your
room means that you also have to develop
Your Capacity to be creative and so then
you can make your
room shine but then what will happen is
that if your family isn't together they
will interfere with that you'll
interfere with that because you won't
have the discipline to do it properly
but then when you start building this
this this little microcosm of perfection
with what you have at hand then it'll
evoke all the pathologies of everyone in
your household they'll wonder what the
hell you're up to in there and they
won't necessarily be happy because if
you're if they're in a lowly Place let's
say and so are you and you're trying to
move out of that then the the higher you
move out of that the more the place
they're in looks bad and you might say
well what they should do is celebrate
your victory over chaos and evil but
that isn't what will happen what will
happen instead is that will attempt to
pull you back down they'll attempt to
and I mean obviously All Families don't
do that but but all families do that to
some degree and some families do almost
nothing but that and so what that means
is that if you're going to organize your
room then you're going to have to
confront the devils in your house and
that's often that's often a terrifying
thing because some of those Devils have
have lineages that go back many many
many generations and God only knows what
you have to struggle with in order to
overcome that and so and then and so to
sort yourself out and to fix up your
room is a non-trivial matter you know
and you you can do that you'll learn by
doing that and then maybe you'll learn
Enough by doing that so that you can fix
up your family a little bit and then
having done that you'll have enough
character so that when you try to
operate in the world at your job or
maybe in the broader social spheres that
you'll be a force for good instead of
harm because you'll have learned some
humility by noting just how difficult it
was to put your damn room together well
and yourself for that matter and so
you'll proceed cautiously with your eyes
open towards the good and so well I
those are some of the things I've been
thinking about this week and they're
germine they're like they're Germain to
what we're going to discuss tonight
because what happens at the beginning of
the abrahamic story is basically God
comes to Abraham and just says
go get going man do something do
something get going and you might think
well where should I go and God God is
somewhat vague about that and where he
sends Abraham it's it's a real fixer
upper man it's like there's starvation
there and and there's tyranny and
there's and there's marital dissolution
and there's deceit like it's it's just
like where you live you know it's
exactly the same thing it's it's it's
tyranny and catastrophe so that's you
know the the great the tyrannical great
father because because Abraham ends up
having to sojourn in Egypt and and
there's a famine and so mother nature is
on the Rampage Abraham lies about his
wife as we'll see and so it's it's the
world it's the world it's tyranny and
and vulnerability and deceit and yet God
says go because if you do go then you'll
become a father of Nations and you think
well again that's pretty good news
although it's strange because you'd
expect that if God chose Abraham then
he'd send him immediately to the land of
Honey land of milk and honey and that
isn't what happens at all it doesn't
happen at all and Abraham never gets
there but his mission is still regarded
as Divine and thank God for that because
that's what your mission will be because
that's what you will encounter in your
life those are the AR archetypal things
everyone encounters the tyranny of the
social structure and the and the
rapaciousness of Nature and the
deceitful the deceitful quality of the
human psyche it's like that's the world
now it's a negative that's a negative
view in some sense but it's positive in
the story because what it basically says
is something that's akin to The Sermon
on the Mount which is that if you're
aligned with God and you pay attention
to the Divine injunction then you can
operate in the midst of chaos and
tyranny and deception and flourish and
you could hardly hope to have a better
piece of news than that given that
that's exactly where you are so and I
didn't see any of that in the abrahamic
stories to begin with so it's been very
interesting to have that sort of reveal
itself the Abraham section thus develops
the personality and character of a man
to a new degree in bibl
narrative while picturing him in a new
degree of responsibility in him a new
degree of responsibility so here's the
other thing that's really struck me and
I think this is of absolutely crucial
importance and I I don't know how much
importance but it's certainly important
to me one of the things that has just
blown me away in the last year because
I've talked to lots of people lots of
people live you know but also lots of
people online but it's more obvious live
and it's obvious in this theater as well
is that I I've i' I've gone around and
spoken and a large proportion of my
audience has been young men y you know
under 30 something like that and I've
spoken to them a lot about
responsibility and what's so odd about
about this is that of all the things
that I've spoken about because I can see
the audience and I can feel how the
audience is reacting because I'm always
paying attention to all of you in so far
as I can manage that so I I get some
sense of how what I'm saying is
Landing you know which you have to do if
you're going to speak effectively to
people and what what happens is if I
talk about responsibilities everyone be
is silent just like they are now silent
and and not moving right focusing
attentive say pick up your
responsibility pick up the heaviest
thing you can and carry it and the room
goes quiet and everybody's eyes open and
I think that always makes me break
up I was
[Applause]
I don't I don't know why I was speaking
to an English journalist today who's
going to write an article in ins
spectator magazine and I was talking
about this and at the same point in the
discussion the same I had the same
emotional reaction I don't really
understand it it's I think it's
something there's something about it
that's so crucial because you know we've
been fed this unending diet of Rights
and freedoms and there's something about
that especially there's something about
that that's so pathologically wrong and
people are starving for the antidote and
the antidote is truth and responsibility
right and it it isn't it isn't because
that's what you should do in some you
know in
some some I know better or someone knows
better for you what you should do sense
it's that it's that it's that it's that
that's the secret to a meaningful life
and without a meaningful life then all
you have is suffering and and nihilism
and despair and all of that and
self-contempt and and that's not good
and so the men it's necessary for men to
stand up and take responsibility and
they all know that and and are starving
for that message and and the message is
more that that's also a good thing to
stand up and take responsibility because
you're cursed so much now from from from
from when you're young with this notion
that your active engagement with the
world is part of what is destroying and
undermining the planet and adding to the
tyranny of the social systems it's like
how about not so much of that hey
because it's it's it's too Soul
deadening it's anti-human right to the
core and my sense instead is that you
know if you if you were able to reveal
the best of yourself to you in the world
that you would be an overwhelming Force
for good and that whatever errors might
be made along the way would wash out in
the works and that's the other thing
that you see in the abrahamic stories
because Abraham is not a perfect person
by any stretch of the imagination he's a
real person and he makes mistakes but it
doesn't matter the overarching narrative
is you know maintain your Covenant with
God and despite your inadequacies then
not only will you Prevail but your
descendants will prevail it's like great
that's really good news you know so it's
been really something to see that in the
in the stories it's not that so that's
responsibility it's not just that
Abraham is Kinder gentler more intrepid
ethical or a better debater than his
ancestor Noah rather both the Noah and
Abraham stories are pieces of a
development of an increasingly stronger
stance of humans relative to the deity
before the story is over humans will
become a good deal stronger and Bolder
than Abraham well that's really
something to say because Abraham is
pretty bold so we'll let's read the
stories the first one is about Abraham
Sarah and lot now these are the
generations of Tara Tara begat Abraham
so his name is Abraham to begin with and
that actually turns out to be important
it's not Abraham nahor and Heron and
Heron begat lot so Heron is Abram's
brother and Heron died before his father
Tara in the land of his Nativity in ER
of the chelis and Abram and nahor took
them wives the name of Abram's wife was
Sarai and the name of nahor's wife milka
the daughter of Heron the father of
milka and the father of isca but Sarai
was Barren she had no child and Tara
took Abram his son and lot the son of
Heron his son's son and Sarai his
daughter-in-law his son Abram's wife and
they went forth with them from the ER of
chelis from ER of the chelis to go into
the land of Canaan that's Exile and they
came unto Heron and dwelt there and the
days of Tera were 205 years and terara
died in Heron and there's a reason that
Sarah is is introduced as Barren and and
it's it's to set the stage I think it
was Anton COV who when he was talking
about this the stage setting for a play
that if there was a rifle hanging on the
wall then it had better been used before
I believe the second act or it shouldn't
be hanging there at all right and so
this is stage setting and I part of the
reason that the biblical writers are
pointing out that Abram's wife is Barren
is because it's a real catastrophy for
Abraham and for Sarah as well that she's
Barren and so it's it's showing the
trouble that Abraham's in at the
beginning of the story and it's also
it's
also see what happens as the story
progresses is that Abraham Abraham and
Sarah are eventually granted a son but
it's way late in the story and they're
very very old by the time it happens and
of course you're not going to be a
father of Nations without having a child
and so the the writers are attempting to
to make the case that if you
forthrightly pursue that which God
directs you to pursue let's say that all
things are possible that's that's the
idea in the narrative and you know you
you might say that's naive and you know
it it's not it you think it when you're
naive right and then you dispense with
that idea and then when you stop being
the sort of person who dispenses with
ideas then you come to another place and
that's the place where you
think you have no idea what might be
possible for you if you if you got
things together and pursued what you
should pursue you don't know how much
what's impossible to you right now would
become possible under those conditions
it's an unknown phenomena and like I've
watched people who put themselves
together across time you know
incrementally and continually and they
become capable of things that are jaw
not only jaw-droppingly amazingly but
also sometimes metaphysically impossible
to understand and so we don't know the
limits of human endeavor we truly don't
and it it's it's premature to put a cap
on what it is that we are what that what
it is that we're capable of and so you
you know you're already something and
maybe you're not so bad in your current
configuration but you might wonder if
you did nothing for the next 30 Years
except put yourself together just
exactly what would you be able to do and
you might think well that's worth
finding out but of course that's that's
the adoption of responsibility and one
thing I've also learned over the years
because I've been curious about this
battle between meaning and nihilism you
know and I mean I mean I could see for a
long while the rationale in nihilism and
and the power of the nihilistic argument
but it it it occurred to me across
across time that despite that the power
of the nihilistic argument is more
powerful than naive optimism but it's
not more powerful than the optimism that
is not naive because the optimism that
is not naive says it's self-evident that
the world is a place of suffering and
that there are things to be done about
that and it's self-evident that people
are flawed and that there's things to be
done about that and then The non-naive
Optimist says the suffering could be
reduced and the insufficiency could be
overcome if people oriented themselves
properly and did what they were capable
of doing and I do not believe that
that's deniable I I do I do I think that
human potential is virtually Limitless
and that there's nothing perhaps that's
beyond our grasp if we're careful as
individuals and as a society and so I
think that there's no reason for
nihilism and there's no reason for
hopelessness and and there's no reason
to bow down before evil because we're
capable of so much more and I think that
you can easily you know that first
because you're not happy with who you
are and you're ashamed and embarrassed
about it as you should be and you know
it because if you look out there you see
people who are capable of doing great
things and you know that we're not
giving at our all and still we're not
doing so badly you know and so you you
might wonder if if if we devoted 90% of
our effort to putting things right
instead of 55% of our effort or maybe
even less than that you might wonder
just how well could things be put
together and I think that you can figure
that out by starting with your room by
the
way and the Lord said unto Abram and
this is this is the this is the opening
of the story get thee out of thy country
and from thy Kindred and from thy
Father's House unto a land that I will
show thee and this is one of those
phrases where every Clause is
significant go somewhere you don't
understand that's the first thing get
thee out of thy country you know back in
the 1920s there was a whole slew of
American Writers who ended up as exp
Patriots in Paris Hemingway among them
and and who wrote The Great
Gatsby Fitzgerald yes and then a variety
of others it was very inexpensive in
Paris at the time and part of their
transformation into great literary
figures was the fact that they were out
of their country and now they could see
what their country was because you can't
see what your country is until you leave
it so you have to go into the unknown
and that's that's God's First Command go
into the unknown because you already
know what you know and so and that's not
enough unless you think you're enough
and if you're not enough and you don't
think you're enough then you have to go
where you haven't been and so that's the
first commandment to Abraham it's like
okay that that's a good one that makes
perfect sense go to where you don't know
yes and from th Kindred well that what
does that mean it means grow up right
that's what it means it means get away
from your family enough so that you can
establish your Independence and that
isn't because there's something wrong
with your family although perhaps there
is you know as there is perhaps wrong
with you but it means get away you know
I talk to people very frequently whose
families have provided them with too
much protection and they know it
themselves and that means they're
deprived of necessity you know one of
the things that you see in in in the
United States for example is that um the
children of first generation immigrants
often do better than the CH than the
than their children and the reason for
that is that the children of first
generation IM immigrants have necessity
driving them and you don't know how much
you need necessity to drive you because
maybe you're not very disciplined and if
a catastrophe doesn't immediately befall
you if you don't act forthrightly today
then maybe you never act forthrightly
right because the the the gap between
your foolishness and the punishment is
is lengthened by your unearned wealth
and so you never grow up and learn and
you have to get yourself away from your
dependency in order to allow necessity
to drive you forward and that's to
become independent and to become mature
and I think part of what's happening in
our culture is that the the the force
that's attacking the the forthright
movement forward of young men in
particular is afraid of the power of men
because it's confused about the
distinction between power and authority
and competence
like a man who's who has Authority and
competence has power as a byproduct but
the authority and competence is
everything and and and people who can't
understand
that fail to make the distinction
between power and authority of
competence and they're afraid of power
and so they destroy Authority and
competence and that's a terrible thing
because we need Authority and competence
what else is going to what else is going
to allow us to Prevail in the long run
and so you get away from your country
and you get away from your kin and from
your father's house right and you go out
there and you establish yourself in the
world it's a call to Adventure that's
what this the the first lines in the
abrahamic story is a call to Adventure
so great unto a land that I will show
you well you know what does that
mean you know what one of the things
that I've been struck very hard by a
number of writers Carl Jung obviously
among them I mean he he wrote things
like nature that if you understand them
they just break you into pieces you know
and and one of the things that Yung
understood in the psychoanalysts
understand it's one of the most
terrifying elements of psychoanalytic
thinking it's very tightly allied with
religious thinking which is that you are
not the master of your own house there
are spirits that dwell in you within you
meaning you have a will and you can
exercise a certain amount of conscious
control over your being but there are
all sorts of things that occur within
that seem to be Beyond Your Capacity to
control your dreams for example that's a
really good example or your impulses for
example you you might think of those as
so foreign from you that they're not
even you don't even want them to be part
of you but but more subtly even how
about what you're interested in what
compels you like where does that come
from exactly because you can't you can't
conjure it up of your own accord you
know so if you're a student and you're
taking difficult course you might say to
yourself well I need to sit down and
study for 3 hours but then you sit down
and that isn't what happens your
attention goes everywhere and you might
say well whose attention is it then if
it goes everywhere because you say it's
your attention it's like well if it's
your attention maybe you would be able
to control it but you can't and so then
you might think well J just exactly what
the hell is controlling it and you might
say well it's random it's well it better
not be random I can tell you that that's
that happens to some degree in
schizophrenia there's an element of
Randomness in that it's not random it's
driven by the action of of phenomena
that I think are best considered as
something like subpersonalities although
even that's only a partial
description you can't make yourself
interested in
something interest manifests itself and
grips you that's a whole different
thing and so what is it that's gripping
you and and how do you conceptualize
that is that a divine power well it's
divine as far as you're concerned
because it grips you and you can't do
anything about it and so there's a
calling in you towards what you're
compelled by and what you're interested
in and sometimes that might be very dark
and sometimes not but you're compelled
forward by your interest and
so and so the idea that what moves you
away from your country and your father's
house and the Comforts of your childhood
home is is something that's beyond you
and that you listen to and hearken to
that's exactly right and you can say
well I don't want to call that God it's
like it doesn't matter what you call it
exactly it doesn't matter to what it is
what it's called it's still is and if
you don't listen to it that's the other
thing if you don't listen to it and I've
been a clinician and talked to enough
people now as old as I am to know this
absolutely if you do not listen to that
thing that beckons you forward you will
pay for it like you cannot possibly
imagine you'll have everything that's
terrible about life in your life and
nothing about it that's good and worse
you'll know that it was your fault and
that you squandered what you could have
had
so this is not only a calling forth but
a warning unto a land that I will show
thee and and that's it that I will show
thee that and you don't want to be too
concrete about this you know there's all
sorts of new territories that you can
inhabit if you there's there's abstract
and conceptual territories if you go to
university and you study biology or you
study Physics or or any discipline
you're in territory right you're in the
territory that all the scholars have
established and then as you master the
discipline you move out beyond the
established territory into the unknown
and and that's a new land right maybe
it's even a land of your enemies for
that matter but it's a new land the
frontier is always in front of you and
so you know when the Earth was less
inhabited than it is now the frontier
was the psychological Frontier and the
geographical Frontier was the same thing
and now they've separated to some degree
because there's not so much geographical
Frontier but there's the Frontier is a
place that never disappears and the land
that's beyond the land that you know is
always there and it's always where you
should go and all of that's packed into
these what four phrases
so well so when I've been thinking about
narrative you look at the world through
a story you can't you can't help it and
this the story is what gives value to
the world or or the story is what you
extract from the value of the world you
can look at it either way you're
somewhere and it's not good enough right
that's the Eternal human predicament
wherever you are isn't good enough and
to some degree that's actually a good
thing because if it was good enough well
there's nothing for you to do so it's
actually maybe a good thing that it's
insufficient and that might be why
sometimes having less is is better than
having more and and I don't want to be a
poana about that I mean I know that
there's deprivation that can reach to
the point where it's no where it's
completely counterproductive but it
isn't always the case that starting with
little is
you if you start with little you start
with more possibility it's something
like that so you move from always from
what's unbearable about the present to
some better future right and if you
don't have that then you have no you
have nothing but threat and and negative
emotion you have no positive emotion
because the positive emotion is
generated in the conception of the
better future and then the evidence that
you generate yourself that you're moving
towards it that's where the positive and
fulfilling meaning of life comes so you
want to set up this structure properly
it's very very important and so what it
means is that you want to be going
somewhere that's good enough so that the
going is worth the while and you can ask
yourself that and that's partly what we
tried to build into the future authoring
program which is well we know what's
wrong with life it's rif with suffering
and insufficiency and deception and evil
it's all of that obviously okay what
would make the journey
worthwhile well you can ask yourself
that it's like all right in order to
Bear up under this load what is it that
I would need to be striving to attain
and if you ask yourself that that's to
knock and and the door will open that's
what that means if you ask yourself that
then you will find an answer and you'll
think you'll shrink away from it you'll
think well there's no way I could do
that it's like well you don't know what
you could do you don't know what's
possible and you're not as much as you
could be and so God only knows what you
could what you could do and have and
give if you sacrificed everything to it
it and that's the reason Abraham is
constantly making sacrifices and it's
archaic right he's burning up like baby
lambs but like well they're alive you
know that's something and and they're
valuable and that's something it's you
have to admit even if you think about it
as a modern person that the act of
sacrificing something might have some
dramatic compulsion to it you know to go
out into a flock and to take something
that's newborn and to cut its throat and
to bleed it and to burn it might be a
way of indicating to yourself that
you're actually serious about something
and it isn't so obvious that we have
rituals of seriousness like that now and
so it's not so obvious that we're
actually serious about anything and so
maybe that's not such a good thing and
so maybe we shouldn't be thinking that
these people were so archaic and
primitive and superstitious it's
possible that they knew something that
we don't and certainly in the abrahamic
stories one of the things that maintains
Abraham's Covenant with God is his
continual willingness to sacrifice it's
so that sacrificial issue is so
important because you are not committed
to something unless you're willing to
sacrifice for it commitment and
sacrifice are the same thing and I think
it's it borders on miraculous that those
concepts are embedded into this
narrative at the level of dramatic
action you know instead of abstract
explanation people are acting this out
and then the the fundamental conception
is so profound that it's really quite
it's quite a inspiring it's it's
breathtaking really when you understand
what message is trying to be invade you
have to make sacrifices what do you have
to sacrifice you have to sacrifice that
which is most valuable to you currently
that's stopping you and God only knows
what that is it's certainly the worst of
you it's certainly that and God Only
Knows to what degree you're in love with
the worst of you
so well so you move from the unbearable
present to the ideal future and and you
can't help that you have to live in a
structure like that that's your house
that's another way of thinking about it
then if you want to get your house in
order and if you want it to be a place
that you can live properly then you have
to plan the future that is
perfect and then I think well what does
that mean and it means it's good for you
right and one of the things that I I'm I
do all the time with my clinical and
Consulting clients is try to figure out
what would be good for them but we we do
more than that we try to think okay well
what how can we set this up so it's
really good for you and that all the
side consequences of that are things
that are good for other people and so
because people are often also timid
about trying to get something that's
good for themselves because they feel
that it's selfish or that they don't
deserve it so we set it up so that well
look we're going to set it up so that
it's plainly obvious that this will not
harm the structure of the universe for
you to have what you need and to do it
in a way that's of benefit to other
people there's no downside to that and
and so it's okay it's okay if you reach
out and take that and one of the things
that's interesting about the biblical
Stories the abrahamic stories as well is
that God doesn't really seem to be
opposed to the success of the people
that he's chosen you know what happens
to them is as they progress through
their journey is they they get larger
flocks and they they get more Authority
and they they get they get more they get
life more abundant that's what happens
it's God isn't doesn't seem to be a
miser in the Old Testament it's like if
you put in the and you and you accept
the Covenant and you make the sacrifices
then you get to be successful and maybe
successful beyond your wildest dreams
and that that's actually seems to be
okay with God and that's pretty cool
given that you know that that General
notion of Old Testament God is that all
he's doing is casting out curses and
death you know wherever he happens to
wander and I mean there's certainly no
shortage of that but but again it seems
to me that that's very good news and
that you also don't have to be perfect
in order for have that happen and then
the other thing this is the issue about
going into the unknown it's like well if
you leave your country and your kin and
your father's house and you go out into
a land that your intuition guides you to
you're going to undergo these radical
Transformations this is a sacrificial
transformation too because you're you're
moving forthrightly and voluntarily into
chaos right and that's the same as the
dragon fight that's the hero's story and
what will happen there is that you will
transform yourself and so the call to an
ideal is also the call to a sequence of
deaths and rebirths that move you closer
and closer to the ideal and that's what
that's what God is calling Abraham to
do in the first sentence of this
story you see these things
echoed in the strangest places and so
the SE are Stills that I took from
Pinocchio and this little Cricket so he
the still Small Voice right that's the
thing that calls to you it's your
conscious conscience in part it's your
intuition in part and it's the thing
that opens up the Great Book of the
world the great Sacred Book of the world
and that's what happens here right and
the animators are at pains to show you
that it's a leatherbound book with guilt
lettering it's a valuable book and it's
something that's quiet that's showing it
to you right you have to meditate let's
say you have to be somewhere where the
world is drowning you out in order to
understand how to open this to listen to
that voice that tells you where you
should go what what you should do
next and then what happens is that
something beckons to you in the night
it's a star right it's something that
transcends the Horizon it's it's
Glitters it's it's brilliant it's it's
not day-to-day it's something that's
beyond you it's something that
represents a Transcendent ideal and that
makes it manifest to you if you're quiet
enough to listen and that's what you
wish upon so strangely right and people
do that they wish upon a star they teach
their children that and they don't know
why why what do you mean you wish upon a
star what what in the world does that
mean it means you lift your eyes to the
heavens and make a pact with the
transcendant and then your and then what
your heart's desire will come to you
that's what it means and you think well
that's so that's not naive it's the most
sophisticated thing that you can
know and it's the birth of the hero
right because that's the that's the
Nativity star
obviously and this is where it takes
place it's just anywhere and the person
in it is just a carpenter and a toy
maker but that's pretty good a carpenter
if you're a deceitful Carpenter then
your house falls down and if you're a
toy maker then you love children it's
that's a good start you know so so
jepetto who lives in this little it's
it's it's a it's not a grand house it's
it's it's just everyday house but
everything that's happening in it is
good and so that means it's it's a
palace because everything in it is H
that's happening is good there's a
saying and I I don't remember where it
comes from that it's better to have
bread and water in peace than a feast in
conflict and like that's not a saying
that's just the starkest possible
description of the truth because there's
nothing worse than eating a grand meal
with people you hate and despise that
are at each other's throats it's much
better to have bread and water in peace
it's it's it's it's not it's it's just
clearheaded analysis of the structure of
the world to say things like that and so
the magical transformation can happen in
the most mundane of places because and
the reason for that is that the mundane
nature of places is an illusion because
every place is the potential birthplace
of the kingdom of God that's the
case and so japeto he's a good guy he
has a kitten you know the kitten likes
them he makes puppets and he's humble
person and he knows that compared to the
ideal that he's attempting to subscribe
to that he's he's not a based before it
or anything like that he's not
despicable in relationship to it but the
reason he's on his knees is because the
thing he's pointing at is above him you
know if it wouldn't be the right aim if
it wasn't above him and so the fact that
he's on his knees so to speak is only an
indication that his is proper because
you should be on your knees to something
that you actually admire and if you
don't feel like being on your knees in
front of it then perhaps you don't
actually admire it and then that means
you haven't got the stage set properly
it could be it should be something that
fills you with awe your aim should
should be at something that fills you
with awe because what why why do
something else well perhaps because it's
easy and perhaps because it's malevolent
and all of those things but but those
are no answer to the problems that beset
you they just make things worse and
that's
clear and so then jedo have having made
his pact his Covenant just like Abraham
he falls into a dream right he falls
into a dream and the rest of the movie
actually takes place in a dream and it's
a Dream It's The Dream Within which
transformation takes place and that's
laid out at least in part time stops in
in in the Pinocchio story and everything
happens to Pinocchio in some sense in a
land that's outside of normal time and
that's that's the infinite archetypal
space that's a real place that's a real
place the infinite and the finite
coexist and most of the time we're in
the place of the finite but that doesn't
mean that the place of the infinite
doesn't exist it just means that we
can't get access to it we just get
intimations of it from time to time you
know when things are going perfectly
well for you on those rare occasions
where everything comes together for the
brief moment you inhabit that Divine
place and you have some sense of what
your life could be like if you organized
it from the smallest element to the
largest element and that's a place that
you can inhabit if not forever in a
manner that at least felt like
forever well because of jepetto's
decision the Transcendent manifests
itself it takes the form of the Blue
Fairy here that's the positive element
of nature right so we could say well
nature it's not so clear that she's or
your side right she's the Red Queen in
Ellison Wonderland who runs around
screaming when you go down the rabbit
hole she runs around screaming off with
their heads and who says In My Kingdom
you have to run as fast as you can just
to stay in the same place that's mother
nature but then we might say well how do
we know that Mother Nature's attitude
towards you isn't negative because your
attitude towards things isn't proper and
that's what this film attempts to
indicate the idea is that if you aim
properly then nature aligns itself
behind you now it also arrays itself in
front of you perhaps even as an
antagonist but the power that it it it
provides you with from within might be
sufficient to overcome it from without
and I think that I think that the
clinical evidence is clear about that
because one of the things that we do
know is that if you take people who are
confronting terrible things and
shrinking from them and you teach them
how to structure their behavior so that
they can advance with
courage everything works better for them
their fears decrease and their character
grows and so there might be enough of
nature within us to help us withstand
the nature that's outside of us and it
depends at least to some degree on how
it is that we Orient ourselves in the
world to some in to some unknowable
degree
now jepetto wants an autonomous
individual as a
son and that's also something that makes
him a great person because autonomous
individuals have their own will and if
you're a tyrant it's the last thing that
you're going to want and if you're the
Tyrant who's jealous of his son it's
even more so the last thing you're ever
going to want and so to aim high and to
want the development of the autonomous
individual are the same thing and I
would say that's the core story in some
sense of the of Western culture is that
to aim high and to develop the
autonomous individual are the same thing
and that's what happens in Pinocchio
that's what happens in the story of
Abraham and the transformation takes
place the magical transformation and in
the Pinocchio story one of the things
that's so interesting about it and this
is part of its mythological substructure
from the scientific perspective there's
only two determining forces with regards
to the destiny of the individual there's
nature deterministic and culture
deterministic and then Scholars Wrangle
about which of those is the greater
force but in mythological stories
there's always a third element and that
third element is something like
autonomous Consciousness and there's no
place for autonomous Consciousness in
the deterministic story of Nature and
culture but we all act as if autonomous
Consciousness is the primary reality and
the biblical stories are predicated on
the idea that autonomous Consciousness
is what gives rise to the world and I
don't think that we're in a position to
presume that that is necessarily an
error and so what that means is to aim
high and to develop the autonomous
individual is is simultaneously the
decision to formulate an allegiance with
the the conscious power that brings
being into
existence and that all takes place
inside this little puppet and then he
has his adventures right he's he's he's
still half jackass and half deceptive
but he still despite that and despite
all the errors he has the capacity to
move forward and to transform into
something to transform himself into
something that can be properly
considered described as a true Son of
God and that's the right
aim and it works like this as far as I
can tell you know when I had talked to
people about doing the future authoring
program they often put it off and it's
not surprising because it's hard and and
but it's more than that they think well
I don't know how to write I'm going to
do a bad job I don't really like
assignments I'm going to have to do it
perfectly I need to wait till I have
enough time and like one of those is
enough to stop your cold and all five of
them you're just done and so I tell
people do it halfhazard
a tiny bit at a time and badly
because you can do that I tell my
students when they're doing their thesis
Master's thesis write a really bad first
draft and then we have a little
conversation about that because they
don't think I mean that because it
sounds like a cliche in some sense it's
not a cliche it's not a cliche at all it
means you're a terrible writer but but
if someone put a gun to your head and
said you have to have your 100 page
thesis done by next Monday or I'll shoot
you but I don't care how terrible it is
you would sit down and write it and the
thing is then you have it right then
then you have something and then you can
fix it you can iterate and fix it that
bad first draft that's the most valuable
thing and so that's what you need you
need a bad first draft of
yourself and there's there's an idea
that Jung developed about the trickster
and the jester the comedian right that
the the trickster is the precursor to
the Savior that's one of the things I
learned from Yung that was just it's so
unlikely you never think that it's so
amazing that that might be the case but
the the the the the SAT the satirical
and the ironic and the and the
Troublemaker the the comedian the fool
the fool is the precursor to the Savior
why because you're a fool when you start
something new and so if you're not
willing to be a fool then you'll never
start anything new and if you never
start anything new then you won't
develop and so the willingness to be a
fool is the precursor to transformation
and that's the same as humility and so
if you're going to write your destiny
you can do a bad first job you're going
to get smarter As you move forward
that's the thing is that so something
beckons to you that's what happens here
maybe the star that jepetto wished on
was the wrong damn star but at least it
was a star right at least it was in the
sky at least it moved him forward and so
you say in your life well something
grips you and and and fills you with
interest and you think well should I do
that and the answer is if not that then
something'
what if it's a mistake it's a mistake
rest assured what do you know you're
going to stumble around right and what's
going to happen is this you're going to
move to you're going to not stay in
stasis you're not going to wander around
in circles and I see people like that
they said well I never knew what to do
and now I'm
40 it's like that's not so good that's
not so good and you might say well and
there is a literature too that suggests
that people are a lot more unhappy when
they look back on their lives about the
things they didn't do than they are
about the mistakes they made while they
were doing things and so that's really
worth thinking about too because there's
Redemptive mistakes and a Redemptive
mistake would be a mistake that you make
when you go out and try to do something
you know you actually you think okay I'm
going to try to do this and you're not
good at it you make a bunch of mistakes
it's like what what's the consequence if
you pay attention is you're not quite so
stupid anymore that's the thing is
you've been informed by your by the
results of your errors and so what
happens is
you you you follow the beacon you follow
the light and and you're blind so you
don't know where the light is it's it's
dimly apprehended only and you're afraid
to follow it but you decide to take some
stumbling steps towards it and as you
take stumbling steps towards it you
become illuminated and enlightened and
informed because of the nature of your
experience because you're pushing
yourself Beyond where you are and you're
going into the country that you have not
yet been in and you learn something and
so what happens then is the star moves
you move 10t towards it and you think no
that's not right I didn't get it right
it isn't there it's actually there and
so then you you see it somewhere else
and you shift yourself slightly and you
move forward and that's what happens is
that you continue as you change the
thing that guides you forward moves
right it's like God in the in the in the
desert in Egypt the pillar of light that
you're following it's moving it's not a
permanent thing you move towards it it
moves away it guides you forward and so
you say well is what I'm aiming at
Paradise itself and the answer to that
is no because what do you know you you
couldn't see Paradise if it was right in
front of you but you might get a glimmer
of it and so you move towards it and you
grow and then the next time you open
your eyes you see a little bit more
clearly and that's what happens is that
just happens over and over right it
keeps
moving and so you move like this
but the thing that's so cool is that all
those zigs and zags you say and each of
those zags is and zigs is a catastrophy
I hit a wall my God and then I had to
die a little bit and I barely got back
up it's a phoenix transformation at each
at each turn and it's painful but the
thing is is that even though you've
you've traveled 20 miles let's say on
that road and you've only moved three
miles forward you've moved three miles
forward instead of falling backwards
because that's the thing too is that if
you stand still you fall backwards you
cannot stand still because the world
moves away from you if you stand still
and there's no stasis there's only
backwards and so if you're not moving
backward back forwards then you're
moving backwards and that's
more more of the underlying truth of of
the Matthew principle to those who have
everything more will be given from those
who have nothing everything will be
taken taken it's a warning do not stay
in one
place well as you Zig and zag maybe the
maybe the cataclysm of each
transformation starts to lessen there's
not so much of you that has to die with
every
mistake and maybe you end up oriented at
least reasonably properly and if you
were sensible that would have been your
trip but it wasn't right it's that and
perhaps it's a lot worse than that
perhaps per there's no shortage of
backtracking but it doesn't matter
because as you stumble forward you you
illuminate and inform yourself and
perhaps that's partly because the world
is made of information and if you
encounter it and Tangle with it then it
informs you and then you become informed
and then you're information and then
you're
ready and so God says to Abraham I will
make of thee a great name
and I will bless thee and make thy name
great and thou shalt be a
blessing that's that's a good offer
fundamentally I mean it
means what does it mean to to be made a
great nation of well perhaps it has
something to do directly with your
descendants but I don't think it's just
that you know is if you're a force for
good in the world then that radiates out
from you and if you good enough it's
difficult to say how much of an impact
on things you could have you know dovi
who is a very crazy person partly
because of his epilepsy he said a man is
not only responsible for everything he
does but for everything that everyone
else does and you
think well
no no
no and yes sometimes no
sometimes that's what you think if
you're cataclysmic cataclysmically
depressed right is that your sins are so
egregious that that they're unforgivable
and that in some manner you're at you're
at fault for everything that's terrible
with the world but there's actually
truth in that and there's actually
Redemptive truth in that is that things
wouldn't be so bad if you weren't
so if you weren't so far from what you
could be and that's terribly pessimistic
because it's all on you man but it's
terribly optimistic because God there's
a lot of things that you could do and if
you're crying out for something to do
then that's the best news you could
possibly have it's like things aren't so
good but neither are you so if you stop
doing the things that you knew to be
destructive which is the right place to
start you know if you're going to clean
up your room what do you do first well
you just get rid of the mess you know
and you know what not no one has to come
in and tell you hopefully what's the
worst mess it's just it announces itself
to you and you can certainly know
yourself and this is a very easy
meditative exercise to sit down and
think okay I'm doing one thing really
stupidly that I should stop doing it's
like how long is it going to take you to
figure out what that is it's about two
seconds right you've known it forever
and you could even make it less
demanding you could say there are some
stupid things that I'm doing that I know
are stupid and wrong that I could stop
doing that I would stop doing
and then you can just start with that
and you can just do that and maybe it's
just a little thing although it's not
because it's it's a it's a step forward
on the proper Voyage it's not a small
thing and you think well what would
happened you could say let's do this for
a year or even a month just try not to
do things you know to be stupid and
wrong for a month and that means not to
say things you know to be stupid and
wrong as well maybe that's the most
important thing just do it as an
experiment see what happens and it's so
fun because I have people writing to me
from all over the world who are saying
they're doing that they're saying well
you know I cleaned up my room and and
then I stopped saying stupid things and
my God it's like things are way better
it's like who would have guessed it you
know and
so it's lwh hanging fruit man because
there's a that's the other thing if
there's a lot of things wrong with you
then it's it's really easy to start
fixing it you know you got so much
there's so much territory that you can
inhabit I will make of thee a great
nation I Will Bless thee that's good I
mean the whole nation thing that's
positive but to have God on your side
that's you know you might want that when
things get rough that would be good and
make thy name great and thou shalt be a
blessing
wonderful that's a good
deal and I will bless them that bless
thee that's good too and curse him that
curseth thee and in thee shall all
families of the earth be
blessed that's something
that's something wouldn't it be
something if you could wake up and your
day was cons composed in part of people
thanking you for all the good things
you've done in the world wouldn't that
be
good it's not impossible for that to
happen so Abram
departed yes as the Lord had spoken unto
him and lot went with him and Abram was
7 and five years when he departed out of
heran
that's old now Abraham lives a long time
but this is also part of the story so he
has a wife who can't have children he
has nothing obviously he's been hanging
around dad's Shack for a little too long
given that he's 75 right it's time it's
time to get a fire lit underneath him a
bit and so he's not got much going for
him but he still decides to to move
forward and I've seen this too you know
like if you don't have your destiny in
Hand by your time you're 30 it's it's
rough you start hurting and if you don't
have your Destiny at Hand by the time
you're 40 then you really start hurting
and 40 is a
real fork in the
road the fork in the road that's always
where you meet the Devil by the way and
that's because every time you have to
make a decision the possibility of evil
beckons that's why that is I had a
friend I've told you a little about him
and he killed himself just after 40 know
he had had a book published with a very
small press he was quite a good writer
but he could could not get himself
together and it hit him too hard at 40
and I'm not saying that it's hopeless at
40 I'm not saying that and and I'm not
saying that partly because of these
verses but also partly because of what
I've seen in my clinical practice I've
had people come to me who have had very
chaotic and ill-spent lives let's say
who were in that neighborhood of Age and
and it's true for people who are older
as well who then decided to make a real
effort and to try to make where they
were better you know instead of being
bitter out where they weren't because
that's the bitterness that really does
you in it's really not good it's the
opposite of gratitude it's it's it's the
manifestation of resentment it makes you
malevolent it's very very bad to be
bitter it's not it's
not it's hell to be
bitter and if you're 40 and you're not
successful then you have to accept your
lot and you have to start to improve
what's right in front of you and if you
do that it doesn't take very long it's
quite interesting to watch people things
be a lot better in 6 months and they can
be way better in 2 years like it's a
struggle uphill struggle but it's by no
means impossible and and I don't know
again what the limit of that is I
suppose it depends to degree to some
degree on the degree of your commitment
but anyway so Abra it's another
indication of the the real validity of
this story God isn't setting this up to
be easy right Abraham's old and and and
his and his wife is old too and more
than that she's Barren how is he going
to be the father of Nations how is he
going to be successful ful well the
initial departure point is insufficient
radically insufficient and and that's
very inspiring because it means that you
can start from where you
are so Abram departed as the Lord had
spoken unto him and lot went with him
and Abram was 75 years old when he
departed out of heran and Abraham took
sarai's wife and and lot his brother's
son and all their substance that they
had
gathered and you know he has a
relationship with lot right he doesn't
have his own son but he his brother died
and so he takes his nephew as his son
that's grateful you know he could be
very angry and and have nothing to do
with him because he didn't get his own
son but that isn't that isn't what
happens is he's offered a substitute
let's say and he accepts it and so good
for him you know and and
that's and that's also something that
I've seen that characterizes people who
can make the best of a bad lot is they
don't get
exactly what they want but something
comes along that offers possibilities
that
are sufficient perhaps if exploited
properly and they open their heart and
welcom them in instead of rejecting them
in bitterness and so that's a good thing
and that's part of Abraham's
character and Abram took sarai's wife
and lot his brother's son and all their
substance that they had gathered and all
the souls that they had gotten in heran
and they went forth to go into the land
of Canaan into Exile let's say and into
the land of Canaan they came
and that's
another repetition of the transformation
story right you have to go to a land
where you're not
welcome and Abram passed through the
land unto the place of sichem Unto the
plain of morah and the Canaanite was
then in the land and the Lord appeared
unto Abram and said unto thy seed I will
give you this land and there he build an
altar to the Lord who appeared unto him
and he removed from then unto a mountain
on the east of bethl and pitched his
tent having bethl on the west and high
on the East and there he built an altar
unto the Lord and called upon the name
of the Lord now we don't understand
these rituals precisely you know I don't
know if the people who did this engaged
in a meditative ritual was that the idea
that you take something of value you do
this you you undertake this dramatic
transformation a life and death
transformation and is that an aid to
meditation and what do you do do you sit
down and think do you do you pray pray
being to ask you know to what do I do
next how do I Orient myself in the world
it's a useful exercise to do that to I
think it's something that people could
do every morning I think it's useful to
sit down and think okay what's the most
important thing I should do
today what I have an array of things
that call to me to be done some of which
I will do with joy and some of which I
will bear as responsibilities but I they
array themselves in front of me and what
what should I attend to First well do
you ask or do you decide and it seems to
me when I do it because I do it all the
time I do it every morning I try to sit
down and think okay I've got things that
I would like to do and things that call
to me out of
necessity what do I do first and it's
not so much a decision as it is a
question and and I don't know what I'm
calling on it's I'm calling on my
capacity to think I suppose but that's
not my capacity
exactly I I'm I I can I can commune with
whatever provides answers and I can
think that that's me thinking
but and it isn't that I believe that I
can't think I do believe that I can
consciously think but that's not the
same as calling for inspiration it's not
the same process just like a dream is
not conscious thinking it's something
that happens to you and that kind of
inspiration is also something that
happens to you because I ask myself well
what's the most important thing I could
do next and then I have an answer to
that but it isn't because I decided
exactly I've decided that I'll do it
whatever it is and that I want to know
what it is those are the decisions but
but there's an involuntary aspect to the
Sorting that occurs and and that's the
psychological equivalent I suppose to
this and I guess the sacrifice
is when I feel that I will do whatever
it is that calls to be done then I don't
do the other things that I might want to
do and that's a
sacrifice it's to me it's the proper
sacrifice because my sense is that
things don't go properly unless you do
what's most important and if I want
things to go properly and I do because
I've had my taste of things not going
properly I want things to go properly
and so
then it's not so difficult to do what's
necessary to to do what makes things go
properly under those circumstances and
it's hardly
see this is partly why the story of
Sodom and Gomorrah is embedded in the
abrahamic stories I think because that's
an apocalyptic story right if things go
badly enough the whole city is
destroyed and then and the reason it
goes badly is because the people in the
city do not behave properly and the
people in the city might be you and so
if you're not behaving properly then you
go and so does the city and maybe you
don't want maybe you do want that but
maybe you don't want that and if you
don't want that then maybe and you know
that if you don't do things properly
then it's you and the city if you
actually know that then maybe that
terrifies you badly enough so that
you're willing to make the sacrifice to
do the right things instead of the
impulsive things that you might
otherwise want to
do you know I learned from Victor Frankl
and from Carl Jong and from Alexander
Sol niton and from many of the people
whose works on the Holocaust that I read
and on the catastrophes in the Soviet
Union and the people who' studied it
most deeply always came to the same
conclusion the state became corrupted
because each individual allowed
themselves to be corrupted or perhaps
participated joyfully in the process of
being corrupted and the consequence of
that was the end of the
world and so what that means is that if
you don't behave properly then you bring
about the end of the world
and maybe you think well that's only the
end of your world fair enough or maybe
it's the only the end of your family's
world you know which I suppose might
give you some pause but there's more to
it than that because you're connected to
everyone else and what you do that isn't
good distributes itself and all the
things you don't do that could be good
take away from the
whole and so if you know that and I do
think you know that if you take it
seriously because if you look
at if you look at the historical events
the cataclysmic events of the 20th
century seriously I do not think that
you can fail to come to that
conclusion and Abraham journeyed going
on still towards the
South that's interesting because to go
south means to go downhill to it's not
good to go south it's colloquial for
going to where you shouldn't go and so
this is what happens to Abraham you know
he his Ascent is preceded by a descent
and that's very common in life I would
say and so
so the Redemptive element of this
narrative is that if the Covenant is
constructed properly so it's an arc
which is your decision to align yourself
with God for all intents and purpos says
then even the journey South can be part
of a broader Journey
upward and there was a famine in the
land that's Mother Nature failing to
cooperate I mean that's got to be pretty
disheartening for Abraham don't you
think because he finally gets it
together when he's 75 to leave and then
you know because God says well it's you
know get going and and so the first
place he goes everyone's starving to
death it's like you know you might think
about that as a test of Faith wouldn't
you say but he keeps going and then what
happens well he has to go to Egypt so
great he goes where he's starving where
everyone's starving and then to get away
from where everyone's starving he goes
to a
tyranny so the whole beginning of the
story is not particularly
auspicious and Abram went down into
Egypt to sojourn there for the famine
was Grievous in the
land it's a repetition of the same idea
again there's downhill Voyage out into
chaos right it's it's repeated over and
over that the beginning of Abraham's
journey is basically a sequence of of EX
of experiences of Exile chaos tyranny
and catastrophe well you should be able
to relate to that you know how hard it
is to get things together you know you
go out to do what you're supposed to do
say and there's you're beset by the
intransigence of the world and failure
well so what are you supposed to do
about that
well maintain your faith in the good and
continue to move forward that's the idea
and part of that even if even if you
don't buy the metaphor it's like what
are you going to do
instead that won't make it
worse so even if there if it isn't an up
that you're pursuing you're at least
forestalling the transformation of the
chaos into your of your life into sheer
hell and that can certainly happen you
know you see people who are having a
terrible time and then you see people
who are having a terrible time who are
also in hell and it's a lot better to
just have a terrible time than to have a
terrible time and be in hell at the same
time and it came to pass when he was
come to near to enter into Egypt that he
said unto Sariah's wife behold now I
know that thou art a fair woman to look
upon therefore it shall come to pass
when the Egyptians shall see thee that
they shall say this is his wife and they
will kill me but they will save thee
alive so look I mean Abraham is Abraham
is really having a rough time he's a
failure right I mean he's wandering
around through the land of starvation
now he's going to go be a quasi slave in
Egypt he has this incredibly attractive
wife and all he can look forward to is
the fact that the most successful man in
Egypt the Pharaoh will take her from him
so he's got the whole embitterment thing
pretty much nailed down as far as I can
tell and this is when he makes one of
his errors let's say and one of the
errors that humanizes him say I pray
thee that thou art my sister that it may
be well for me for thy sake and my soul
shall live because of
thee and it came to pass that when Abram
was come into Egypt the Egyptians beheld
the woman that she was very fair the
princes also of pharaoh saw her and
commended her before pharaoh and the
woman was taken into Pharaoh's house and
he entreated Abram well for her sake and
he had sheep and oxen and he asses and
Men servants and Maid servants and she
asses and camels so actually things work
out pretty well for for Abram despite
his deceit right which is quite
interesting and I guess it's because if
the overarching structure is solid
something like that it's something like
that then then errors can still be
forgiven to speak about it from a
metaphorical
perspective and the Lord plagued pharaoh
and his house with great plagues because
of Sarai Abram's
wife well it doesn't seem very fair but
because the Pharaoh didn't know but but
it's not the right way to look at it the
right way to look at it see there's a
story later in the in the Bible about
David and David David could be a pretty
bad guy you know so one of the things he
does is when he becomes king he he's in
his castle and he's looking over the
city and he sees a woman nude ba bathing
nude sunbathing nude on on a on a a roof
out on the city and he's Smitten by her
floored by her and he has inquiries made
about who she is her name is ba Sheba
and and he finds out who her husband is
and her husband actually happens to be a
general in his
army and he arranges for that General to
be put at the thick of the battle and
killed and then he takes baath
Sheba so and and
and the Lord is not pleased by that
let's put it that way and that's
interesting you know it's it's an
interesting story because you might say
well why can't the king do whatever the
hell he wants like seriously he's the
king he's not just and he's not like the
prime minister or the President right he
he's the king and so you might say well
why is the king subject to any rules
whatsoever what's the rationale for the
king being subject to rules well the
rational emerges in these stories is
there are social strictures
that are such that even if the ruler of
the land transgresses against them there
will be hell to pay and that's
continually presented over and over in
the biblical stories and it's a natural
law sort of idea it's that there are
there are intrinsic rules to the game of
social human being and if you and maybe
intrinsic rules to the to the Natural
State of human being you break those
rules consciously or uncons iously at
your absolute Peril and not only at your
peril but at the Peril of the state and
it doesn't matter who you are and so I
would say this is actually an indication
of God being fair rather than being
unfair because the rule here is Pharaoh
or
not you don't get to take someone else's
wife and ignorance is no excuse now you
might say that's a little bit harsh and
perhaps it is a little bit harsh but
it's not without Merit the idea is not
without Merit and of course Abram
is complicit in this despite that he is
successful and Pharaoh called Abram and
said what is this that thou Hast done
unto me why did thou now tell me that
she was thy wife why said thou you she
is my sister I might have taken her to
me to wife now therefore Behold thy wife
take her and go thy way and Pharaoh
commanded his men concerning him and
they sent him away and his wife and all
that he
had and Abram went up out of Egypt he
and his wife and all that he had and lot
with him into the South and Abram was
very rich in cattle in silver and in
gold and that's so it's interesting you
know Abraham he he goes to the place of
famine and then he goes to the to the
place of terity and then he he lies and
then he almost loses his wife but
because he
goes things work out for him and so hoay
for that and he went on his JY journees
from the south even to bethl unto the
place where his tent had been at the
beginning between bethl and high unto
the place of the altar so he makes
another sacrifice which he had made
there at the first and there Abram
called on the name of the Lord well so
he's had an adventure right he's he's
he's he's finished his journey and and
so there's a culminating point in this
narrative and now he doesn't know what
to do he's he's left the place he's at
he doesn't know what to do so it's time
to build an altar and make a sacrifice
and figure out and to ask for divine
guidance once again to to figure out
okay well i' I've done that Been There
Done That What's Next and I'm the
question is asked seriously and this is
something to consider if you want to
know what to do ask seriously and say
I'm willing to see Abraham sacrifices a
life to his
vow well so what do you do well you
don't sacrifice an animal you don't you
don't make a blood sacrifice you do it
psychologically you say I'm going to
sacrifice my life to this aim
that's what you do if you're serious
what do I do next well I'm going to
sacrifice my life to this aim what is it
that I should do that's worth
sacrificing my life to that's a serious
question well and maybe that's the sort
of question that people don't ask
because they're afraid of the
seriousness of the question and the and
the what the magnitude of the potential
answer do you really want to know what
you should do that would be worth
sacrificing your life to well the answer
is yes because it's worth it but the
answer is also no because
like really it's it's your life you know
what if you're
wrong and you're probably
wrong but maybe that doesn't matter
maybe it doesn't matter because maybe
the rightness is in the process and not
in the and not in the decision right
because it's not it's the beginning of a
sequence of decisions as we've already
pointed outto the place of the altar
which he had made there at the first and
there Abram called on the name of the
Lord and lot also and lot also which
went with Abraham Abra had flocks and
herds and Tents and the land was not
able to Bear them that they might dwell
together for their substance was great
so that they could not dwell together
and there was a Strife between the
herdmen of Abram's cattle the Cowboys
and the Herdman of Lot's cattle and the
Canaanite and the perizzite dwelt then
in the land well and that's interesting
too because you know Abram's having a
pretty good time of it now right he's
out of starvation hey that's good he's
out of the Tyranny now he's kind of
wealthy and then the story flips on him
he's wealthy and now bad thing happens
to him right and say he's got all this
wealth and so does his nephew and now
they can't get along because they have
too much stuff so that's quite comical
as well I think that's a comic interlude
here now they handle it
properly and Abram said unto lot let
there be no Strife I pray thee between
me and thee and between my Herdman and
thy Herdman because we're brothers is
not the whole land before thee separate
thyself I pray thee from me if you'll
take the left then I'll take the right
or if you depart to the right then I'll
go to the left so B basically they sit
down and say well you know one of us has
got to get out of town and it can be one
or the other it doesn't really matter we
can flip a coin or but we have to we
have to separate and so they they do it
amicably and lot lifted up his eyes and
looked at all of the plain of Jordan
that it was well watered everywhere so
that's an intimation of Eden right
because you remember Eden means well
watered
place before the Lord destroyed Sodom
and Gomorrah even as the garden of the
Lord like the land of Egypt as thou
comest unto zor so interesting you get
foreshadowing here again right so lot
and Abram are making the decision about
where to go and and lot looks out and
and sees a a reasonable place but then
this warning comes up that there's a
there's a city out there there's a place
out there where things are not going to
go well things are being done badly and
things are not going to go well then lot
shows him all the plane of Jordan and
Lot journeyed East and they separated
themselves the one from the other Abram
dwelt in the land of Canaan and then lot
dwelt in the cities of the plain and
pitched his tent towards
Sodom but the men of Sodom were Wicked
and sinners before the Lord exceedingly
now the word sin I've mentioned this to
you before I think it's an interesting
word it's it's the derivation of an
archery term in my understanding of its
derivation it it the Greek word was
hamartia and hamartia is an archery term
which means to to miss the bullsi and
you think it's worth thinking about that
metaphorically because you got to think
about all the ways that you could miss
the bullseye right you could close your
eyes that's very common you could just
not lift up the damn bow and arrow to
begin with you could face the wrong way
you could be unskilled in your aim but I
and I also like the the the archery
metaphor because human beings are built
on a hunting platform right and we
always aim at things we're we're things
that we're we're ballistic creatures on
a trajectory always and we're always
aiming at something we're always aiming
at the Mark and which is of course what
you do when you hunt right because you
have to hit the mark precisely and
that's what we're like and so but we're
like that psychologically we have to aim
at something and then move towards it
and and so to sin is to miss the Mark is
to is to miss the bullseye to to fail to
take aim to aim
badly to aim carelessly or to not aim at
all and that says well
that's that's like a sin of a mission
that's to not do and then to be Wicked
is to aim at what you know you shouldn't
aim at and again I don't I don't think
of that as an external morality
precisely I think that you can read the
entire biblical narrative again from a
psychological perspective and say we're
not talking about external codes of
conduct here although we could we're not
the wickedness that's being described is
the act of you doing something that you
know to be wrong period you know and you
may do something you don't know if it's
wrong or not that isn't the sort of
thing that we're talking about and we're
not talking about the things that you do
that are right are that other people
think are wrong we're not talking about
those either we're talking about those
things that you consciously do although
you know them to be wrong yourself and
that's the things that seem to get
people into the most trouble in these
stories and I I believe that to be the
case I think that's very accurate
psychologically it's amazing because I
see this all the time if you do
something wrong and it's because you're
ignorant you don't know better it it
doesn't go well for you that's the case
but if you do something wrong and you
know it's wrong
the punishment is is manifold and I
think the reason for that I think the
reason for that is because that makes
you can it means you betray your own
ideal right if you just don't know well
you haven't betrayed your ideal you're
just not together maybe you're even
willfully blind but if you do something
you know to be wrong then you've
betrayed your own ideal and that lands
you Cain says to God once Cain destroys
Abel he says I cannot Bear My
Punishment and the Lord said unto to
Abram after that lot was separated from
lift up now thine
eyes look upward and look from the place
where thou are northward and Southward
and Eastward and Westward for all the
land which thou seest to thee I will
give it and to thy seed forever and I
will make thy seed as the dust of the
earth so that if a man can number the
dust of the earth then shall all thy
seed be numbered arise walk through the
land in the length of it and the breadth
of it for I will give it unto thee
in the C Cathedral at chart I can't say
that properly because by French is
non-existent so a cathedral is a cross
and the transformation takes place at
the Crux of the Cross which is exactly
right because the the transformation
takes place at the point of maximal
suffering and the cathedral is designed
to indicate that right symbolically now
what happens in a religious ceremony is
also a journey and it's a journey in
some sense to the holy city and then
that's also played out in the idea of
pilgrimage right because you go to the
holy city actually you go to Jerusalem
or wherever it is that you think the
holy city is you go there and that takes
you out of your country and away from
your kin and away from your family into
the Strange Land and as you make the
journey you transform and when you come
back you're not the same That's The
Hobbit right that's the story of The
Hobbit but let's say you can't afford to
go on a pilgrimage so you go to the
Cathedral at chart and there's a huge
maze on the ground and it's the world
North West South and East just as God
describes here so it's laid out and you
enter the maze at one side and in the
middle is a stone pattern that looks
like a
flower and it's it's the place where
being Wells forth and it's at the center
of the cathedral
and what that means is that if you
accept your suffering then you move to
the place where the spirit of being
Wells forth that's what that means and
so you enter
the the Maze and you walk and it's
divided into
quadrants and you walk one quadrant
completely and then the maze pathway
takes you into the next quadrant and you
walk that completely and then it takes
you to the third one and the fourth one
and then when you walk the maze
completely everywhere when you've gone
everywhere in the world north south east
and west where you've when you've
traversed the territory completely then
you come to the center and then it's
yours and that's what this is so I've
noticed when I've been renovating houses
I like to do that I paid a lot of
attention to the psychological process
of house
renovation because I learned from Yung
that Yung said this this is something
man he said because he was he was
talking about the stages of integration
psychological IC integration and he
looked beyond P I would say um although
P looked very far he said here here's a
conjunction you have to get your
rationality and your emotion together
that's a male female conjunction
symbolically speaking male rationality
female emotionality you want to bring
those together so that they're oriented
in the same direction your emotions and
your rationality serve the same purpose
so then you're unified in Mind and
Spirit let's say but that's not good
enough once you've got that together
then there's a you have a body and then
that's a male female conjunction again a
Divine conjunction the recreation of
Adam before his division into female and
male and the Reconstruction of the
androgynous Christ that all that all
those ideas are linked together so now
you have your emotion and your
rationality moving in the same direction
but you're not acting it
out so now you have to unite that
abstract part of you with your body and
start acting out what you think can feel
and that's the next conjunction but it's
not the last one the last conjunction is
when you realize that there is no
distinction between you and your
experience they're the same thing and so
then when you put together your house
you're putting together
yourself so I've noticed in when I've
lived in places rented or owned didn't
matter that if there were part of the
place if there was a part of the place
that I hadn't attended to whatever that
might mean it might meant clean
it might have meant fixed but it
certainly meant at least thoroughly
investigated then that was chaos it was
like it was it was like the desert that
part that's that's a way of thinking
about it it wasn't mine even if I owned
it wasn't mine I had to interact with it
before it became mine and I had to
interact with it and I had to put it in
order and then it became mine and then
and then to the degree that it became
mine and was in order then I was also
put in order now you know that because
you go into places that make you
uncomfortable and maybe it's your own
house it's highly probable it's highly
probable I you know I walk into well
Chinese doctors do this traditional
Chinese doctors they go into place
people's place and they they diagnose
their health conditions on the on the
balance of Yin and Yang Chaos and Order
they walk into a house this is easy to
do you walk into a house there's too
much chaos hey you can detect that in no
time flat everything is out of order and
chaotic you don't even want to be there
you certainly don't want to open the
refrigerator that's for sure and there
are things that should have been done
years ago everywhere and every one of
those things is a fight that hasn't
happened and something that's been
avoided and you can't even walk in there
and maintain your health as soon as you
walk in there you're sicker than you
were when you were outside and that's
one sort of place and then another sort
of place is you go in you look at the
living room and the person has vacuumed
the living room rug and the lines that
were vacuumed are parallel to one
another and the and the furniture is
covered with plastic and you get a glass
of water and then just as you're going
to set it down on the coffee table the
person rushes over and puts a coaster
underneath it and everything in that
house says to you that it would be a lot
more perfect in that house if you were
either not there or dead and that's the
and that's the message that the whole
house is blasting at you and if you
happen to live there then you're going
to be sick and what you're going to be
sick from is too much order and in the
other house you're going to be sick from
too much chaos
and so when you interact with a
house the unexplored parts are the chaos
that have the parts that you have not
yet contended with are the chaos that is
not yet been transformed by your
embodied logos action into habitable
territory and it does not belong to
you arise walk through the land in the
length of it and the breadth of it for I
will give it unto thee then Abram
removed his tent and came dwelt in the
plain of mamra which is in heon and
built there an altar unto the
Lord and it came to pass in the days of
amrel king of shanar arok king of alisar
chalomar there's a lot of Kings we won't
talk about them these made war with
barah king of Sodom and with Bersa king
of Gomorrah shab king of adma and the
king of Bella which is zor and these
were joined together in the veil of
sidom which is the salt
sea now this is actually very much
relevant hey because you see the veil of
sedom which is the salt sea is the
farthest South you can go if South is
down because it's the Dead Sea and the
Dead Sea is the lowest place that there
is so what's happened is that there's
chaos in the lowest place that there is
that's what this story says and what
happens to lot is he gets Tangled Up in
the chaos of the lowest place that there
is
and in the 14th year came chador Lor and
the kings that were with him and smote
the Reames and astroth kame and the zims
in ham and the emmans in Shava K katham
and the horites in their Mount sire unto
elperin which is by the Wilderness and
they returned and came to en mishpat
which is cadesh and smote all the
country the
amalekites amalekites and the amorites
that dwelt in
he hes
haaz zontar there we go perhaps and
there went out the king of Sodom and the
king of Gomorrah and the king of adma
and the king of zbam and the king of
Bella the same is zor and they joined
battle with them in the veil of sidm so
this is absolute chaos and Mayhem in the
lowest place it's hell
essentially with chedore the king of
alam and with tidal king of Nations and
amrel king of shanar and arot king of
elazar Four Kings with five and the veil
of sidm was full of slim pits low and
hell likee with war isn't enough they
had to throw the Slime pits in there
apparently around the Dead Sea there are
pits of bite bit bitumen like the like
the tar pits in near La and so this
seems to actually be historically
accurate and the kings of Sodom and
Gomorrah fled and fell there and they
that remained fled to the mountain and
they took their goods and they took all
the goods of Sodom and Gomorrah and all
their victuals and went their way and
they took lot Abram's brother's son who
dwelt in Sodom and his goods and
departed so Abram has a family member
who falls into the lowest place and
there came one that had escaped and told
Abram the Hebrew for he dwelt in the
plain of mam the Amorite brother of
ishol and brother of Anor and these were
Confederate with Abram and when Abram
heard that his brother was taken captive
he armed his trained servants born in
his own house 318 and pursued them unto
Dan well so now we also know that
Abraham is a pretty brave guy right he
gets word that this horrible War has
broken out in the worst of all possible
places and that his nephew is involved
and the first thing he does is you know
Mount up his posy and get the hell in
there and rescue his nephew so Abraham's
no whatever goodness is from the Old
Testament perspective it isn't
harmlessness right it isn't emasculation
and castration it's not that it's not
weakness it's not the inability to fight
none of that is associated with virtue
it's the sort of strength that enables
someone to mount and armed team of 300
people when he finds out that his nephew
is being kidnapped in a terrible war and
to get the hell out there and take him
back and so that's a that's a that's a
that's a call to to it's a call to power
that not not a kind of peaceful meekness
that's funny too because you know
there's a line in the New Testament the
meek shall inherit the earth I got to
look at my phone for a sec here because
I don't know what time it is there's a
line in the New Testament that says and
send The Sermon on the Mount says the
meek shall inherit the earth and that I
that line always bothered me I thought
no way that's not that that's not right
Meek can't be the right word so when I
was doing the story of Noah and talking
about The Sermon on the Mount I spent a
bunch of time looking at commentaries on
that line looking at the roots the you
know the Greek roots and the Hebrew
roots and trying to figure out what that
meant and It Meek does not mean Meek
that's wrong here's what it means those
who have weapons and know how to use
them but still keep them sheathed will
inherit the earth Jesus that's a lot
different man it's a lot better right
because the way it's normally it's
normally interpreted is if you're so
weak that you're harmless then things
will go well for you it's like no that's
not right that's that's not that can't
be right it doesn't fit with the
narrative it certainly doesn't fit with
this narrative and he divided himself
against them he and his servants by
night and smot them and pursued them
onto hobah which is on the left side of
Damascus and he brought back all the
goods and his brother lot and and his
goods and the women also and the people
good work Abraham and the kings of Sodom
went out to meet him after his return at
the slaughter of chalomar and of the
kings that there were there with him at
the valley of Shiva which is the King's
Dale and melch as a king of Salem
brought forth Bread and
Wine and he was the priest of the most
high God and he blessed him and said
Blessed Be Abram of the most high god
possessor of Heaven and Earth and
blessed be the most high God which has
delivered thine enemies into thine hand
and gave him TI of all and the king of
Sodom said to Abraham give me the
persons and take thy Goods to
thyself this that that were the goods
that Abram that Abram rescued right of
the of the Kings and Abram said to the
king of Sodom I have lift up mine hand
unto the Lord what is that mean it means
I've made a vow that's what it means
that that's what that phrase means I've
made a vow to God the possessor of
Heaven and Earth that I will not take
anything from a thread even to a
shoelace I won't take anything that's
yours lest you should say I've made
Abram Rich I'll take only that which my
young men have eaten and the portion of
men that went with me and Anor eshkol
and mam let them take their portion and
so Abraham decides here he's he's made
this immense
sacrifice and done this incredibly Brave
act and rescued his nephew and rescued
the king's goods and and they offer him
a reward and he says I'm not going to
take the reward and the reason for that
is that he doesn't want to contaminate
the the the ethical purity of his
actions he doesn't want to be paid he
doesn't want it he doesn't want to
benefit from doing he doesn't want to
what is it exactly he doesn't want to
benefit inappropriately from doing the
right thing it's something like that and
so it's another Testament to his
character and a very complex Testament
right because he's not a s he's not a
good man in any simple sense I mean look
what's just happened he's he's mounted
an armed he's mounted an armed
uh he's he's LED an army into battle and
and part and and participated in a
Slaughter he refuses to benefit from it
except to get back what was his that's
it he refuses to benefit from it except
to get back what was rightfully his and
in that way he maintains his Covenant
with
God even to a Sho latch at I anything
though never so small or me lest thou
should claim a share with God in the
honor Duty him this is from Matthew P
who is an English non-conformist
Theologian commenting on that line even
to a Sho latchet I.E anything though
never so mean or small lest thou should
claim a share with God in the honor due
to him to whose blessing alone I do and
I will owe my riches or lest thou should
say Abram is enriched with my spoils and
however he pretended kindness and
charity yet indeed it was his
covetousness that put him upon this
work after these things the word of the
Lord came unto Abram in a vision saying
saying fear not Abram I'm thy shield and
thy exceedingly and thy exceeding great
reward the vision issue
[Music]
again while we went through that last
week fear not Abram I am thy shield and
thy exceeding great reward and Abram
said Lord God what can you give me
seeing as I'm childless childless and
that's the only thing that matters to
Abram at this point and the steward of
my house is this elier of d damasc us no
kin and Abraham said Abram said behold
to me thou Hast given no seed and lo one
born in my house is mine he and behold
the word of the Lord came unto
him saying this shall not be thine Heir
but he that shall come forth out of
thine own bowel should be nine hair so
he gets promised The Impossible once
again and he brought him forth abroad
and said now look towards the heaven and
tell the Stars if thou be able to number
them and he said unto him so shall thy
seed be and he believed in the Lord and
counted to him for
righteousness you see and this this this
is the Covenant idea this belief because
here's the
belief it's the willingness to act as if
the world is constructed so that if you
do the right thing the best possible
outcome will occur it's a decision
that's the C Covenant right it's a
decision about how to live in the world
because the evidence can't be there
before you make the
decision right and so you might hedge
your bests you know when when Christ
comes back in the Book of Revelation to
judge people because he comes back as a
judge and virtually everyone
gets cast out with the chaff and not
saved with the wheat and he he says
something very interesting he appears in
the vision with a sword coming out of
his mouth it's a horrifying
vision and he divides the the he divides
Humanity into the Damned and the saved
or the dam yes the Damned and the saved
he says something very interesting he
says to those who were neither hot nor
cold I will spew you out of my mouth and
and it's it's a it's a it's a disgust
metaphor right and what it says is that
the worst punishment
isn't waiting
for those who committed to something and
did
wrong the worst punishment is reserved
for those who committed to nothing and
stayed on the
fence and that's really something too
that's really something to think about
and it's also something I believe to be
true because I see that stasis is
utterly destructive because there's no
progress all there is is movement
backwards there's aging and suffering
and no progress and so to not commit to
anything is the worst of all
transgressions to commit means to put
your body and soul into something to
offer your life as a sacrifice means
that you're willing to make a bargain
with fate and the bargain is I'm going
to act as if if I give it my all then
the best possible thing will happen
because of that and to to not see the
analogy between that and the the AC of
faith in God is to misunderstand the
story completely and it has to be an Act
of Faith because how are you going to
know you can look at other people but
isn't going to do it it's at kirkgard
was very clear about this sort of thing
there's certain sorts of truths that you
can only learn for yourself through
experience and that's of course why
Abram also has to go out alone right he
has to leave his K it's it's an
individual it's the individuation
process like dying it's something that
you do alone there's no way you can tell
what is within your grasp let's say
unless you make the ultimate
sacrifice and there's no way of finding
out without actually making it and so
that's the sacrificial act right that's
that's
reemphasized in the act of
Abram being called upon to sacrifice
Isaac you think about that is Abram he's
been doing he's been like breaking
himself into pieces trying to progress
forward through starvation and tyranny
and War and deceit and the potential
loss of his wife and childlessness and
like everything that can really befall
you in some sense and finally God grants
him Isaac when he's old it's impossible
he gets Isaac his son and then what does
God do next is say well you know that
son that you've been waiting for so for
so long it's like I'd like to see just
exactly what you're made of so I think
you should offer him up as a sacrifice
and I mean it's a very barbaric story in
a sense and maybe in more than just a
sense but Abraham does maintain his
Covenant he's willing to make the
sacrifice he's willing to make this is
the thing he's willing to make whatever
sacrifice is necessary to keep his
Covenant with God intact and that that's
that and that's the
decision well maybe it's no surprise
that people don't do
that and he believed in the Lord and he
counted it to him for righteousness and
he said unto him I am the Lord that
brought thee out of er of the cheles to
give this land to you to inherit it and
he said Lord God whereby shall I know
that I shall inherit it and he said to
him this is a sacrificial story again
take an E A heer of three years and a
boat of three years and a ram of three
years and a turtle dove and a young
pigeon it's fairly specific actually and
he took all these and divided them and
laid each piece one against another but
the birds divided he not now there's a
reason for that and I don't know the
reason for it and when the fowls came
down upon the carcasses Abram drove them
away and when the sun was going down a
deep sleep fell upon Abram and low a
horror of great Darkness fell upon him
that didn't mean he was afraid of the
dark which is what I thought it meant
when I first read it it isn't what it
means it means that he fell into a
trance or something like that and then
he was enveloped by absolute horror so
that's how this Story
begins and here's the commentary from
Joseph Benson who was an English
Methodist Minister who lived in
1749 was born in 1749 and when the sun
was going down about the time of the E
evening oblation the washing for he
Abode by them praying and waiting till
toward evening a deep sleep fell upon
Abram well this was not a common sleep
through weariness or carelessness I
don't know what a Sloop is That's
supposed to be sleep not a common sleep
through weariness or car carelessness
but a Divine
ecstasy that being wholly taken off from
things sensible he might be wholly taken
up with the contemplation of things
spiritual well it really makes you
wonder what Abraham was up to in his
campsite so
he was participating in something that
enabled this
experience and lo a or a horror of great
Darkness fell upon him this was designed
to strike awe upon the spirit of Abram
and to possess him with a holy reverence
holy fear prepares the soul for Holy Joy
God humbles first and then lifts
up Echoes of psychedelic experience and
he said unto Abram know of assurity that
thy seed shall be a stranger in a land
that is not theirs and Shall Serve them
and they shall afflict them 400 years
and also that Nation whom they Shall
Serve I will judge and afterward shall
they come out with great substance and
thou shalt go to thy fathers in peace
Thou shalt be buried in a good old age
but in the fourth generation they shall
come hither again for the iniquity of
the amorites is not yet
full commentaries of Joseph Benson once
again they shall come hither again
hither to the land of Canaan wherein
thou not now art the reason why they
must not have the land of promise in
possession until the fourth generation
is because the iniquity of the amorites
was not yet full the righteous God has
Des determined that the amorites shall
not be cut off till they arrived at such
a pitch of w wickedness and therefore
till it come to that the seed of Abram
must be kept out of possession so the
interpretation of the story essentially
is that Abraham's descendants will end
up enslaved in Egypt for a long a
lengthy period of time and eventually
come back to the land of Canaan and it's
interesting too because this is part of
Abram's bargain with God and in this
divine ision I mean he's been promised
everything but it's a pretty tough
bargain because you know when when when
God is pushed or reveals himself let's
say he says look you're going to get
your damn descendants you know but it's
not going to be uh it's it's it's going
to be a tough Journey they're going to
be SL enslaved for a very long time and
eventually come back and you won't see
it you'll be dead long before then and
so it's a realistic promise in a sense
and you might say well Abram is so D
desperate to to keep the faith that he's
willing to read good into what isn't
good but I think I I think I don't think
that's the right way to look at it I
think the right way to look at it is
that the people who wrote these stories
were very realistic and they knew that
even if things turned out well for you I
mean it was still going to be real you
know it wasn't going to be some fantasy
it's like let's say you have a family
that flourishes is people are still
going to die they're still going to get
sick they're they're still going to have
they're still going to be alive you know
with all of its suffering but it'll be
the but it'll be a life that's rich
enough and complete enough so that it'll
justify its its nature essentially and
so and it came to pass that when the sun
went down and it was dark Behold a
smoking furnace and a burning lamp that
passed between the
pieces Albert barns American Theologian
commented on this the oven of smoke and
lamp of flame symbolize the smoke of
Destruction and the light of Salvation
they're passing passing through the
pieces of the sacrificial victims and
probably consuming them as an accepted
sacri rifice are the ratification of the
Covenant on the part of God as the
dividing and presenting of them were on
the part of
Abram in the same day the Lord made a
covenant with Abram saying unto thy seed
I have given this land from the river of
Egypt unto the Great River the river
Euphrates the kenites and the kenites
and the cadit
ETC now Sarai Abram's wife bear him no
children and she had a handmade wait a
second I think we'll stop there I'm
tiring out and it's just and it's 929 so
that's a very good place to stop so
[Applause]
yes so so I
should I should close properly and just
sum up so what happens here is that that
Abram enters into a covenant with God to
act in the world and the action is an
adventure story essentially and the
adventures repeat and they're and
they're punctuated by success and S and
sacrifice and Rec contemplation right
and so it's this it's this journey it's
the it's the hero's journey uphill I'm
here there's a crisis I Collapse I
reconstruct myself to a higher place and
life is like that continually and that's
the story of Abraham and that's all
contained though it's all contained and
this is the thing that's so cool because
that is what your life is going to be
like whether you plan out your life or
not
it's going to be punctuated like that
maybe it won't go up maybe it'll go down
the question is what sort of container
do you need to be in in order to
tolerate the movement up and down and
that's what the story of Abraham
provides it provides a it provides a
description of the Covenant that's like
the ark the Covenant and the Ark are the
same thing right except the Covenant is
the
psychological equivalent of the Ark and
the Covenant
is have faith in the structure of
existence and go forth forth that's the
Covenant and the and the story
is that's the best possible solution
that you have at
hand all right so I'm going to make a
request with regards to the questions
which may mean you have to reorient
yourself in the line I would like the
first two questions on each side if
possible to relate specifically to
tonight's lecture and then I can and
then I can
uh address more General issues if that's
if that's okay so and I again I would
like you to carefully speak into the mic
so that the people who are watching can
hear can you hear me yeah I
can uh the story about Abraham uh saying
his wife was his sister you referred to
that as him making a mistake I'm not
quite sure I understand how you're
reading that as a mistake seeing as it
was very deliberate decision and it had
a pretty good outcome for him and he
does the same thing a few chapters later
yes this is true you see I don't I don't
I don't feel that I've cracked that part
of that story properly now the reason I
said it was a mistake is because it's
clearly an act of Deceit and it and it
and it does put the Pharaoh in a very
awkward position not to mention s Sarai
by the way or S how do you say that I
don't know how to say that Sarai Sarai
it's SAR to begin with yes is that right
Sarai yes okay and then it's Sarah and
that so Abram means High King something
like that and Abraham means father of
the people and Sarai means princess and
Sarah means mother of the people it's
some I I have it exactly right I'll tell
you next week but that's part of the
name transformation the the it it seems
to me that at least in part it's an
indication of Abra Abraham's willingness
to use a suboptimal solution when driven
to it by necessity I don't think it's a
heroic act to pretend that your wife is
your sister now you know and and and
maybe you might say well under the
circumstances there was nothing else he
could have done but it does seem I can't
see how you can interpret it other than
as a departure from the
truth but I know that that's not all
there is to it and it does seem to work
out well for him and my interpretation
is that well if you're oriented properly
in the world the grace of God allows you
a few necessary mistakes something like
that do do you have an alternative
idea I just don't think I would refer to
it as a mistake well why not what what
is it about that that that is it because
it's Abraham and and it isn't reasonable
to attribute mistakes to him or what is
it it's cuz at least I think it says in
the text that he's looking to get out of
a bad situation and he does whatever is
the best thing that it's available to
him and not to mention as I said he does
the same trick a few chapters later yeah
well maybe maybe it is the case that you
know it's like a white lie issue you
know you say well is a white lie
acceptable I would say well the best
that you can come up with is acceptable
that that doesn't mean it's it's optimal
though right like I I I I'll give you a
a foolish example because it's the best
that I could do at the moment but you
know if you if you have a loved one who
says does this dress make me look
fat the answer to that question is I
don't answer questions like that that's
the answer right because the other
answer is the white lie I mean at least
in this context and that means that on
the one hand you're maintaining the the
the positive contract between you and
the person who's asking the question but
then you're still sacrificing the truth
within that so you're you're you're
maintaining your relationship with the
higher ordered truth but sacrificing a
lower order truth and and that would be
better than the reverse but it's not as
good as not sacrificing the truth at all
and I would say that if you're maybe
fortunate because sometimes it's a
matter because you can be in a situation
where all your choices are bad I've seen
people in situations like that I've
probably been in situations like that
and maybe that is what's happening in
that story is every choice Abraham is in
front of him is bad but I can't help but
think that it's more than that it means
that
if you're doing the best you can and
it's not perfect it can still be good
enough that's how it looks to
me thank
you hello Dr Peterson uh you mentioned
earlier that there's been a pervasive
problem of nihilism and moral relativism
uh and that that can kind of be cured
with
a less naive optimism that's grounded in
fact and what can actually be done to
improve improv situations is there a way
to communicate that message to a younger
audience say teenagers in a high school
environment which is nowadays a hot bed
for this kind of nihilistic morally
relativist
thinking great I'm glad you asked
that so I'm going to tell you I was
thinking about saying this at the
beginning but I decided not to but now I
get to say it because I got this
question so that's so cool um I I have
plans and
so plan number number
one I have worked with some people to
design a website that will enable High
University students to enter their
course
descriptions their professor's name the
subdiscipline and the university and an
artificial intelligence agent will tell
them if the course is postmodern Neo
Marxist
indoctrination not not only and I have
made tentative Arrangements
with someone to finance a advertising
campaign for that site and so the goal
is well to inform the consumer do you
want to be educated or do you want to be
indoctrinated and happily you'll be able
to use the site equally for both
purposes right because if you want to if
you want to take the the the courses
that I would regard as indoctrination
then this will give you a way of
ensuring that nothing that you get
exposed to won't be of that sort so and
then I'm going to make a video to
introduce that to University students
and their parents and I'm going to
outline what I think the universities
are doing wrong there's about 20 things
they're doing wrong and and they're
seriously wrong things and I'm going to
start by describing the utility of a
university education a Humanities
education because hum's education makes
you into the kind of autonomous
individual that can go away from that
can be independent and can communicate
and think and that has immense economic
value right not not just spiritual value
and cultural value but economic value
and so there's I don't want to tell
people not to go to university I want to
tell them to go to university and grow
the hell up and and learn to communicate
and think and I want them to avoid the
people who will take the spirit away
from them and so that's what that
website is going to do I hope and the
goal is to drop the enrollment in the
indoctrination courses across the
English-speaking World by 75% within 5
years that's the
goal
so and then you asked that you asked
more specifically about high school
students well we have this future
authoring program that has been used for
University students and it produces
about a 30% Improvement in retention and
we've tested several thousand University
students anyone can use it by the way
it's not for University students but it
was easy for us to test its beneficial
impact even if people only spend under
90 minutes on it it's still has
approximately that effect especially on
young
men especially if they're ethnic
minorities especially if they're not
oriented towards a career and didn't do
very well in school and so that's really
cool because it's really hard to design
a psychological intervention that helps
the people who are doing the worst most
psychological interventions so imagine
there are people who are doing not so
well and people who are doing well and
you produce a psychological intervention
what usually happens is the people who
are doing well benefit even more right
but this seems to work for the
disenfranchised so we're thrilled about
that really and so we've produced a ver
version for high school students yes and
so but we don't have them look three to
five years out into the future because
they can't and they don't know enough
you know it's hard for f full fully
mature adults to look that far into into
the future high school kids can probably
manage 3 to six months and so we're
going to have them concentrate on
character development and and what they
want for their from their friendships
and how they would like to orient
themselves in school and to start
thinking about the sorts of person that
they would like to be and that never
happens in schools weirdly enough
there's a guy named John Gat who won the
teacher of the year award in New York
City and then in New York state and then
stopped being a teacher by the way um he
wrote a series of books about the
education system that explain why
students in
pre-university education aren't taught
to be autonomous individuals it's very
interesting what he's discovered
historically but anyways we're going to
Market that probably to parents and to
University students themselves rather
than to the schools because our
experience has been that producing this
sort of material directly for
individuals works much better it's much
more efficient and so then students will
be able to or or their parents will be
able to purchase the program and the
students will be able to use it to
design their own personality in a manner
that would make them thrilled to be
alive let's say that would be the goal
right that would be amazing see
[Applause]
yes I question
I'm I'm going to get you to turn it to
put it down a little more even excellent
perfect
yes
yesl yeah and I I think um especially
the literature and developmental
psychology I think Bears this out but um
I think a huge part of learning is
interaction and discourse and that seems
very difficult in an online setting um
even if it's through text I don't I
don't quite see it as the same thing and
additionally I think there's a huge
motivational Factor that's uh difficult
to um it's difficult to keep motivated
when you're isolated and nobody else
around you is pursuing the same goal so
um how would you address those you're
absolutely right on both counts um I
would say that the idea of an online
Humanities University is grandiose and
it may not be possible and the reason
for that is that
and as you're alluding to we actually
don't understand what the university is
we think it's lectures and exams but
it's probably
not it's certainly being together with
people of your own age as you start your
life it's moving away from your
household it's establishing yourself as
a credible intellect right it's it's
picking a new group of peers it's all of
those things and it isn't n clear how
that can be replicated online now the
people that I'm talking to are
sophisticated enough to understand
Marshall mclin's dicum that the medium
is the message and so I think it would
be a mistake to attempt to duplicate the
University online because you
can't but so what we're concentrating on
right now is not so much content but
infrastructure the question is we want
to set up an educ an a system of
education online that will be
autonomously self governing and
self-improving and the content in some
sense we're not so much interested in
the content as we are interested in the
process by which people who generate
good content might be optimally rewarded
and that's what we want to get right and
that's probably a discussion that'll
take a a year or two years to to flesh
out we we started to conceptualize what
the system might look like but but to
your
point it isn't we're not taking lectures
and putting them online although
obviously that's what I'm doing that
that that isn't going to make an online
Humanities University and we know that I
think everything you said is exact is is
very accurate and also indicative of the
high probability that something like
this would fail so but you know we're
we're we're going to try to be aware of
the pitfalls we're also going to I read
this great book I would recommend this
book it's it's a very funny book by a
guy named John Gaul it's called
systemantics and it's a cult class
classic systematics and it's about how
systems really work and how they fail
and it's a work of ironic comedy but
it's quite brilliant and one of the
things one line he it's it's made of a
bunch of axioms and here's one Axiom I
just love this is the system does not do
what its name says it does and so what I
worked in Alberta Social Services when I
was a kid about 18 or so and I worked as
a consultant and I I one of the and and
I I got involved in projects that were
above my pay grade I would say and I
learned a lot about how how large
bureaucracies functioned and I was asked
at one point to update a report that had
been made the year before about what
percentage of the spending of the social
services department actually went to the
recipients of welfare and and social Aid
in general and the answer was the system
did not know and could not find out and
they had hired a very expensive
consulting firm to answer that question
the year before and I was asked update
it which was quite odd to begin with but
then I did I went and looked at the
Consulting report and I went into the
data and what I found was that none of
it was real but even more importantly
there was no way of knowing whether it
was true or false because the system had
never been set up to calculate what
percentage of its total spending
actually went to the recipients of
social Aid it just blew me away and then
I thought and I was reading this book at
the same time and I thought oh the
purpose of the social services
department is to employ people in the
social services department and I mean I
wasn't being cynical about that it's
like charity most Charities you know
it's like 90% overhead so what does the
charity do it runs itself now you don't
want to be cynical about that because
big businesses are the same and most
like even if they're running at a profit
the profit is like 5% so the business
spends 95% of its time maintaining
itself you know and it makes a bit of
product and it makes a bit of profit but
most of what it does is maintain itself
so anyways one of the axim in that book
that was one of them is the system does
not do what it says it does so that's
because then you can face the system
with a clear head and say okay well this
thing isn't doing what it says it's
doing but it's probably doing something
and the thing it's doing might be useful
but we should figure out what that thing
is so that's been really useful to me as
a guide to thinking the other thing he
said was if you want to build a big
system that works start with by building
a small system that works and scale it
and we've done that for example with the
self-authoring programs has built small
scale systems that are very robust with
the hope that they'll scale and that's
the same we'll do the same thing here is
start with a small amount of content see
if we can reward see what I would like
to have happen is you know there's a lot
of people out there who are pretty
intensely educated and some of them are
really creative and so imagine that
there's a timeline imagine you could we
do a Humanities issue imagine there's a
timeline say of a thousand years that's
scalable then imagine that that there
would be lectures associated with the
timeline at different levels of
resolution so we might call for a
lecture on uh this the third Century a
ad what happened in the 3D Century ad
you've got half an hour to explain it
you can explain it any way you want you
can use animation you can use lecture
you can use text you can make a movie we
don't care what you have to do is that's
the topic that's the time span that's
the amount of time and then you can post
it and so we could generate content that
way and let people experiment and then
we can have people review the content as
part of their education generate
questions about the content as part of
their assignments rate the questions as
part of their assignments and rate the
content and then if we charge people
imagine you had to pay $50 a month to
enroll something like that maybe we
would allow you when you first enroll
maybe you get to use $5 of it as
disposable income you can reward that to
any Creator you want but as you progress
through the courses your right to
determine where your money goes would
increase as you became more and more
educated hopefully that way we would get
some quality control built into it so
those are some of the ideas that we're
that we're starting to play around with
so the only one I'm consider about is
the motivation what's that the
motivation issue for individuals um well
that I'm not going to go into that
because it would take too long but but
rest assured that we are thinking about
that very hard as well we're going to
build competition into it we're going to
build cooperation into it we hope to
build peer inter relationships into it I
think all that's possible but but
complex right because it's we don't know
how to build an online education system
really and but it would be fun to
experiment and see if we can figure out
how to do it so thank you thank
you hi uh so I I couldn't really um zero
in on any particular question so it's
more of a family questions that I have
about the nature and cultivation of
conscience which was in a sense what the
story uh exemplified about Abraham why
why do you say that why do you think
that the story exemplified the
development of cons of conscience spe
specifically well uh going back to the
zigzag yeah right and the star how you
have to keep okay so that's what you
were referring to orienting yourself
completely autonomously on your own
terms right yeah uh to uh okay so you
you hit on something great there I think
you know and this is something weirdly
enough that I learned most particularly
from the Pinocchio movie which I spent a
lot of time studying is because in in
the Pinocchio movie Jiminy Cricut is an
avatar of Christ essentially but it's
very strange because he's a bug that's
the first thing that's kind of weird and
because Jiminy cricet is Southern us
slang for Jesus Christ among other
things but and and these things get
aggregated in in in great Mythic dramas
like that and that's a great Mythic
drama but you know one of the things
that really makes Jiminy cricet
different from Christ apart from the
fact that Christ wasn't a cricket is
that the cricket learns as he progresses
right even though he's the conscience
and so you'd think that he would be the
infallible guide that isn't how the
movie makers set it up and that's so
cool is that he's just as muddle-headed
as Pinocchio at the beginning and he's a
bit arrogant and puffed up too and so
took me a long time to think that
through and then I realized that well
you you have the voice of you have the
voice of culture in you you have the
voice of culture within you but it's old
and dead and out of date and it's not
fully articulated and updated and then
what happens is that if you enter into a
dialogue with it and you Hammer yourself
against the world then you get hammered
into shape and so does your conscience
and so you both become elevated and so
well so anyways I think that's that's
ridiculously cool because means that
your conscience you don't have an
infallible guide but you have something
within you that you could build into an
infallible guide if you cooperated with
it and and fed it so well so I I think
that's very interesting so that being
said uh yeah the picture that I have in
my mind of um uh the cultivation of
virtue in general it's kind of like
taking a a block of wood and trying to
carve out a sphere out of it it'll never
be perfectly round but the more you
carve right the rounder and rounder
right that's successive appro o imation
yeah well one of it's It's also like U
what do you call that compound interest
this is one of the things that's also
and I think this puts you on the to
Those whom more shall be given part of
the curve it's like you know you don't
have to improve yourself very much each
week to really improve yourself on
ridiculous amount in a year you know so
you could make you could you could you
could vow to make your day one 100th of
a per better than the day before and
that would do the trick if you were if
you were constant about that that would
do the trick so that that's this success
of approximation is you you don't want
to underestimate the utility of
incremental progress man it's really
it's deadly powerful so so so let's say
you get to the um you know the higher
ends of the curve right you're like a
pretty virtuous person um let's say you
even become a sage or something of the
sort and
I
mean when should you doubt your
conscience like what are things that we
should watch out for even when we that's
great well that's yep okay um Ju Just to
get it out of the way right yeah um I
don't know how much this relates well it
does relate but Psychopaths for example
the entire idea that they lack a
conscience and that's why right that's
what psychopathy is um whether or not
you agree with that def definition right
but there's an issue of conscience again
at play with psychopathy um how can
we the first question uh doubt ourselves
in a way that's warranted right
regardless of how virtuous we've become
yes
and can you treat a psychopath could
they cultivate a conscience okay so let
we'll start with the first one part of
the reason that that I believe that
freedom of speech is the canonical
right let's and obligation right more
importantly even obligation is that
that's how you figure out if you're
wrong you know because so I sit home and
I think and I think and I think let's
say but I'm like who am I to think
there's so many things I don't know that
it's it's just there's the what I know
compared to what I don't know is
so
minuscule that it's a Preposterous act
just to say something
okay so so no matter how much I sit at
home and think I'm not going to fix that
I'm going to be full and then I have
biases but my temperament and I have
biases because of my malevolence and I
have biases because of my my gender my
sex let's say since we're not so fond of
that word
um so IFA no matter how much I sit home
and think I'm still going to be wrong
and
malevolent so then what I have to do is
I have to talk to some other people and
I have to
say this is what I
think and it's going to be ugly you know
because what the hell do I know but then
if I
listen people will tell me why I'm wrong
and lots of people have been telling me
why I'm wrong like a lot and it's hard
you know it's hard but it's but I've
learned something from it like I I had
this Revelation let's say about being
yelled at by your father now I know that
you can be yelled at too much by your
father but it's like you're wrong man
and so someone's yelling at you and
maybe they're only 10% right but if you
shut the hell up and listen then you can
figure out where you're wrong and then
maybe you can be thankful for that and
then maybe if you shut up and listened
your father would quit yelling at you
you know because he's wrong too what the
hell does he know he knows how to yell
at you and tell you how you're wrong and
he's throwing things out you at you that
are probably not true
but some of it's
true and you know if someone can tell
you why you're wrong they've given you a
great gift because then you don't have
to be wrong anymore and you might think
well who cares if you're wrong but you
know there's a line in the New Testament
too is if the blind lead the blind won't
they fall in won't they fall into a
ditch the answer to that question by the
way is yes they will and so the reason
that you want to think is because
thinking is how
you like when you think you create a
a fictional world that's that's an
analog of the world and then you make an
avatar of yourself to act in that world
and then if the Avatar dies you don't
act out those actions right well so if
you think properly then you don't have
to suffer and die and so if you can say
what you think and people can tell you
why you're wrong and you know to say
what you think under extreme
circumstances means that you're going to
say things that no one wants to hear
because those are the things you don't
know about those are the things that are
conflictual and difficult
those are going to be hard conversations
man and you're going to be wrong about
them a lot if you don't get to stumble
forward with your
stupidity then you can't be corrected
and so so there's no distinction between
free speech and thinking and there's no
distinction between thinking and
thriving and so those who want to
inhibit Free Speech do not wish for
people to thrive and I believe that
so thinking does not happen in inside
your head that's only the beginnings of
thinking and it's this that we're doing
here that's thinking you know so we have
to protect that
Psychopaths I
don't I say this I hope non-
naively also having dealt with
psychopaths in my clinical practice and
I would say now and then in my life I
don't believe in
Psychopaths I don't believe that we know
enough to say there are people born
without
conscience um I don't think the
psychometric measurement of psychopathy
is everything that it should be I've
been trying to model it B in the big
five domain I think now it's complicated
because so I would say a psychopath a
classic psychopath is likely extroverted
especially assertive disagreeable and
unconscientious and maybe extremely low
in neuroticism so you can't frighten
them but so that's a rare combination
because it's extreme many traits right
but that I don't believe that that means
that someone with that personality
configuration is doomed from birth to a
pathological existence because there's
things about psychopathy that that the
that the classifiers those who claim
like clly that the psychopath is born in
some sense can't explain it's like well
what about the
cruelty there seems to be a motive there
you know they're passionless and they
lack no they lack emotion well
why are they cruel then for
entertainment well but then you have to
explain the entertainment motivation
like there's a failure in some sense
with the classic psychopathy theorist to
come to grips with the problem of
malevolence it's skirted over and you
can't do that if you're talking about
psychopathy it's like malevolence is the
bloody issue here and
so the other issue with the psychopath
is that he's irredeemable right that's
the idea
I don't think we know enough to make
such claims now and that doesn't I know
the psychopathy literature quite well
and I have great respect for the primary
researchers in the field I want to make
that perfectly clear but we're talking
at a different we're talking we're
approaching the problem from a different
level of analysis here something like a
spiritual level of analysis and I don't
think that there's an easy easy
translation from the descriptive
psychometric psychiatric approach to the
spiritual level they don't match and I'm
more likely to say let's not assume the
soul is doomed from birth right and I'm
I'm loathed to think that there are
people born
irredeemable although I do think there
are irredeemable people you know the the
death penalty issue is interesting in
that regard you know because I've read a
lot about really terrible people and
I've also read a lot about what really
terrible people said about themselves
and many of them wished for the death
penalty and so it's absolutely clear
that there are things that you can do
that deserve the death
penalty but that doesn't mean that the
state should have the right to impose it
that's a different question
so
yeah in the previous lecture you
mentioned the 2008 economic crisis and
one of the very interesting themes
that's emerged at many levels be it
universities or economic policies this
perceived culture War specifically the
the idea of Marx versus Mill and you've
criticized postmodern and Neo Marxist
thought very frequently one interesting
critic of uh the policies of the EU
specifically EC ECB and IMF during the
Greek debt crisis was Janis vakas the
former Greek Finance Minister and his
criticism of Mill was the was Mill's
alleged contempt for the population and
vaca's comments on the type of
capitalism that results in too big to
fail he describes himself as an erratic
Marxist to me personally he's an example
of someone whose position on the
philosophical moing of policy is
interesting to compare and contrast with
yours he's certainly not your typical
Marxist or postmodernist even though I'm
not really sure what that means but if
you look at his work during the Greek
debt crisis and his current work with
dm25 he seems to be well reasoned well
positioned and and and articulate now I
wanted to know if you had an opinion on
that type of criticism of Mill or his
taking of a position as an erratic
Marxist okay I would say I would say no
to the specifics of of the question I
don't think that I have the detailed
expertise in order to answer the
question at the level of analysis that
you where you formulated it but I I have
something to say that's more General
about the set of phenomena that you
described there's no doubt that
distribution is a major problem that
capitalism contends with imperfectly at
best and the distribution problem is the
predo distribution problem right and and
something that Marx commented on which
mostly in the monetary sphere is that
money tends to accumulate in the hands
of very few people it's like there's no
doubt about that now as we've discussed
before the people in whom hands the
money accumulates do turn over more than
people say think especially in in in
countries that are functioning
reasonably well and it's really
important that that
happens yes yes yes but that
doesn't that doesn't solve the problem
of the fact that produced Goods
gravitate towards an extreme minority
now they're also produced Often by
extreme minority which is also a problem
um I would
say then that the idea that capitalism
is more prone
to that distribution problem than any
other system I don't believe that to
have been demonstrated at all and I
think that capitalism is actually pretty
good at self-destruction except when
that's interfered with and I think
that's particularly the case in the
United States where generally the policy
has been if you're an idol with feet of
clay no matter how big you are you get
to fail now that's been compromised
severely in the last 20
years and we're probably going to pay
for that I think they really paid for
that in Japan right where there was
every attempt to prop out the the gods
that should have died
so so fair enough for the critique of
capitalism that's not the issue the
issue is do you have a better idea and
if the idea is well we could kind of do
what Mark suggested then you don't get
to have that position
and
claim what should I
say I haven't seen any evidence that
systems predicated on that set of axioms
have done anything but more harm than
good thank you yeah and when will you be
announcing the monthly extension to this
lecture series as soon as I find out
whether or not I can rent this theater
in the
fall
yeah thank you we'll see you next week
[Applause]