[Music]
hello everyone so hopefully we're going
to get past Genesis 1 today that's the
theory so I finished my new book
yesterday
[Applause]
yes that's that's taken about three
years of writing it's quite a long time
to write something so yeah it's done
except for the mopping up you know copy
editing and that sort of thing so
hopefully it's as good as I can make it
I don't know if that's any good but it's
as good as I can make it anyways all
right so this is the stories that I'm
gonna tell you tonight I've been
thinking about well like the ones last
week for that matter for a very long
period of time but I think these even
longer and one of the things that I just
do not understand I cannot fathom this I
I cannot understand how there can be so
much information in such tiny little
stories especially the story of Cain and
Abel that story just every time I read
it it just flattens me because it it's
only like a paragraph long there's just
nothing to it you know and I think about
it I think about it and I think about it
I think about it and every time I think
about it another layer comes out from
underneath and then another layer comes
out for underneath it and I can't figure
that out like you know the rational
approach that I've been describing to
you is predicated on the idea that these
stories have somehow encapsulated wisdom
that we generated interpersonally and
behaviorally and that an image over very
vast stretches of time and then
condensed it into very very dense
articulated words that are then further
refined by the act of being remembered
and transmitted and remembered and
transmitted and remembered and
transmitted over vast stretches of time
and that's a pretty good argument I'm
willing to I'm willing to go with it but
it still never ceases to amaze me how
much information such tiny little
passages can can contain so we'll take
that apart today and I think it's
especially true with the story of Cain
and Abel because it it works on the
individual level and it works on the
familial level and it works on the
political level and it works at the
level of warfare and it works at the
level of economics and
it's that's a lot for a little tiny
one-paragraph story to cover man now you
know you could object well with these
stories you never know what you're
reading into it and what's in the story
right that's part of let's call it the
postmodern dilemma and and fair enough
and there's really no answer to that any
more than there is an answer to how do
you know your interpretation of the
world is well let's not say correct but
sufficient there's some answer to that
it's it's sufficient in if you can act
it out in the world and other people
don't object too much and you don't die
and nature doesn't take a bite out of
you any more often than necessary you
know those are the constraints within
which we live so it you have some way of
determining whether your interpretation
is at least functionally successful and
that's and that's not trivial and I
guess you can say the same thing to the
interpretations that might be laid out
on these stories and at the moment
that's probably good enough hopefully
you find the interpretations
functionally significant at multiple
levels and I also think the chance of
managing that by chance is very very
small you know to be able to pull off an
interpretation of a story that works at
multiple levels simultaneously you think
with each level that it applies the
chances that you've stumbled across
something by chance have to be
decreasing right that there's a
technical term for that in psychology
it's called something like multi method
multi trait method of determining
whether or not something is accurate and
the idea is them the more ways that you
can measure it and get the same result
the more confident you can be that
you're not just deluding yourself with
your a priori hypothesis you know that
there's actually something out there so
I guess that's another part of this
method is that and it's also a method
that I use in my in my speaking I think
I don't try to tell people anything that
isn't personally relevant you know
because you should know why you are
being taught something right you should
know what the fact is good for and then
it should be good for you personally at
least in some sense and then if you act
it out in the world it should be good
for your family and maybe should have
some significance for the broader
community and I think that's what
meaning means and I don't really see the
utility in being taught things that
aren't meaningful facts that aren't
meaningful because
there's an infinite number of facts and
there's no way you're going to remember
all of them they have to be they have to
have the aspect of tools essentially
something like that because we are tool
using creatures while these these
stories have that aspect is as far as I
can tell there's nothing there's no
doubt about that so here's the stories
in Genesis two very famous stories
obviously virtually everybody who's even
vaguely versed in Western roughly
speaking Western Western culture knows
these stories and that's something
that's interesting too that stories can
be so foundational that everybody shares
them I mean you can say the same thing
about a fairly large handful of fairy
tales as well or you could at least
until recently but the fact that stories
are foundational I think also means that
they have to be given a kind of well
even if you don't give them any respect
you have to at least treat them as
remarkable curiosities
so why those stories and why did they
stick around and why does everybody know
them and it's not self-evident by any
stretch of the imagination and you can
use explanations can use the Freudian
explanation Freud sort of thought that
the judeo-christian was predicated on
the idea that the figure of the father
the familial father was expanded up into
cosmic dimensions so that mankind
existed in the same relationship to the
cosmic father let's say that an infant
or a small child existed in relationship
to his or her own father and that's a
reasonable critique I would say to some
degree but it does and and and this was
purposeful it does imply more than imply
and for its case that people who adopt
religious belief that has a personified
figure as at its apex are essentially
acting out the role of dependent
children and you know I thought about
that critique for a long time and
believe me that's been a powerful
critique one of the best books I've ever
read called the denial of death by
Ernest Becker I think took that line of
argumentation it developed it as well as
any
any book I've ever seen argue it
Becker tried to bring closure to
Freudian psychoanalysis on religion he
did a pretty wicked job of it like I
think the book is seriously flawed and
wrong but it's really a great book like
some books are well some books are wrong
in really good ways right they make a
powerful powerful argument they really
take it to its extreme
I think Becker missed the point and he
missed it in the same way that Freud
missed Jung's point and Becker who wrote
this book on the psychology the
psychoanalysis of religion never
referred to Jung except very briefly in
the introduction and I think that was a
major mistake but Becker took the
argument that the hypothesis of God is
nothing but an attempt by human beings
to recreate quasi infantile state of
dependency and to be able to rely on an
all-knowing father and to thereby
recover the comfort perhaps that we
experienced when we were young and had a
hypothetically all-knowing father for
those of us who were lucky to have
someone who rigged vaguely resembled
that but the more I thought about that
the more that struck me is quite
implausible across time Charles Taylor I
think it was Charles Taylor wrote an
interesting book called the I think it
was called the origins of the modern
self
he's a megillah' philosopher and I
wouldn't necessarily call him a friend
of classic religion but it doesn't
matter he made a very interesting point
about Christianity in particular he said
well if you're going to invent a
religion that offered you nothing but
infantile comfort why in the world would
you bother with conceptualizing hell
that just seems like an unnecessary
detail to add to the whole story right
if it's it's all about comfort why would
you hypothesize that the consequence of
of serious error was eternal torment
that doesn't really sound very it isn't
the sort of thing that that is likely to
make you feel comfortable James Joyce
when he wrote about that said he had
terrible nightmares when he was a child
because of the Hellfire sermons that
Jesuits used to
spew forth let's say and he wrote down
what he remembered of them and they were
pretty hair-raising I think in James
Joyce's book I think it was portrait of
the artist of a young man man he talked
about the Jesuits telling them and
telling him that hell was a like a
prison with walls that were seven miles
thick that was always in darkness and
consumed by fire and that the people who
were trapped there were continually
burnt by this dark fire that gave new
light which also simultaneously
rejuvenated their flesh so that it could
be burnt off eternally in case you were
wondering how it was going to be burned
off eternally that's apparently the
process it's not easy for me to see that
as an infantile wish-fulfillment
I'm afraid now you could well you could
be a cynic about it and Elaine Pagels
who wrote a book on the devil was
cynical about it in this manner she
thought that the Christians so to speak
invented hell as a place to put their
enemies and you know yeah fair enough
but no that's not accurate really well
although it's convenient to have a place
to put your enemies Charles Taylor did
point out for example that the modern
terror of loss of self let's say the
existential loss of self and loss of
meaning was perhaps roughly paralleled
by the medieval terror of Hell you know
in terms of existential intensity and so
it wasn't hell wasn't merely a place
where those people that you didn't care
for would end up it was the place where
you were going to go if he didn't walk
the line properly and so I don't think
Freud's Freud's critique really holds
water in the final analysis and then
Marx's critique of course was that
religion was the opiate of the masses
and he made an argument that was similar
to Freud's although somewhat earlier and
made the based upon the presupposition
that religious beliefs were stories told
to the gullible masses in order to keep
them pacified and happy well their
corporate overlords for lack of a better
purpose continue to exploit them and and
and weaken them and you know I find that
I find the critique of human
institutions as driven entirely by power
very let's say questionable to
to say the least and of course every
human institution is corrupted by
corrupted is corrupt by for one reason
or another and it's also corrupt
specifically by such things as deception
and arrogance and and the demand for
unearned power and the same thing of
course can be applied to religious
systems but that doesn't mean that they
are in some special way characteristic
of those false and maybe you think they
are and you know maybe you can make a
case for it but it's not prime FSA I
think that's how you say that evident
that that is that also is a particularly
useful criticism I don't buy it
I think there's I think that's far too
cynical I think that the people who
wrote these stories first of all what
are you gonna do you cannot really
you're gonna run a bloody conspiracy for
three thousand years successfully it's
like good luck with that
can't run a conspiracy for fifteen
minutes without somebody ratting you out
you know it's it's impossible so
whatever's at the basis of the
construction not only of these stories
but of the dogmatic structures that
emerged from them I think that it's a
terrible mistake to reduce them to you
know dimensional explanations in fact I
generally think that reducing any
complex human behavior to yoona
dimensional explanation is often the
sign of a seriously limited thinker and
you know I say that with some caution
because Freud did do that with religion
at least to some degree and so it was a
serious thinker and Marx I suppose was a
serious thing or two even though well
yeah is he someone you just if you have
any sense marks just leaves you
speechless so so anyway so that's all to
say that I don't think there's any
simple explanation for how these stories
have the power that they have I I really
don't I don't think you can reduce it to
political conspiracy that's for sure I
don't think you can reduce it to
psychological infantilism I think you
can make a case like I have that they
are repositories of the collective
wisdom of the human race I had an
interesting letter this week from
someone I get a lot of interesting
letters I think I'm going to make an
archive out of them and put them on the
web at some point with people's
permission obviously and he said that
he'd been following my lectures and
noted that I had been making what you
might describe as a quasi biological or
evolutionary case for for the emergence
of the information that the stories
contained and he said well how do you
know that someone from a different
religious tradition or speaking of a
different religious tradition couldn't
do exactly the same thing and I thought
well first of all to some degree they
could because there is overlap like I've
talked to you a little bit about Taoism
for example in the Taoist view of being
as you know the eternal balance between
chaos and order one thing I didn't tell
you I don't think about that and I don't
know if you know this but there's a
neuropsychologist named Al Conan
Goldberg who was a student of Alexander
Luria and Luria was I think the greatest
neuropsychologist of the 20th century he
was a Russian and he was one of the
first people to really determine in
large part the function of the frontal
cortex which was quite a mystery for a
very long period of time and Goldberg
you know you know how we have two
hemispheres right we have a left
hemisphere and a right hemisphere and
people often think of the left for
right-handed people
right-handed males more particularly
because women are more neurologically
diffuse it's one of the things that
makes them more robust to head injury
for example and maybe men are less
defuses somewhat more specialized which
makes them a bit more specialized but a
little more subject to damage anyways we
have two hemispheres left
the right and no one exactly knows why
and we know that they how is quasi
independent consciousness is because if
you divide the corpus callosum that that
unites them which was done to in cases
of intractable epilepsy for example that
each hemisphere is capable of developing
its own consciousness to some degree the
right generally nonverbal and the left
verbal and so there has been this idea
that the left is a verbal Hemisphere and
the right is a nonverbal hemisphere
but that can't be right because of
course animals don't talk and they have
a bifurcated hemisphere so if it's right
it's not causally right now goldberg
hypothesized instead that the
hemispheres were were specialized for
routinization and non routinization or
for novelty and familiarity or for chaos
and order and so that's pretty damn cool
when i ran across that i also thought
about that as a as a signal of what
would you call it Multi method multi
trait construct validation because I'd
never thought of the hemispheres as
operating that way and Goldberg came up
with this in a in a historical pathway
that was entirely independent from any
mythologically inspired thinking
completely independent in fact it was
motivated more by materialist Russian
neuro psychology which was materialist
for political reasons and also for
scientific reasons but the idea is that
we have one hemisphere that reacts very
rapidly to things we don't know and it's
more imaginative and diffuse in it and
it's associated more with negative
emotion because negative emotion is what
you should feel immediately when you
encounter something you don't understand
because it's a form of thinking right
negative emotion it's like I'm somewhere
where things aren't with what they
should be right hemisphere does that
generates images very rapidly to help
you figure out what might be there and
then the left hemisphere takes that and
develops it into something that's more
articulated and and algorithmic and
fully understood and so then there's
this dynamic balance between the right
and the left hemisphere where the left
tries to impose order on the world
that's Ramachandran who's a neurologist
in in california very famous neuro
neuro neurologist who also developed a
theory like goldberg who said that the
left hemisphere
imposes routinized order on the world
and the right hemisphere generates
novelty and and and reacts to novelty
and generates novel hypotheses and he
thought and there is some good evidence
for this that's what's happening during
the dream is that information is moved
from the right hemisphere to the left
hemisphere in small doses basically so
that the novel revelations of the right
hemisphere don't demolish the
algorithmic structures that the left
hemisphere has so carefully put together
so and I like that theory too because it
also does help justify the hypothesis
that I'd be laying out for you which is
that you know there's part of us that
extends ourselves out into the world
interest to understand what we don't
know and that that part extends itself
out with behavior and also with emotion
and also with image and then maybe with
poetry and then maybe with storytelling
and then as that develops then we
develop more and more articulated
representations of that emergent
knowledge and so you can map that quite
nicely onto the neurologists and the
neuropsychologists presumption about
what constitutes the reason for the
hemispheric differentiation but the
other thing that's so cool about the
hemispheric differentiation argument as
far as I'm concerned and this is really
this is worth thinking about man because
it's a real it's a real there's a word
that Ned's Ned Flanders uses for that
Norgan scratcher I think it's something
like that anyways you know we do make
the assumption that what it is that we
are biologically adapted to is reality
right it's actually an axiomatic
definition if you're a Darwinian because
nature is what selects by definition
that's what nature is its what selects
and if the nature that selects has
forced upon you a dual hemispheric
structure because half of you has to
deal with the chaos and half the half of
you has to deal with order then you can
make a pretty damn strong inferential
case that the world is made out of chaos
and order and that's really something to
that's really something to think about
man you know so you can think about that
for a while if you want
so anyways for whatever reason there is
a lot too packed into these stories and
so let's investigate a couple more of
them we'll start with this story by of
Adam and Eve now you may remember that
the Bible is a series of books Bible
actually means something akin to library
and these books were written by all
sorts of different people and groups of
people and groups of editors and groups
of people who edited over and over
across very very large periods of time
so they're offered by no one and many at
the same time the there was a tradition
for a long time that the earliest books
were written by Moses but that that's
probably not technically correct even
though it might be dramatically correct
let's say or correct in the way that a
fairy tale is correct and I'm I'm not
trying to put down fairy tales by saying
that but there's a number of authors and
the way the authors have been identified
tentatively is by certain stylistic
commonalities across the different
stories different uses of words like the
words for God different poetic styles
different topics and so forth and people
have been working for probably 200 years
roughly that to try to sort out who
wrote what and how that was all cobble
together but it doesn't really matter
for our purposes what matters is that
it's an aggregation of collected
narrative traditions and maybe you could
say it's an aggregation of collective
narrative wisdom we don't have to go
that far but we can at least say it's
aggregated narrative traditions and that
there was some reason that those
traditions and all others were kept and
that there was some reasons complex
though they may have been why they were
sequenced in the order that they were
sequenced because one of the things
that's really remarkable about the Bible
as an as a document is that it actually
has a plot and that's really something I
mean it's it's sprawling and it goes
many places but the fact that
something's being cobbled together over
several thousand years maybe four
thousand years maybe longer than that if
you include the oral traditions that
preceded it and god only knows how old
those are that that collective
imagination part of the human collective
imagination has cobble together a
library with a plot and like I see the
Bible as an attempt a collective attempt
by hee
you solve the deepest problems that we
have and I think those problems are the
problems of primarily that the problem
of self-consciousness the fact that not
only do we are immortal and that we die
but that we know it and that's the
unique that's the unique predicament of
human beings and it makes all the
difference and I think that's laid out
in Adam and Eve in the story of Adam and
Eve I think the reason that that makes
us unique and is laid out in that story
and interestingly and I really realized
this only after I was doing the last
three lectures so the Bible presents a
cataclysm and okay a Cataclysm at the
beginning of the top of Time which is
the emergence of self-consciousness and
human beings which puts a rift into the
structure of being that's the right way
to think about it and that's really
given cosmic significance now you can
dispense with out and say well nothing
that happens to human beings does have
caused me significance because we're
these short-lived you know mold like
entities that are like cancers on this
tiny little planet that's rotating out
in the middle of nowhere on the edge of
some unknown galaxy in the middle of
infinite space and nothing that happens
to us matters and it's fine you like you
can walk down that road if you want I
wouldn't recommend it I mean and that's
part of the reason I think that for all
intents and purposes it's untrue you
know it isn't it isn't a road you can
walk down and live well in fact I think
if you really walk down that road and
you really take it seriously you end up
not living at all so it's certainly very
reminiscent I mean I've talked to lots
of people who were suicidal and
seriously suicidal and you know the kind
of conclusions that they draw both the
utility of life prior to wishing for its
cessation are very much like the kind of
conclusions that you draw if you walk
down that particular line of reasoning
long enough if you're interested in that
you could read Tolstoy his confessions
Leo Tolstoy's confession it's a very
short book it's a it's a killer man it's
it's a powerful book very very short and
Tolstoy describes his obsession with
suicide when he was at the height of his
fame most well-known author in the world
you know huge family international fame
wealth beyond anyone's imagining at that
time influential admired he
everything that you could possibly
imagine that everyone could have and for
years he was afraid to go out into his
barn with a rope or a gun because he
thought he'd either hang himself or
shoot himself and he did get out of that
he and he describes why that happened
and where he went when that happened so
if you're interested in that that's a
very good book but so the biblical
stories and starting with Adam and Eve
they present a different story
they present the emergence of
self-consciousness in human beings as
cosmically cataclysmic event and you
could say well what do we have to do
with the cosmos and the answer to that
is it depends on what you think
consciousness has to do with the cosmos
and perhaps that's nothing and perhaps
it's everything I'm going to go with
everything because that's how it looks
to me now of course anyone who wishes to
is welcome to disagree but if you
believe that consciousness is a force of
cosmic significance which Britt which
which being itself is dependent on in
any real sense at least in any
experience will sense that it's that
it's not unreasonable to assume that
radical restructurings of consciousness
can worthily be granted some kind of
cosmic or metaphysical significance and
even if it's not true from outside the
human perspective whatever that might be
it's bloody well true from within the
human perspective that's for sure and so
that's the that's the initial event in
some sense after the creation is the
cataclysmic fall and then the entire
rest of the Bible is an attempt to
figure out what the hell to do about
that and everything in it is is and so
you could say for example in the
earliest in the Old Testament stories
what seems to happen is that the State
of Israel is is founded and it rises and
falls and rises and falls and so there's
this experimentation for centuries
millennia even with the idea that the
way that you protect yourself against
the tragic consequences of self
consciousness is by organizing yourself
into a state but then what happens is
the state itself begins to reveal its
pathologies and as those pathologies
mount the state becomes an unstable and
collapses and then it rises back up and
becomes unstable and collapses and then
it rises back up after it does this a
number of
times.this is primarily from Northrup
fries interpretations people start
wondering if there's not something wrong
with the idea that the state itself is
this is the is the pathway is the place
of redemption that there's something
wrong with that idea and so then I think
on on the heels of that comes the
Christian revolution with its hypothesis
that it's not the state that's that's
the place of salvation it's the
individual psyche and then there's
there's a there's a an ethic that goes
along with that too which is quite
interesting so the ethic of redemption
after the state experiment fails let's
say is that it's it's the it's within
the individual that Redemption can be
manifested let's say and even insofar as
the state is concerned because the
state's proper functioning is dependent
on the proper functioning of the
individual rather than the reverse most
fundamentally and that the proper mode
of individual being that's redemptive is
truth and truth is the antidote to the
suffering that's that emerges with the
fall of man in the story of Adam and Eve
and then that relates back to the
chapters that we've already talked about
because there's this insistence in
Genesis 1 that it's the word in the form
of the of truth that generates order out
of chaos but even more importantly and
this is something like I said I most
clearly realize just doing these
lectures for the last three weeks is God
continues to say as he speaks order into
being with truth that the being he
speaks into being is good and so there's
this insistence that the being that
spoke into being through truth is good
and so there's a hint there it's so
interesting there's a hint there right
at the beginning of the story that the
the state of being that Adam and Eve
inhabited before they fell before they
became self consciousness conscious
insofar as they were made in the image
of God and acting out the truth that
that being itself was properly balanced
and it takes the entire Bible to
rediscover that which is a which is a
journey back to the beginning right and
that's a classic theme
it's a classic mythological theme that
the wise person is the person who finds
what they lost in childhood and regains
it right so that's a I think that's a
Jewish idea this is addict if I remember
correctly who is a messiah figure is the
person who finds what he lost in
childhood and regains it his idea of
this return to the beginning except that
the return is you don't fall backwards
into childhood and unconsciousness you
returned voluntarily to the state of
childhood
well awake and then determined to
participate through truth in the
manifestation of proper being now you
know I'm a psychologist and I've taught
personality theory for a very long time
and I know personality theory is that
profound personality theory is pretty
well and I'm reasonably well versed in
philosophy although not as well-versed
as I should be but I can tell you and
all the things I've ever read or
encountered or thought about I have
never once found an idea that matches
that in terms of profundity but not only
profundity also in believability because
the other thing I see is a clinician and
I think this is a very characteristic of
clinical experience and also very much
described explicitly by the great
clinicians is that what cures in therapy
is truth that's the curative now there's
exposure to the things you're afraid of
and avoiding as well but I would say
that's a form of enacted truth because
if you know there's something you should
do by your own set of rules and you're
avoiding it then you're enacting a lot
you know you're not telling one but
you're acting one out it's the same damn
thing so if I can get you to face what
it is that you're confronting that you
know you shouldn't be avoiding then
what's happening is that we're both
partaking in the process of attempting
you to act out your deepest truth and
what happens is that that improves
people's lives and it improves them
radically and the evidence of the
clinical evidence for that is
overwhelming we know that if you expose
people to the things they're afraid of
but that they're avoiding they get
better and you have to do it carefully
and cautiously and with their own
participation in all of that but of all
the things that clinicians have
established that's credible that's
number one and that's nested inside this
deeper realization that the clinical
experience is redemptive let's say
because it
it's designed to address suffering
insofar as the people who are engaged in
the process are both telling each other
the truth and then you think well
obviously because if if you have some
problems and you come to talk to me
about them well first of all just by
coming to talk to me about them you've
admitted that they exist now and that's
a pretty good start and second well if
you tell me about them then we know what
they are and then if we know what they
are we can maybe start to lay out some
solutions and then you can go act out
the solutions and see if they work but
if you don't admit they're there and you
won't tell me what they are and I don't
and I'm like posturing and and and
acting egotistically and and taking the
upper hand and all of that in our
discussions well how the hell is that
going to work you know it might be
comfortable moment to moment while we
stay encapsulated in our delusion but
it's not going to work so a lot of that
seems if you think it through it seems
pretty self-evident and you know Freud
thought that repression was at the heart
of much mental suffering the difference
between repression and deception is a
matter of degree and that's all its
technical it's a technical
differentiation and Alfred Adler who was
one of Freud's greatest associates say
and much underappreciated I would say he
thought that people got into problems
because they started to act out a life
lie that's what he called it a life lie
that's worth looking up because I have
there although not as charismatic as
Freud was very practical and and and
really foreshadowed a lot of later
developments in cybernetic theory and of
course you believed that you could
bypass psychotherapy entirely by merely
making a proper moral effort in your own
life and Carl Rogers believed that it
was honest communication mediated
through dialogue that had redemptive
consequences and the behaviors believe
that you do a careful micro analysis of
the problems that are laid before you
and help introduce people to what
they're avoiding it's like all of those
things to me are just secular variations
of the notion that truth will set you
free essentially so so you know it's a
pretty powerful story and a it's not
that easy to dispense with and B the
other thing is you dispense with it at
your peril because what I have seen as
well is that the people that I've seen
who've been
have been hurt mostly by deceit and
that's also worth thinking about that
you know you get walloped by life
there's no doubt about that absolutely
no doubt about that but I've thought for
a long time that maybe maybe maybe
people can hang handle earthquakes and
cancer and even death Meany
but they can't handle betrayal and they
can't handle deception they can't handle
having the rug pulled out from
underneath and by people that they love
and trust that just does them in you
know it it it it makes the meal but it
does where it hurts them you know psycho
physiologically it damages them but more
than that it makes them cynical and
bitter and vicious and resentful and
then they also start to act all that out
in the world and that makes it worse so
so you know this story starts god uses
the spoken truth to create being that is
good and then the Cataclysm occurs and
then human beings spend until millennia
trying to sort out exactly what to do
about the fact that they've become self
conscious and you know by the way we
have right we are in fact self conscious
no other animal has that distinction
now you'll read that chimpanzees can for
example if you put lipstick on a
chimpanzee it's kind of a strange thing
to do yeah well I won't pursue that any
further but the chimp a chimpanzee will
wipe off the lipstick if you show it a
mirror and dolphins seem to be able to
recognize themselves in mirrors and
there is so there is the glimmerings of
self conscious recognition and other
animals but to put that in the same
conceptual category as human
self-consciousness is to my way of
thinking it's it's well it's uninformed
to say the least but I also think that
it's motivated it's motivated by a kind
of anti humanistic underlying an
underlying motivation because our
self-consciousness is so incredibly
developed compared to that that they're
hardly in the same conceptual universe
it's it's like comparing the the alarm
cries of
vervet monkeys when they see a predator
to the language of human beings it's
like yeah yeah yeah there's some
similarities man there are other iNSYS
and there are other insisting but
they're not language and the
self-consciousness of animals is proto
self-consciousness and it's only there
in a very small number of animals and
it's it's nothing like ours they're not
aware of the future like we are they're
not aware of their boundaries in space
and time and that's the critical thing
and most particularly time human beings
discovered time and when we discover
time we discovered the end of each of
our being and that made all the
difference and that's what the story of
Adam and Eve is about so genesis ones
derived from the priestly source where
God is known as Elohim or El Shaddai
and there's God in the singular and
there's gods in the plural and I suppose
that's because it seems that if you
analyze the history of the development
of monotheistic ideas that monotheism
emerges out of a plurality of gods and
as I mentioned I think it's because the
gods represent fundamental forces at
minimum and those fundamental forces
have to be hierarchy to be organized for
with some with something absolute at the
top because otherwise they do nothing
but war like you have to organize your
values hierarchically or you stay
confused and that's true if you're an
individual and it it's true if you're a
state if you don't know what the next
thing you should do is then there's 50
things you should do and then how are
you gonna do any of them you can't you
have to prioritize something has to be
above something else it has to be
arranged in a hierarchy for it not to be
chaotic and so there's some principle at
the top of the hierarchy and maybe the
organization of the gods over time
that's the battle of gods that Mircea
Eliade i talked about and if you're
interested in that you could read a
history of religious ideas which I would
really recommend it's a three-volume
book it's actually quite as
straightforward read as far as these
things go and Elliott it does a very
nice job of describing how and even why
polytheism tends towards monotheism even
in polytheistic cultures there's a
strong tendency for the gods to organize
themselves in a hierarchy with one God
at the top in a monotheistic culture and
some in some sense all the other gods
disappear across time and there's
nothing left but the top god but even in
a polytheistic society there's a
hierarchy of power among the gods the
first story is newer than the second one
so the story I'm going to tell you today
is actually older than the one I already
told you even though their order was
flipped by the redactor who's the
hypothetical person or persons who
edited these stories together and we
don't know exactly why he or the
committee or what I suspect it was a
single person but who knows we don't
know why the stories were edited
together in the order that they were
added together but we could infer I mean
they were added together in that order
because the editor thought they made
sense that way because that's what an
editor does right an editor tends to
take diverse ideas and then to organize
them in some manner that makes sense and
part of the manner that makes sense is
that you can tell them to people and the
people stay interested and you can tell
them to people and people remember them
that's that's one of the ways you can
tell if you've got an argument right
because it's communicable and
understandable and memorable and so he
this person was let's say motivated by
intuition to organize the stories in
this particular manner so the second the
yahwist strand contains the stories the
classic stories in the Pentateuch that's
five books Genesis Exodus Leviticus
numbers and Deuteronomy which we'll try
to get through perhaps in these twelve
lectures with Steve we'll see how that
goes it's strongly under for Norfolk so
the God in the August account is for all
intents and purposes a sort of meta
person and I dealt with that a little
bit last week because people tend to you
know think of that as unsophisticated
but when you think that the mind that
the the ground of consciousness is the
most complex thing that we know of then
it's not so unsophisticated to assume
that the most complex thing that there
might be is like that or it's at least
it's as good as we can do with our
imaginations and so I don't think it's
so it's so it's so unsophisticated it's
also the case and this is practically
speaking is that it is not at all
unreasonable to think of God the Father
as the spirit that arises from the cry
that exists into the future right and
that's we talked about that in
relationship to the idea of sacrifice at
least a little bit tomorrow or we're
going to you make sacrifices in the
present so that the future is happy with
you and the question is what is that
future that would be happy with you and
the answer to that is it's the spirit of
humanity that's that's who you're
negotiating with because you make the
assumption that if you forego impulsive
pleasure and get your medical degree
that when you're done in ten years and
you're a physician humanity as such will
honor your sacrifice and commitment and
open the doors to you right so you're
treating the future as if it's a single
being and you're also treating it as if
it's a something like a compassionate
judge you're acting that out and maybe
we had to imagine God in that form
before we could understand once we
started to understand that there was a
future perhaps we had to imagine God in
that form in order to concretize
something that we could bargain with so
that we could figure out how to use
sacrifice to figure out how to guide
ourselves into the future because I
sacrifice as a contract with the future
but it's not a contract with any
particular person it's it's a contract
with the spirit of humanity as such it's
something like that and so when you
think about it that way that should make
you faint with amazement because that is
such a bloody amazing idea to come up
with that idea that you can bargain with
the future that is some idea man
that's that's like the major idea of
human of humankind we suffer what do we
do about it we figure out how to bargain
with the future and we minimize
suffering in that manner it's like no
other animal does that either you know
like the Lions they just eat everything
I think a wolf can eat forty pounds of
meat in a single sitting right it's like
there's some meat eat it it's light not
like save some mammoths for tomorrow
that's a that's that's not a wolf thing
man that's a human thing and that might
mean you have to be hungry today
or maybe you're a farmer you know
several thousand years ago six thousand
years ago or so what agriculture first
got going and you're starving to death
waiting for the spring planting and you
think we bill it bloody well better not
eat those seeds right and that's really
something to be able to control yourself
to make the future real to put off what
you could use today and not just in some
and Paul
of manner man maybe your kids are
starving to death you think we are not
touching the seeds that we need for the
future and for human beings to have
discovered that and then to also have
figured out that we could bargain with
the future it's like man
that's something and I think that that I
think that the stories that are laid out
in this book actually describe at least
in part the process by which that
occurred the always stories begin with
Genesis 2:4 this is the account of the
heavens and the earth wind so there's
two real creation stories at the
beginning the newer one which is the
first one and the older one which is the
second one and the older one begins in
Chapter two and that's the story that
we're going to that we are getting into
now Adam and Eve are in that Cain and
Abel knoweth the Tower of Babel in the
August strand Exodus numbers along and
there's some of the priestly version in
there too as well as the Ten
Commandments well there's some lovely
representations of of paradise this is
Garden of Earthly Delights what's his
name say that oh yes Hieronymous Bosch
he has a crazy I mean if you how he
didn't get burnt at the stake is
absolutely beyond me I mean you know
some of you know about salvador deli i
suppose most of you do I mean delis a
[__] compared to Hieronymous Bosch man
you could spend because there's three
pieces of this particular painting you
could spend a very bizarre and surreal
month looking at that painting I don't
know what it was with Bosch but he was
some sort of creature that only popped
up once and probably for the best and so
there's been very many representations
of paradise maybe god only knows what
that is it's like I could probably guess
but I won't
and then look I mean that's that's
that's the lion lying down with the lamb
right so that's this idea that's it's
maybe projected back in time that there
was a time or maybe will be a time when
when that then the horrors of life are
no longer necessary for life itself to
exist right and the horrors of life are
of course that everything eats
everything else and that everything dies
and that everything's born and that the
whole bloody place is at
Arnel house and it's it's a catastrophe
from beginning to end and this is this
is the vision of it being other than
that and you know there's a strong idea
this is also in implicit in the
alchemical ideas and I think it's also
implicit in the Scientific Revolution
that human beings can interact with
reality in such a way so that the tragic
and evil elements of it can be mitigated
and so that we can move somewhat closer
to a state that might be characterized
that's obviously imagistic but it might
be characterized by something like that
where we have the benefits of actual
existence without all of the catastrophe
that seems to go along with it and Carl
Jung when he wrote about the emergence
of alchemy or the emergence of science
from alchemy he thought of science as
being motivated by a dream because for
Jung dream was the dream was the
manifestation of the instincts it was
the boundary between the instincts and
thinking said well science is nested
inside a dream and the dream is that if
we investigated the structures of
material reality with sufficient
attention and truth that we could then
learn enough about material reality to
alleviate suffering right to produce the
Philosopher's Stone to make everybody
wealthy to make everybody healthy to
make everyone live as long as they
wanted to live for perhaps forever that
that's the goal to alleviate the
catastrophe of existence and that that
idea the idea that mysteries the
solution to the mysteries of life that
might enable us to develop such a
substance or let's say a multitude of
substances provided the motive force for
the development of science and young
trace that the development of that mode
of force really over a thousand years
and if you're interested in reading his
books on alchemy which are
extraordinarily difficult and that's
really saying something about young
because all of his books are difficult
and then the books on alchemy they kind
of take a quantum leap that's actually a
very small leap so I shouldn't say that
they take a massive leap into a whole
different dimension of complexity but
that's what he was trying to get at he
went back into the alchemical texts and
interpreted them as if they were the
dream on which science was founded
Newton was an alchemist by the way I
mean Jung's hypotheses are certainly
well supported by the historical fact
science did emerge out of alchemy the
question is what were the alchemists up
to and they were trying to produce the
Philosopher's Stone and that was the you
know
so medica meant for mankind's pathology
Jung felt that what had happened was
that you know Christianity had promised
that the cessation of suffering promised
it for a thousand years and yet
suffering went on unabated and at the
same time Christianity had attempted to
really put emphasis on spiritual
development let's say at the expense of
material development right thinking of
material development as something akin
to a sin trying to get a control of
impulsivity and and all the things that
went along with a to embodied existence
there was a reason for it but that by
about a thousand AD the European mind
somewhat educated by that point someone
able to concentrate on a single point
perhaps because of a very long history
of intense religious training turned its
dream to the unexplored material world
and thought well you know the spiritual
Redemption that we've been seeking
didn't appear to produce the result that
was promised or intended and so maybe
there's another place that we should
look and that was in the Damned material
world right which which which was
supposed to be at least according to
some elements of classic thinking
nothing about the creation of the devil
so but the point I'm making is that you
know it's very difficult to
underestimate the amount of human
motivation that's embedded in the
attempt to alleviate suffering to
eradicate disease to help people live a
healthy a healthy life and well that's
the disease obviously but to live a long
life as well and to make things as
peaceful as possible I mean you can be
cynical about people and you too can
talk about them as motivated by power
and being corrupt in all of those things
and all of those things are true but you
shouldn't throw away the baby with the
bathwater because we have been striving
for a very long time to set things right
and we've done actually not too bad a
job of it for half starving crazy insect
ridden chimpanzees with lifespans of 50
to 70 years so you know we could deserve
a bit of sympathy for our position as
far as I'm concerned so
[Applause]
some other representations this one I
like the one on the left
that's para de perak dice has a walled
garden and that's what paradise means
it's paradise I was which is I don't
remember the language it's a it's a it's
a it's associated with Persian Paradiso
means walled garden and why a walled
garden well it goes back to the chaos
order idea so this is where God puts man
and woman after the creation in a walled
garden
well the wall is culture and order in
the garden is nature and the idea is the
proper human habitat is nature and
culture in balance and swell we like
Gardens well why because well they're
not completely covered with weeds and
mosquitoes and black flies right so
they're civilized a little bit but still
within that civilization nature in its
more benevolent guys is encouraged to
flourish and people find that
rejuvenating and so the idea that
paradise the proper habitat of a human
being is a walled garden is a good one
and it's walled because well you want to
keep things out right I mean raccoons
for example if you want want to keep
those things out man even though it's
impossible and you know you don't you
don't want well there's all sorts of
things you don't want your garden like
snakes walls don't seem to be much use
against them but the idea that paradise
is a walled garden is is a an echo back
to the chaos order idea walls culture
right garden nature so the proper human
habitat is a properly tended garden now
the radical left-leaning anti theist
environmentalists tend to make the case
that the predations of the Western
capitalist system are a consequence of
the injunction that was delivered in
Genesis by God to man to go out and
dominate the earth David Suzuki has
talked a lot about this by the way they
believe that that statement has given
rise to our inappropriate assumption
that we have the right to exert control
over the world and that that's what's
turned us into these terror
predatory monsters sometimes described
as cancers on the face of the earth or
viruses that have inhabited the entire
ecosystem who are doing nothing but one
wandering everywhere and wreaking havoc
as rapidly as we possibly can which is
another perspective on the essential
element of humankind that I find
absolutely deplorable I mean if you look
at the historical record for example
even casually you'll find out that as
early as as late as the late 1800s 1895
thereabouts Thomas Huxley who was Aldous
Huxley's grandfather and a great
defender of Darwin prepared a report for
the British government on ocean
sustainability and his conclusion was
huh fish away guys man there's so many
fish out there the oceans are so
inexhaustible that no matter how hard
humanity tried for for any number of
years the probability that we could do
more than put a dent in what was out
there was zero now Huxley turned out to
be wrong he didn't realize that our
population was going to spike so
dramatically partly because we got a
little bit rich and our children stopped
dying at the rate of like 60% before
they were 1 years old and you know we
actually managed to populate the you
earth with a few people but wasn't
really until 1960 or so that we woke up
to the fact that there were so many of
us that we actually hard to start paying
attention to what we were doing to the
planet and that's like what 50 years ago
well we've just started to develop the
technology or the wherewithal to
understand that the whole world might be
well considered a garden and we need to
live inside the proper balance between
culture and order or culture and and and
chaos before that we were spending all
of our time just trying not to die and
we usually very unsuccessfully so so I
don't agree with that interpretation of
the opening sections of Genesis I don't
believe that it's given human being is
the right to act as super predators on
the planet I think that instead the
proper environment for human beings is
presented quite properly as a garden and
that the role of people and that's
explicitly stated in in the second story
in Adam and Eve was to tend the garden
and that means to make
proper decisions and to make the sure
that everything thrives and flourishes
and and so that it's good for the things
that are living there that aren't just
people but also good for the people too
so fine I think we can we could at least
note that that's a slightly different
take on the story than the than the
ultimately cynical interpretation that's
so commonly put forward today now inside
that wall garden is a couple of trees
and Adam and even some animals and all
of that and unfortunately the tree
happens to have a snake wrapped around
it now that's an interesting thing we're
gonna talk about that a lot and the
snake in both of these representations
is no ordinary snake say it's got a
human head and it's got a human head
there too so whatever that snake is well
let's forget about looking at this from
a religious perspective like if you can
just imagine that you're an
anthropologist and you've never seen
this image before it's like what do you
see or you see walls and you see
something a fairly pleasant enclosure
and then you see a tree and people are
eating from the tree but the tree has
the snake in it that has a human head
and so then you might think well what's
a snake with a human head and then you'd
think well it's half snake and half
human that's hardly revelatory it's just
self evidence so whatever that snake is
isn't just a snake it's snake and human
or it's it's it's its snake and partakes
in whatever human beings are and that's
very important so we'll continue we'll
consider that later and you see the same
thing here and and you see in this
particular version there's the head this
one also has wings and so this is a
winged snake sort of like a dragon and
so it curls on the ground like a reptile
and it's got an aerial aspect or a
spiritual aspect so here it's a snake
which is like the lowest form of
reptilian life say something that crawls
on the ground it's something that's
human and it's something that's
spiritual at the same time and it
inhabits the tree which look a lot like
magic mushrooms by the way and you can
look that up if you want that's quite an
interesting little rabbit hole to wander
down if you're curious about it but but
there's an idea here too is that there
was something in the garden at the
beginning of time that was like a snake
that was like a person that was like
something that was winged it was
something spiritual so it's spiritual
human and reptilian all at the same time
and it's the animating
spirit of the tree okay so keep that in
mind thus the heavens and the earth were
finished this is in relationship to
Genesis 1 and all the host of them and
on the seventh day God ended his work
which he had made and he rested on the
seventh day from all his work which he
had made and God blessed the seventh day
and sanctified it because that in it he
had rested from all his work which God
created and made that's wisdom in that
one - I think the idea of the Sabbath
you know because one of the things I've
worked with a lot of people who were
hyper conscientious and thing about
hyper conscientious people is that
they'll just work til they die and
that's actually not very productive
because then they're dead and they can't
work and so what you have to do with
hyper conscientious people is you have
to say well I know you'd rather do
nothing but work and maybe you're just
as guilty as you can possibly be when
you're not working but let's figure out
what you're up to and what you're up to
you know probability is the attempt to
be productive in the least problematic
longest sustaining possible manner and
that might mean you have to take a rest
and so one of the things I used to work
with lawyers with people who had risen
to the top of large law firms and they
were hyper productive types they're
often you know trying to hit their
impossible quota for yearly hours and
and burning themselves to a frazzle as a
consequence and one of the things that
we used to do was they couldn't work
fewer hours because that a day that just
didn't work but what we did was we have
them take more time off you know like a
four-day weekend every two months or
something that was plotted out into the
future and then we track their billable
hours which is their degree of
productivity it would actually increase
so that was so cool because you could
take hard-working people and you could
say look you know take a break
why well because you'll be more
productive if you take a break no that
couldn't possibly be like I should just
work flat out all the time it's like
let's test that out you take a break now
on that it's like well what happened was
their productivity would increase often
by 10 percent so there's a there's
wisdom here too which is okay and this
is alludes to the Adam and Eve story
near the end you you're self conscious
you discover the future you have to work
well then the question is how much
should you work and one answer is you
better bloody well work all the time
because no matter how much work you do
you're not solving your problems they're
coming along man and you can stack up
all the money you want you can stack up
the wealth you want it is not going to
protect you in the final analysis so you
better be hitting the ground running and
you better run flat-out all the time or
what happens if you do that well then
you die that's not a good solution so
maybe you should rest and so how does
that rest get instantiated well it's not
easy to tell but one way to do it let's
say conceptually is to say look even God
had to rest one day a week and so you
don't have to be so presumptuous to
assume that if God had to rest one day a
week that maybe you know you are allowed
to work non-stop without a break at all
you know and I think our culture has
slipped into that in quite a dangerous
way because everything is open all the
time and I mean I'm I'm find that just
as convenient as the rest of you but you
know it's so strange to talk to modern
people because one of the things they
always tell you we say well how are you
and what do they always say they don't
say good they don't say bad they say
busy it's like yeah well okay this is
where Genesis 2 starts and we finally
got there these are the generations of
the heavens and of the earth when they
were created in the day that the Lord
God made the earth and the heavens and
every plant of the field before it was
in the earth and every herb of the field
before it grew for the Lord God had not
caused it to rain upon the earth and
there was not a man to till the ground
but there went up a mist from the earth
and watered the whole face of the ground
and the Lord God formed man of the dust
of the ground and breathed into his
nostrils the breath of life and man
became a living soul well you know
there's some archaic thinking and there
the breath is life right that's psyche
that's spirit that's inspiration that's
respiration that's that's all associates
its numa like pneumatic tyre it's its
breath and the reason that people
associated life with breath well that's
not so foolish you know I mean you're
breathing man and something you do all
the time and when you die you start
breathing and so the idea that there's
something integral to life about
breathing is a perfectly reasonable
supposition it actually happens to be
very true and though then to associate
the act of creation with the act of
first of all inspiration and respiration
and and the breathing of life into
something that was inanimate is is
well what do you expect for a
one-sentence description it's not a bad
one sentence description you know so and
the Lord God planted a garden eastward
in Eden and Eden means well watered
place and that's particularly relevant I
suppose if you're a desert dweller right
because the issue there is can you get
enough water to make things grow and so
the the walled garden which is paradise
is also Eden which is a well watered
place and water has the element of chaos
we already saw that in relationship to
Genesis 1 where the underlying chaos was
often assimilated symbolically to water
and so the idea too is that a certain
amount of chaos has to be brought into
the order in order for it to be fruitful
and you can see that in the form of of
allowing in the water and out of the
ground made the Lord God to grow every
tree that is pleasant to the sight and
good for food The Tree of Life also in
the midst of the garden and the tree of
the knowledge of good and evil so two
trees are marked out among the rest one
is the Tree of Life and one is the tree
of the knowledge of good and evil now
you know you know when you read
something like that if you're thinking
about it that you're in a metaphorical
space now we've got to be careful about
metaphors because you know I could say
and did that the chaos order idea is a
metaphor but then I also said oh wait a
second it's a metaphor but it's also
what your brain is adapted to and so you
know let's just not be pushing the idea
that it's merely a metaphor too hard and
then and the same thing is is here is
happening here these are metaphors the
Tree of Life and the tree of the
knowledge of good and evil but that
doesn't exactly mean that they're mere
metaphors because sometimes as I
mentioned before and as if you have a
set of things and you abstract out from
them a common element you can make a
strong case that the common element is
more real than the set of things from
which you extracted it that's the whole
utility the abstraction why would you
bother with it otherwise if you can't
take a set of things and say look
there's something in common across this
set of things that's more important than
the differences between them then you
wouldn't bother abstracting at all and
so the tree of life and the tree of the
knowledge of good and evil are
abstractions now one of the questions is
this is a tough one man I've been tried
tried to figure out for a long time why
a fruit and something you eat would be
associated with the
transformations of psychology because
that's basically what happens in the
Adam and Eve story why would it be
something that you eat now Eric Newman
who was one of young students had
written a fair bit about this and got a
fair ways with it he said well you know
we do have noted we've noticed forever
that the act of eating especially if
you're hungry especially if you're
starving produces a rapid spiritual
transformation right I mean some of you
this is worth knowing you probably have
a Crabby partner or child because
everyone does and one thing you might
try is that if they get erratic during
the day and you know get all volatile
about nothing at all it's give them
something to eat really I'll tell you
man leave this solves for I do this with
my clinical clients all the time it's
like they say well I fly off the handle
at the littlest things it's like okay
yeah just try this for a week when
you're crabby and unreasonable eat a
piece of cheese or eat a peanut butter
sandwich eat something that's high
protein high fat and then just wait ten
minutes and see if you're sane and
you'll find out that you're saying after
you eat so often that you just can't
believe how crazy or when you're hungry
look here's it's really absolutely
bloody remarkable so I'm telling you try
this
it'll-it'll especially if you don't eat
breakfast this will change your life and
so here's a practical bit of information
for you to for all of you
antisocial types who are going to end up
in prison so if you're in prison and you
want to go on parole okay so you have to
go in front of the judge and tell them
why you're not gonna do it again
so here's the deer's the deal it doesn't
really matter what you did and it
doesn't really matter what you promise
what matters is whether you see the
judge before lunch or after lunch
because if you see the judge after lunch
the probability that you'll get parole
is 60% higher yeah right that is just
like so never have an argument with your
partner when you're hungry or when
they're hungry especially if you want
something for it from them it's like
here's the sandwich they'll eat it then
they'll be happy then you can manipulate
them before before that man no
[Applause]
so you know it's it's not that
unreasonable to think that there's a
spirit in food because food rejuvenates
and it just doesn't rejuvenate you
physically it rejuvenates you
spiritually and then of course there's
the other things that we consume that
aren't exactly like food that have a
walloping spiritual impact like alcohol
let's say which is a spirit and is
regarded are nice yes right I mean it's
the god of the vine and the god of the
Varden possesses you and makes you act
all the fun ways that alcohol makes you
out you know the fun ways that you
regret the next day and so there's the
spiritual element of that too and and
then but there's something even deeper
that I think is so cool that's
associated with food and information
because the story of Adam and Eve
represents the fruit as producing a
psychological transformation and so the
tree of the knowledge of good and evil
is an abstraction across trees and it's
trying to say here's something that's
common across trees it's it's a fruit
that's common across trees it's
something like that and so the fruit
across it's common across trees is
something you might call food fair
enough that's a generalization but
here's something that's even more cool
the food that's stable across the entire
domain of food isn't food it's
information it's information and we use
the same bloody circuits in our brain to
forage for information that squirrels
used to forage for food that animals
used to forage for food it's the same
circuit and why is that because we
figured out that knowing where things is
knowing where the food is is more
important than having the food and so so
knowing where the food is as a form of
mass of food information is a form of
meta food and once you and well that's
why we're information foragers and so
once you grasp that and and that ideas
is embedded into the story of Adam and
Eve so whatever it is that they ingest
is a form of meta food it's it's it's
information and and you know we'll trade
food for information right so if you're
stuck on the edge of the highway and you
know you're you're hoods up and you're
you're going places thing is turned into
a pile of junk that you don't understand
and somebody pulls beside you pulls up
beside you and they're a mechanic and
they point to something to say well just
put that way
there you'll immediately give them a
sandwich right or you would offer them
something in return you know what I mean
because they've provided you with
information that has value and it has
value because it actually provides you
with energy because information provides
you with energy because otherwise why
would we bother with it and so food
provides energy but so does information
and so there's the there's the idea of
food that you abstract from everything
you can eat but then there's the idea of
what you could abstract from all sources
of food and the answer to that would be
information and the trees that are being
referred to in Adam and Eve are these
method trees they're not ordinary trees
just like paradise is no ordinary place
just like Adam and Eve are no ordinary
people and just like the logos that God
is using at the beginning of time is no
ordinary conception and and these aren't
they're not metaphors there more than
metaphors there I think of them as hyper
realities is something like that
is there more real than what you see
there more real than the reality that
presents itself to you and lots of
things are like that
right numbers are like that we wouldn't
think or abstract if there weren't
things that were more real than what we
can see so what's most real well that's
partly what we're trying to figure out
and out of the ground made the Lord God
to grow every tree that is pleasant to
this sight and good for food The Tree of
Life also in the midst of the garden and
the tree of knowledge of good and evil
and a river went out of Eden to water
the garden and from thence it was parted
and became into foreheads that's
produced a tremendous amount of
speculation now you know the Garden of
Eden is also the holy city that's
another way of thinking about or it's
Jerusalem right or it's the ideal state
which could be the ideal City or it
could be an ideal state of being or
could be the ideal psyche here it's all
of those things stacked up at the same
time right and this is a Mandela and
this is the Mandela form that people
what would you call hypothesized that
constituted the structure of paradise he
knows it's got this cross form that's
Eden itself and there's the the center
of Eden and there's the rivers those are
rivers not snakes those are the rivers
that go out of it and they're turned
into these Mandela images that are
representative of what Jung described as
the self which would be the center
element of being that he associated of
conscious being that he associated with
divinity I would say but also with the
idea of the holy city and so I'm just
showing you that to show you what we're
the imagination has taken ideas of
paradise so the name of the first river
is Kaizen that is which compasses the
whole land of havilah weather is gold
and the gold of that land is good
there's bdellium and the onyx stone and
the name of the second river is gijn
the same is it that compasseth the whole
land of ethiopia and the name of the
third river is headache L or Hideko I
don't know that is it which goes towards
the east of Assyria and the fourth River
is the Euphrates so there's this strange
intermingling there of geography with
mythical geography right which you see
happen fairly frequently in the books
and the Lord God took the man and put
him in the Garden of Eden to dress it
and keep it okay so that's that's a good
that's a good command that's what you're
supposed to do is take care of the damn
thing it was a lot of work to make right
took a whole week and the Lord God
commanded the man saying of every tree
of the garden thou mayest freely eat but
of the tree of the knowledge of good and
evil thou shalt not eat of it for in the
day that thou eatest thereof thou shalt
surely die well there's a sponge of
questions there that people have been
puzzling they're puzzling over for a
long time gaudy he's tricky character in
the story of Adam and Eve it's like okay
if we can't eat the damn thing well why
put in the garden to begin with that
would be one question and you made us
and then you told us not to eat this
knowing perfectly well that the first
thing we were going to do is eat it
because people are of exactly that type
which is that if you say to them with
their insatiable curiosity this is all
fine and nice but over here is something
you should never look at and then you
leave the room it's like everybody is
over there trying to figure out what the
hell that thing is instantly right
because we're curious curious curious
curious creatures and so you have to
wonder exactly what God was up to here
and there's Gnostic speculation that the
original God this one was not really a
very good God he was kind of an
unconscious evil God and that he wanted
his creation to be unconscious and so
forbade them from developing
consciousness and that it was a higher
God who and maybe in the form of the
serpent who tempted human beings towards
consciousness and you know that that
idea got scrubbed out of classic
Christianity pretty early although
there's something that's interesting
about it and
remnants of it in different forms that
stayed inside the story like the idea
that the fall was you know a terrible
tragedy but on the other hand it was the
precondition for the greatest event in
history which was the birth of Christ
and the redemption of mankind and so
it's complicated let's put it that way
god only knows what God was up to you
but you know this is a good example of
that ambivalence and to me again that
it's an indication of the sophistication
of the people who put these stories
together I also consider this somewhat
miraculous because you know if you're
just a simple propagandist of sorts you
wouldn't leave this sort of complexity
in the text you just get rid of that
because if you're a propagandist
everything is supposed to make sense
along the ideological plane and here God
is supposed to be good it's like well we
better get there to that line because
something's up with it and it isn't
obvious what it is but that isn't what
people did and to me that indicates that
that they were doing two things as they
were trying not to be too careless with
the traditions that they were handed
they they were they were touching them
at their peril they were very careful
with them and also that they were
actually trying to understand what was
going on because why otherwise keep this
why not just simplify it or maybe just
to tribute this to the devil that would
be easier and having God do it but and
the Lord God said it is not good that
man should be alone I will make help
need for him and out of the ground the
Lord God formed every beast of the field
at every fall of the air and brought
them unto Adam to see what he would call
them and whatsoever Adam called every
living creature that was the name
thereof and Adam gave names to all the
cattle in the fall of cattle means
animals basically and to the fall of the
air and every beast of the field but for
Adam there was not found to help meet
for him okay well a couple of things
there speculations number one it's like
why does God care what Adam calls the
animals and the answer to that seems to
be that it's associated again with the
magic of speech right so that we know
according to this story that human
beings were already made in the image of
God and that God used language in order
to call order forth from chaos and that
human beings were made in that image and
so there's an echo of that here even
though it's from an independent
tradition the echo is the thing isn't
quite real till you name it
and
and that's that's an interesting thing
and we don't exactly know how far that
extends it's certainly the case that
like seem things often exist in a
strange potential form interconnected
form where everything's confusing like a
massive confusion before you put your
finger on it name it what's going on
here you name it it's like it it carves
it out from all that underlying chaos
and makes it into Agrippa belen today
that you can then contend with and you
might say well it was real before you
named it it's like well yes it was real
before you named it the same way things
are there when there's no one there to
perceive them and it isn't obvious how
things are there when you're not there
to perceive them I'll tell you something
bloody weird about perception you can
look this up and John Wheeler John
Leader's a physicist so here's a really
cool thing let's say you go outside at
night and you look up and you see a star
and like so a photon from That star
enters your eye then maybe that photon
has been cruising along for like 30
million years do you know that that
photon would not have been emitted from
that star at that time if your eye
wasn't there at that time to receive it
you think well how in the hell can that
because it happened 20 million years ago
it's like well I don't know how it can
be to tell you the truth but I know that
John Wheeler has done a very good job of
detailing out why that's true and
necessarily true and so a wheeler is
also the physicist who developed the
notion of it from bit and he believes
that the world is best construed as a
the potential of the world is best
construed as a place of information it's
something like latent information and
that what consciousness does is
transform the latent Internet in
information into something like concrete
reality he doesn't mean that
metaphorically and one of the cases that
he makes in that regard is this story
that I just told you is that the photon
couldn't have left from where it was
unless it had a place to go now it's
it's complicated and confusing because
from the perspective of a beam of light
from a photon there is no time and
there's no distance from one point to
another well of course that's completely
impossible to understand too but from
the perspective of a photon the universe
is completely flat perpendicular to the
direction that the photon is traveling
so it's there and here at the same time
for us it's not it's like 20 million
years ago but for the photon it's it's
all here and now so anyways the reason
I'm telling you all that is because the
relationship between consciousness and
reality is by no means straightforward
it is seriously not straightforward and
physicists physicists debate what the
relationship is between consciousness
and reality and they debate about what
the sort of phenomena that I just
described mean and I'm not really
qualified to enter into that debate
because I'm not a physicist but I do
know and I've read it fair a bit of
wheeler as about as much of it as I can
understand and I do at least know that
that's what he claimed and I also know
that that claim is it is not that's a
claim that's taken seriously among
physicists of the caliber of the
physicists who can understand wheeler so
that's pretty interesting so anyways
there is emphasis again on this
importance of naming in order to make
things real you know and sometimes
people won't name things just so they
don't become real so you know if you're
if you have a relationship which
undoubtedly you do and it has problems
which undoubtedly it does you bloody
well know that lots of times there's
something under the carpet that no one
wants to name and everybody's thinking
well as long as we don't name it it's
not really there and in some sense it
really isn't there because you can act
as if it's not there and get away with
it at least for short periods of time as
soon as you name that thing it's like
you give it form and it's there and no
one can ignore it and that's annoying
because then you have to deal with it or
Noor or face the consequences but the
reason I'm telling you that is because
we have a an intuition even that we can
have things not exist by not naming them
you name it and it comes forward with
staggering clarity and it's not as if
naming it is the only thing that gives
it reality but it is something like it
sharpens it and brings it into focus and
gives it borders and barriers and
borders and boundaries and so anyways
guards interested enough and what Adam
has to say that he has him named all the
animals and that sort of makes them into
animals no there's more to the
Linguistics story than that so social
psychologists Roger Brown was one of
them studied this really interesting
phenomena which is associated with the
relationship between perception and
action you know how a kid will call a
particular animal a cat well the word
path is very short like the word dog and
it turns out that you know you could
think that we could perceive cats as
multicellular organisms like we could
see the self we could see the molecules
we could see the atoms we could see or
we could see the ecosystem that the cat
is part of but we don't or maybe the
broader mammalian classification that
it's part of we could perceive that as
the unit of perception but we don't we
perceive things at the level of cat and
you can tell the perceptual level that
people naturally perceive that which
doesn't seem to be socio-culturally
determined to any great degree by the
way because the words are often short
and easily remembered and early learned
and so there's this level of analysis
out of all the possible levels of
analysis that the world does exist at we
perceive it at a certain level of
analysis and that level of analysis
seems to have something to do with the
world's functional utility for us at
that level and the perception at that
level and the naming at that level gives
things a reality at that level you know
because the thing about things is that
they're not easily separable from other
things they tangled together in all
sorts of strange ways and yet when we
cast our eye and and and use our
language to orient ourselves in the
world we cut things up into discrete
discriminable objects that we can then
utilize and there's something about that
that makes them real in a way that
they're interconnected potential the
interconnected potential that they were
before that that it's not it's not real
in the same way at least I think it's
even less real I think that's a right
way of thinking about it even though
it's not completely unreal but it's an
echo atoms a little God at that point a
little God the farther and God's already
done the groundwork but Adam has to come
along and says say well that's a cat
it's like poof whatever that is is now a
cat and that's a dog and that's a sheep
and you know it gives them it gives them
something like pragmatic form but for
Adam there was not found to help meet
for him
and the Lord God caused a deep sleep to
fall upon Adam and he slept and he and
God took one of his ribs and closed up
the flesh instead thereof and the rib
which the Lord God had taken from man
made he a woman and brought her unto the
man
and Adam said this is now bone of my
bones and flesh of my flesh she shall be
called woman because she was taken out
of man therefore shall a man leave his
father and his mother and shall cleave
unto his wife and they shall be one
flesh that's a walloping statement to
put in there at the end of those three
sentences
I mean therefore comes as somewhat of a
surprise but there's an injunction there
well it's a good injunction man you know
tell you people who don't do that they
have a hell of a time in their marriage
and so this is a good thing to know if
you are married or if you're planning to
get married is like you know we have
very strong orientation towards our
parents and for good reason it's like
the injunction here is that secondary as
soon as you're married and failure to do
that makes your marriage collapse and
then you deserve it to collapse - as far
as I'm concerned because it's a
reflection of your pathological
immaturity and your unwillingness to
extract yourself from the you know
telling like grip of parents who are a
little bit too much on the interfering
side but the injunction there's there's
a deep injunction here it's very
complicated so one of the ideas is that
the original Adam wasn't a man like like
a separate man it was more like a
hermaphroditic being and in that him
Alfred etic being there was a kind of
undifferentiated perfection and then
that was split into male and female and
then that part of the goal of human
beings is to reunite that as the
singular unity that reestablishes the
initial perfection and that's actually
the goal of marriage from a spiritual
perspective and you could read about
that if you read young because he wrote
quite a bit about that so lovely it's
such a good idea so I had these friends
that went to Sweden to get married they
were northern they were from northern
Alberta but his heritage their both
their Heritage's were sweet Swedish and
in this ceremony they did this cool
thing yes they they were being married
and they had to hold a candle up between
them right while they were being married
and you think well okay what's the
candle what's the source of light it's a
source of illumination right it's a
source of enlightenment
it's the candle that you put on
Christmas trees in in Europe so it's the
light that emerges in the darkness in
the depth of winter it's a symbol of
life in in darkness it's the reemergence
of the Sun that the
at the darkest coldest time of the year
which is also associated symbolically
with the REIT with the birth of Christ
for all sorts of complicated reasons and
so the candles all that and then the
next question is why do you hold it
above you and the answer is because
what's above you is what you're below -
so it's single simplify something
transcendent and so why do you both hold
on to it well cuz you're both supposed
to hold on to the light right and you're
supposed to be subordinate to the light
and so you ask well who's in charge in a
marriage well the light that's the idea
so you come together as one thing you no
longer two things
it isn't what's good for you and it's
not what's good for your wife it's
what's good for the marriage and the
marriage is about the combined being
which is the reassembly of the original
Hema firma burma frenetic hermaphroditic
being at the beginning of time
that's the idea and that's all packed
into like these four sentences and you
know there's been well all of these
sentences have tremendous history of
interpretation associated with them
right it's just endless and endless and
endless and that's one of the lines and
so it's also an antidote to the idea
that women taken out of man which is
obviously the reverse of the biological
process by the way meets women in some
sense subordinate to man that is not
built into this text I don't see that at
all is built into the text and there's
something else that's associated with it
too and there's an idea that you know in
in in sleeping beauty you know sleeping
beauty goes to sleep and the reason she
goes to sleep is because you have to
remember what happens is she has parents
who are quite old and so they're pretty
desperate to have a child like so many
people are now and they only have one
child like so many people do now and
they don't anything it happened to this
child because like hey it's a miracle
and there's only one of them and so and
she's the princess and so it's like
we're not letting anything around her so
they have a big christening party right
and they invite everybody but they don't
invite Maleficent and Maleficent is the
terrible mother she's nature
she's like the thing that goes bump in
the night she's the devil herself so to
speak she's everything that you don't
want your child to encounter so the king
and queen saying well we just want to
invite her to the Krishna
it's like good luck with that that's an
eatable story right the eatable mother
is the mother who devours her child by
refusing by over protecting him or her
so that instead of being strengthened by
an encounter with the terrible world
they're weakened by too much protection
and then when they're let out into the
world they cannot live and that's the
story of Sleeping Beauty and that's what
the king and queen do and they apologize
to the two Maleficent when she first
shows up and say well you know they have
a bunch of half-witted excuses why they
don't invite her
we forgot it's like I don't think so you
know you don't forget something like
that and she kind of makes that point
it's right the whole horror of life you
don't forget about that when you have a
child that's for sure you might wish
that it would stay at bay but you do not
forget about it the question is do you
invite it to the party and the answer is
it bloody well depends how unconscious
you want your child to be and if you
want your child to be unconscious well
then you have the added advantage that
maybe they won't leave home and so you
can take advantage of them for the rest
of your sad life instead of going off to
find something to do for yourself well
and then of course you can take revenge
on them if they do have any any what
would you call impetus towards courage
that you sacrificed yourself thirty
years ago and want to stamp out as soon
as you see it developing your child
that's another thing that would be quite
pleasant and so that's what happens in
Sleeping Beauty yeah well none of this
is pleasant and nothing that happens in
that story is pleasant so Sleeping
Beauty she's naive as hell they put her
out in the forest and have it raised by
these three like goody two-shoes fairies
that are also completely devoid of any
real potency and power right there's no
nothing Maleficent about them and then
the first idiot Prince that wanders by
she falls in love with so badly that she
has post-traumatic stress disorder
really rides off on his horse right
that's what happens and then she then
she goes into the castle and she's all
freaked out because she met the love of
her life for like five minutes for God's
sake and you know that's when the
spinning wheel that's the Wheel of Fate
pops up and she pricks her finger right
they try to get rid of all the spinning
wheels they try to get rid of all the
wheels of fate with her pointed end but
she finds it poke pricks or fingers and
finger falls down unconscious well she
wants to be unconscious and no bloody
wonder she was protected her whole life
she's so damn naive that her first love
affair just about kills her she wants to
go to sleep
never wake up and so that's exactly what
happens and then she has to wait for the
Prince to come and rescue her well you
think how sexist can you get that story
well seriously because that's that's the
way that that would be read and in the
modern world it's like she doesn't need
a prince to rescue her that's why I
Disney made frozen that absolutely
appalling piece of rubbish so you know
you can say you can say well the
princess doesn't need a prince to rescue
her but you know that's a boneheaded way
of looking at the story because the
prince isn't just a man who's coming to
rescue the woman and believe me he's got
his own problems right he's got a whole
goddamn dragon he has to contend with
but but the prince also represents the
woman's own consciousness the
consciousness is presented very
frequently in stories as symbolically
masculine as it is with the logos idea
and the idea is that without without
that forward going courageous
consciousness a woman herself will drift
into unconsciousness and terror and so
you can read it as well the woman who's
sleeping needs a man to wake her up and
of course just like a man needs a woman
to wake him up it's the same damn thing
that's the dragon fight in Sleeping
Beauty but it's also the case that if
she's only unconscious all she can do is
lay there and sleep like the sleep of
the naive and Damned she has to wake and
wake herself up and and and bring her
own consciousness her own masculine
consciousness into the forefront so that
she can survive in the world and of
course women are trying to do that like
mad but that's partly what's represented
in the story like that and that's partly
what's implicit in this idea is that
unless the woman is taken out of man so
to speak then she isn't a human being
she's just a creature and that's partly
what's embedded in this story so you
don't want to read it as a patriarchal
you don't want to read anything that way
so really it's it really it's yeah I
won't bother with that but really we can
do better than that man therefore shall
a man leave his father and his mother
and shall cleave unto his wife and they
shall be one flesh it's like yeah thing
another thing about marriage this is
really worth knowing too is that I read
this in part from reading young it's
like what do you do when you get married
that's easy
see you take someone who's just as
useless and horrible as you are and then
you shackle yourself to them and then
you say we're not running away no matter
what happens yeah well that that's
perfect because then you don't get to
run away and the thing is is like if you
can run away you can't tell each other
the truth because if you tell someone
the truth about you and they don't run
away they weren't listening and so if
you don't have someone around they can't
run away then you can't tell them the
truth and so that's part of the purpose
of the marriage it's like okay okay I'll
bet on you you bet on me it's a losing
bet we both know that but given our
current circumstances were unlikely to
find anyone better that's for sure you
know there's two things that come off of
that one is you know people are waiting
around to find mr. or mrs. right it's
like here's something to think about man
to put yourself on your feet right if
you went to a party and you found mr.
right and he looked at you and didn't
run away screaming that would indicate
that he wasn't mr. right at all right
it's like the old Nietzsche and joke if
someone loves you that should
immediately disenchant you with them
right right or it's the Woody Allen joke
I never belonged to a club that would
take me as a member so so that said
that's an interesting that's a very
interesting thing to think about and so
you're going to shackle yourself to
someone who's just as imperfect as you
are and then the issue is you you you
might be in a situation where you can
actually negotiate because you might
think well there's some things about you
that aren't going so right and there's
some things about me that aren't going
so right and we're bloody well stuck
with the consequences for the next 50
years so we could we can either
straighten this out or we can suffer
through it for the next five decades and
you know people are of the sort that
without that degree of seriousness those
problems will not be solved you'll leave
things unnamed because there's always an
out it's like and it's the same thing
when you're living together with someone
you know that people who live together
before they're married are more likely
to get divorced not less likely and the
reason for that is what exactly are you
saying to one another when you live with
each other just think about it well
for now you're better than anything else
I can trick but I'd like to reserve the
right to trade you in conveniently if
someone bitter happens to stumble into
me
well how could how could someone not be
insulted to their core by an offer like
that now they're willing to play along
with it because they're gonna do the
same thing with you now well that's
exactly and it's like yeah yeah I know
you're not gonna commit to me so that
means you don't value me or our
relationship above everything else but
as long as I get to escape if I need to
then I'm willing to put up with that
it's like that's a hell of a thing I
mean you might think how stupid is it to
shackle yourself to someone it's like
it's stupid man there's no doubt about
that but compared to the alternatives
it's pretty damn good because without
that shackling there are things you will
never ever learn because you'll avoid
them you can always leave and if you can
leave then you don't have to tell each
other the truth it's as simple as that
because you can just leave and then you
don't have anyone you can tell the truth
to so there's some representations of
the idea of the original it's not this
isn't all Adam this is this is an old
Chinese symbol I think it's Fuxi and new
although I think I have the
pronunciation wrong but it's really cool
see it's see the snakes down here
they're kind of like DNA symbol which I
find very interesting and so that's the
original cosmic serpent that's there to
the potential out of which that emerges
and then that's the differentiation of
that into male and female and so that's
like the predatory unknown that's one
way of thinking about it that's the most
fundamental conception of mankind is
something like that is the predatory
unknown and then the bifurcation of that
into the two fundamental cognitive
elements of human perception masculine
and female and you see the same thing
here this is Chinese this is Egyptian
also extraordinarily old it's the it's
the great serpent that underlies
everything
forgetting itself into Isis queen of the
underworld and Osiris king of the king
of king of King Pharaoh king of order
you see the same thing in the old
alchemical symbol I love this one does
it looks quite a lot like the little
thing that Harry Potter chases around eh
yeah and that's not accidental by the
way because the seeker is the same the
thing that chases this and the seeker
that chases this and catches it wins and
that's a really old idea and how they
held JK Rowling knew that I cannot
figure out because that is a very very
archaic symbol arcane symbol on Google
it's called the rau
to chaos and the only reference to the
round chaos that I can find on Google is
on my web page and so I have no idea how
Rowling came up with that I mean I know
she looked at a lot of old texts but the
idea that if you play the meta game and
you catch this you win all the games is
exactly right and that and that's the
motif for what's the name of that
Quidditch yeah so there's the potential
that's like the potential out of which
God made the world at the beginning of
time and what emerges out of that is
some kind of that's the dragon you know
that in the dragon fight that's partly
the serpent that's in the Garden of Eden
and then that's the manifestation of
masculine and feminine out of that
potential predatory unknown masculine
and feminine it's like a single it's
like a single representation of the
evolutionary history of human cognitive
consciousness so cool and that's also an
image of the ideal it's the union of Sun
and Moon and it's this hyper creature
hermaphroditic that's also the Adam and
Eve that existed at the beginning of
time before the fall and it's the
purpose of marriage all of that as a
sacrament all of that in these images
it's just absolutely unbelievable what
images can pack into them and there's
some more classical representations of
Eve being extracted from Adam and this
is a cool line and they were both naked
the man and his wife and we're not
ashamed
well that see someone who wrote that
would only write that like that if they
were surprised that they weren't ashamed
because why would you point it out
otherwise and so there's this intimation
that of two things number one is there
was a point at time in time when human
beings were naked and they weren't
ashamed of it and there is a point of
time which is now where they're naked
and they are ashamed of it and then the
question is well what's the association
with nakedness and shame and that's
often given a sexual connotation in in
classic interpretations of the Adam and
Eve story because of its association
with nudity I presume but I think it's a
lot more complicated than that so you
think I know I would notice my daughter
she probably won't be very happy that
I'm revealing this in this lecture but
my daughter was never really concerned
about nudity when she was a little kid
is all the same to her one way or
another but my son by the time he was
three man that kid was private he his
his bedroom door was shut the bathroom
door was shut it was like get the hell
out of here and that seemed to just
happen of its own accord and you know we
had two children and one was like that
and the other one wasn't I didn't think
we had much to do with it at all but it
was really fascinating to watch that
emerge in him and you know that that
sense of of self-consciousness does seem
to emerge in children somewhere around
the age of three and you know that's
generally also when we start thinking
that maybe having your baby wander
around naked on a beach isn't exactly
the best idea there's there's there's
something like that it's the nudity and
children is generally okay under some
circumstances in public display we seem
to think of that as merely as acceptable
why I don't know why it stops being
acceptable well that has something to do
with sexuality obviously but it's a very
complicated phenomena but you know that
whole nudity thing is then is a very
complicated thing I mean first of all
people are kind of strange because we're
hairless roughly you know compared to
most animals and we don't know why that
is some people think it's because we
lost our heroine we were wandering
around in the day in the desert running
around in Africa because we're really
really good runners we can run down
animals say like a human being in good
shape can run a horse to death in a week
we can really run man and a lot of our
ancestors the Kalahari Bushmen still do
this
they just run an animal for like it
until it dies and that Bushman doesn't
die I mean they also sometimes shoot
them with poison arrows but they can
just run them till they die so we have
tremendous endurance and you and you
have to be able to get rid of a lot of
heat if you're gonna run around in the
desert so we don't have much hair that's
one explanation and Buckminster Fuller
had an interesting explanation which was
he thinks that at some point during our
evolution we spend a lot of time near
the water and so we're like fish Apes
something like that well you know we
like to be on the beach and there's lots
of food there and we like to swim and
we're really good at swimming for
terrestrial creatures and we cry salt
tears like some seagoing creatures - and
women have a layer of subcutaneous fat
like some seagoing creatures - and we
have kind of our feet are which are very
odd things are kind of good for flapping
in the water although we can also walk
with them and so he thought that maybe
that adaptation was to - water exists
like seals and so forth like we kind of
went back to the ocean but not quite and
so but anyways the evolution of that
hairlessness is an interesting thing but
it certainly does make us exposed to the
world in a way that animals that have a
covering of fur aren't and then we're
upright which is very strange because
most animals aren't there on all fours
and so they're very vulnerable parts are
protected and not exposed to view and
then of course when you're standing up
nude your your your visit let's call it
your psychophysiological quality is on
painful display right and people
complain about that all the time you
know if you look at the feminist tack
for example on beauty the idea that
women have eating disorders is directly
attributed to the presence of too many
beautiful women on the cover of
magazines something like that even
though women buy those magazines and
they're attracted to the band their mood
goes up when they purchase them and if
the if the stimulus was negative the
women would avoid the magazines and not
buy them so as a theory it's a very very
bad one but it's still the case that you
know it's still the case that standards
of beauty shame people and that's for
sure and everyone because if you're not
ugly now man you're gonna be at some
point in your life so that's kind of a
rough thing to contend with right it's
it's a rough thing to to know that that
there's an ideal that you could be and
maybe even once were that you're not
going to be for long or knit orden or
never were and it's really an appalling
issue because I think it's harder on
women because women are judged by men
more for their but for their youth and
fertility that's how it turns out from
the evolutionary point of view men are
judged more on their socioeconomic
status by women it's harsh both ways but
so anyways it's you know it's a terrible
thing to to carry the knowledge with you
that you're exposed to the most serious
possible evaluation of the quality of
your being that you can possibly be
exposed to all the time and that that's
further amplified if you're without
clothing and so part of clothing is
protection but a tremendous amount of it
is merely stopping other people from
evaluating you too harshly all the time
it just gets in the way so and
this store this this story makes the
case that at some point we weren't like
that well animals aren't like that so it
seems perfectly plausible that at some
point we weren't like that but at some
point that changed and they were both
naked the man and his wife and we're not
ashamed how the serpent was more subtle
than any beast of the field which the
Lord God had made and he said unto the
woman yea hath God said you shall not
eat of every tree of the garden I like
this this is remember who did the edging
who is it DeRay yeah DeRay exactly he
dorade did etchings for Paradise Lost
that are absolutely remarkable and this
is Satan and this is the snake here and
of course in in in the Genesis story
Satan is weirdly associated with the
snake and I'll tell you that's a that's
a that's a tough one to sort out because
in the story of Adam and Eve there's no
indication whatsoever that the serpent
who tempts Eve is also Satan the author
of all evil and how in the world those
two stories got tangled together well I
think I figured that out and I'm gonna
tell you that tonight but it took a very
long time to figure it out and it's
absolutely it's so bloody brilliant I
just can't believe that people figured
it out it's so it's so unbelievably
spectacularly brilliant and that's a
that's a an intimation of that idea
right that there's a kinship between
these two things so anyways the serpents
more subtle than any beast of the field
subtle is an interesting word this is
from the oxford english dictionary
so because will amplify the word a bit
this is what you do in Union dream
interpretation for example is to kind of
look at the connotations of the concepts
that are associated with the dream
subtle of a person or animal and action
behavior crafty cunning sly treacherous
so it's something that sort of sneaks
along right it's not something that you
really pick up on that easily of a look
or glance sly furtive surreptitious of a
person skillful expert clever of a work
of art mechanical device cleverly made
or designed ingenious well that's I
think that's all fairly all those terms
so far are fairly well attributed to
snakes I mean they are very cool things
and and they are very well designed and
they're quite remarkable and they're
also very subtle
on the nature of or involving careful
discrimination of fine points or fine
points difficult to understand and
abstruse of a person the mind or
intellectual activity intellectual
activity characterized by wisdom or
perceptiveness discriminating discerning
and truth that's interesting because
Milton's Satan is also the intellect and
you know you see that very often you
know it's so often the bad guys an evil
scientist right and there's something
about and you see the same thing in the
Lion King with scar
I mean scar is an intellect and arrogant
deceitful intellect he's there's nothing
stupid about scar he's not wise but he's
the he's the evil voice that's always
whispering in the Kings ear and that's
associated with the pride of the
intellect and the Catholics had warned
people warned humanity about the pride
of the intellect for centuries that's
partly what produced somewhat of this
Gizem between Catholicism and science
although that's much overstated if you
look at the historical record the idea
was that the intellect has its own
particular it's a remarkable faculty
let's say it's the highest angel in
God's heavenly kingdom that's the way
that Milton portrayed it but it's also
the thing that can go most terribly
wrong because intellect the intellect
can become arrogant about its own
existence and accomplishments and it can
fall in love with its own products and
that's what happens when your
ideological II possessed because you end
up with a Dogma like say a human
constructed Dogma in Solzhenitsyn's
words that possesses you completely of
which you believe is 100% right right so
it eradicate the necessity for anything
transcendent and so that's the subtle
element of the intellect that's
associated symbolically with the snake
in the garden of paradise of a feeling
scent sensation acute and keen involving
distinctions that are finer delicate
especially to such an extent as to be
difficult to discern or analyze also
almost imperceptible and elusive having
little thickness or breadth thin fine
subdial matter now historical rarefied
matter barely there at all and the woman
said unto the serpent we may eat of the
fruit of the trees of the garden but of
the fruit of the tree which is in the
midst of the garden
office goddess said he shall not eat of
it neither shall you touch it lest you
die and the serpent said to the woman ye
shall not surely die for God doth know
in the day that you eat thereof then
your eyes shall be opened and you shall
be as God's knowing good and evil
sneaky subtle it's a nice story a the
first thing is the for instant the
instant implication is well you can't
trust God so that's pretty sneaky and
the next is well he's trying to he's
trying to pull a fast one on you and the
next one is he's trying to do that
because he's jealous and he doesn't want
you to know things that he knows because
that wouldn't be so good and he's lying
to you anyways because you're not going
to die and if you eat it
contrary to what you've been informed
then all that's going to happen is your
eyes will be open and you'll be like
God's knowing good and evil that sounds
pretty damn good so you know and I I
mean Eve what does she know you know
it's no wonder she's susceptible to such
blandishments and it's quite interesting
too because Adam and Eve God tells Adam
and Eve not to eat the damn fruit but
they never promise not to write so they
haven't promised they've just been told
to and well should they be obedient
well how obedient do you want your
children to be you want them to be
obedient enough so they don't get hurt
but disobedient enough so that they go
out in the world and do something
courageous and they break some rules
that they learn some things and so you
know it's it's it's a very paradoxical
story anyways the serpent ones that wins
this round man and so Eve pays attention
to the snake so again we have the same
set of images right we have Adam and we
have Eve we have this tree and we have
this strange serpent that's a
dragon-like form they're a sphinx like
form that's associated with the tree the
snakes eternally associated with the
tree well the snake was eternally
associated with the tree we spent god
only knows how many tens of millions of
years as tree dwelling primates and the
primary or one of our primary predators
we had three primary predators snakes
birds cats and so the snake has been
associated with the tree for a very very
long time and the lesson the snake tells
people is you bloody well better wake up
or something you don't like we'll get
you and who's going to be more
susceptible susceptible to paying
attention to the snake and that's going
to be Eve and the reason for that is Eve
has offspring and there's nothing
tastier to a snake than a child and so
Eve had every reason to be
self-conscious and neurotic and women
are more self-conscious and neurotic
than men by quite a substantial amount
and that's true cross culturally and in
the emerges at puberty and part of the
reason is as far as we can tell is that
women are more sexually vulnerable
they're also smaller so that's a problem
if you're engaged in any physical
alteration but most importantly I think
is that why would you ever assume that a
human females nervous system is adapted
to her or her well-being why wouldn't
you assume instead that her nervous
system is adapted to the female infant
dyad because if it isn't then the
infant's die and so you might think well
women are way more susceptible to
depression and anxiety than men are
that's a hell of a burden to bear and
that's also true cross culturally by the
way and it also kicks in at puberty and
the biggest differences are in
Scandinavia for those of you who think
it's socio-cultural which it isn't
so but there's reasons for it you know
and it's also at puberty when men and
men and women start to become sexually
dimorphic in terms of size and men are
way more powerful in their upper bodies
it's incomparably more powerful and so
that makes them a lot more dangerous and
human human primary human defense
mechanism is punching like with
kangaroos for because there's some other
animals that punch chimps can punch too
but human beings it's a punch and most
of the force and that is upper body and
shoulder and so a woman's no match for a
man in a fight so she has every reason
to be nervous
especially when you add that to that her
additional sexual vulnerability and the
fact that she has to take care of
extraordinarily dependent infants were
extremely fragile for a very long period
of time and so she had every and women
are more self-conscious than men the
empirical literature on that is clear
it's associated with trait neuroticism
because self-consciousness is actually
an unpleasant emotion who wants to be
self-conscious if I'm self-conscious on
the stage talking to you then all of a
sudden I can't even talk to you all I'm
doing is thinking about me and all the
things that are wrong with me and I fall
inside myself
it's like self-consciousness although
it's a great gift let's
is nothing Pleasant its associated
primarily with anxiety so we've had
every reason to pay attention to the
snake that's for sure I think I read
this week that among I can't remember
which tribes minute where it was
unfortunately although I did put a
footnote in my new book about this these
were jungle dwelling tribal people five
percent of the adults had been attacked
by a python and a substantial number of
children had been killed by them so
snake predation was no joke it shaped
our evolutionary past and still is no
joke in many places and so we're a tuned
to snakes and the thing is as lynn has
bel pointed out an anthropologist we are
really good at detecting the camouflage
patterns of snakes especially in the
lower half of our visual field and
there's evidence that part of the reason
that human beings have such acute vision
which means that our eyes open let's say
is because we were we co-evolved with
snakes and we learned how to see them
and then the price we paid for seeing
was that our brain grew because you need
a lot of brain to be able to see and the
consequence of our brain growing is one
day we woke up and discovered the future
and the future is where all the snakes
might live instead of where they live
right now so there's that the same thing
and the same so interesting again these
images you see in this one you have the
specter of death in the tree with the
snake and the fruit now fruit is
interesting - I already made the case
that there's a tight linkage between
what you eat and information right a
conceptual link as well as a practical
link but it's also the case that we can
see colors and the question is why and
the answer is because we evolved to see
ripe fruit so in the story of Adam and
Eve human beings are given vision by the
snake and the fruit and that turns out
to be correct
so isn't that something and then you
think what role do women play in
relationship to men well first they make
them self conscious let's not ever
forget about that because I would say
the primary role that women have in
relationship to man is to make them
self-conscious and men don't precisely
like that there's nothing that will make
a man more self-conscious than being
rejected and why because why is he
rejected well obviously
their nature in the guise of that
particular woman has said you're not so
bad for a friend but there's no reason
that your genetic material should
propagate itself into the future right
well it's not like men are exactly happy
about being me but made self-conscious
by women right it's a major source of
continual tension between men and women
and it's no wonder but it's also the
case and this is something really cool
and interesting to know you know we
divulged dyv divulged dye whatever
that's it diverged we diverged from the
common ancestor between us and
chimpanzees about six million years ago
here's why at least in part chimpanzee
females are non discriminant mater's
they'll mate with any male when they go
into heat which human females don't when
they go into heat then any male is
allowed access now the dominant males
chase the subordinate males away and so
the dominant males are more likely to
leave offspring but it's not because of
a female choice it's not the case with
human beings human females engage in
hypergamy and hypergamy is the ten this
is also true cross culturally and it's
also quite it's just as extensive in
Scandinavia not quite there's a bit of
attenuation but not much women mate
across and up dominance hierarchies
man-made across and down okay when that
has to be the case cuz it obviously it
has to work that way if one goes up the
other has to go down the socio-economic
status of a woman is almost determined
almost zero of her attractiveness
towards a man whereas the socio-economic
status of a man is a major determinant
of his attractiveness towards a woman
and it isn't as wealth either because
that's been tested it's his capacity to
generate and be productive and to share
because that beats the hell out of
wealth wealth can disappear right but
the capacity to be productive and share
that's that's a much more important
element and why not be chosen on the
basis of that especially because women
have to have infants and infants make
the women dependent and the woman is
just looking logically rationally and
from an evolutionary perspective for
someone who's useful enough to give a
tool and a hat so women make intense
demands on men and it's
wonder but the thing is is that because
women engaged in hypergamy at least in
part we diverged quite rapidly from
chimpanzees because the selection
pressure that women placed on men
developed the entire species now there's
two things that happened as far as I
could tell the men competed for
competence let's say so the male
hierarchy is a mechanism that pushes the
best man to the top virtually by
definition and then that's that's the
effect of that is multiplied by the fact
that women who are a Pergamus appeal
from the top and so that the males who
are the most competent are much more
likely to leave offspring and that
seemed to be what drove our cortical
expansion for example which happened
very very rapidly over the course of
evolutionary time so and when the woman
saw that the tree was good for food and
that it was pleasant to the eyes and a
tree to be desired to make one wise she
took of the fruit thereof and did eat
and gave also unto her husband with her
and he did eat
oh yes and women share food that's a
very strange thing because most
creatures don't do that right most
animals don't share food like if you if
you're a wolf and you bring down
something in a hunt you eat your fill
the dominant creatures eat their fill
and then if there's some left over the
subordinates get to eat too but that
doesn't how human beings work we share
food now you can imagine how that
evolved because lots of female creatures
share food with their offspring ok you
don't need much of a twist in that from
an evolutionary perspective till you
start to share food not only with your
offspring se but with your mate and
that's another way that you entice a
mate it's like we're gonna be better
together then alone well that's the
offering of the fruit well what's the
self-conscious part well here's part of
the bargain you know I'm gonna wake you
up and partly I'm gonna wake you up
because you need to be woken up because
I have this infant that needs some damn
care and so you bloody well better be
awake and part of the bargain is all
offer you something I'll offer you some
food and in response we're gonna make a
team and that's the deal well that's the
human deal and that's why we're more or
less monogamous by why we more or less
pair bond and why something
approximating marriage is a human
Universal it's cross-cultural now you
can find exceptions but who the hell
cares
the vast really man who cares
the VIP you look at the vast pattern the
vast pattern well in the price we pay
for having large brains is that we're
very dependent and it takes a long time
for us to get programmed and because of
that we need relatively stable family
bonding and that's basically what we've
evolved and you know you don't get that
without making men self-conscious
because male creatures
why not impregnate and run I mean why
the hell not and that's something to
really no kidding like that's the thing
to think about it is not why man
abandoned their children that's the
mystery
it's why any men ever stick with them
that's the mystery because you just have
to look at the animal kingdom and like
the simplest and easiest thing is always
the most likely thing to occur so it's
the exception that long-term commitment
that needs explanation she took of the
fruit thereof and did eat and gave also
unto her husband with her and he did eat
and the eyes of both of them were opened
implying that before that they were
closed and they knew they were naked and
they sewed fig leaves together and made
themselves aprons so that's so
interesting so their eyes are open which
indicates that they weren't to begin
with so whatever God created to begin
with was kind of blind indeed but not
blind in some strange way cuz they
weren't obviously wandering around in
the garden bumping into trees it was
some sort of metaphysical blindness
that's been removed by whatever has just
happened and whatever's just happened
also made them realize that they were
naked okay so what sort of eye opening
is that well what does it mean to
realize that you're naked it means to
realize that you're vulnerable that's
what people discovered it's like oh we
can be hurt so you're a zebra in a herd
of zebras and there's a bunch of lions
around there laying on the grass you
don't care those are laying down lions
laying down lions are no problem
it's standing up hunting Lions that are
the problem you're not smart enough to
figure out that laying down lines turn
into standing up hunting lions so you're
not like building a fort to keep the
Lions out you're just mindlessly eating
grass
you're not very awake but that's not
what happens to human beings is they
wake up and they think we're vulnerable
permanently it's never going away right
it's the it's the recognition of that
eternal vulnerability and what happens
the first thing they do is clothe
themselves
well what happens when you're naked when
you need protection from the world well
obviously look you're all wearing
clothes you know why
well we've been doing that for a very
very long period of time it's tens of
thousands of years at minimum in fact
you can track more or less when clothing
developed because you can do DNA testing
of the kind of lice that cling to
clothes rather than hair and so we have
a pretty good idea of when clothing
emerged and of different types as well
so that's quite cool but the point is
they're naked and they think that's not
so good we're vulnerable so their eyes
were open enough so they become
self-conscious and they recognize their
own vulnerability and the first thing
they do is the first step of culture is
to protect themselves with something
from the world and you protect yourself
from the world and from the prying eyes
of other people this is the book by Lynn
Isabel why we see so well from the
temptation of Eve to the venomous murder
of the Mighty Thor the serpent appears
throughout time and culture as a figure
of mischief and mystery misery the
worldwide prominence of snakes in
religion myth and for Clure underscores
our deep connection to the serpent but
why when so few of us have first-hand
experience mm-hmm the surprising answer
this book suggests lies in the singular
effect of snakes on primate evolution
predation pressure from snakes Lynn
Isabel tells us is ultimately
responsible for the superior vision and
large brains of primates and for a
critical aspect of human evolution that
was tested recently psychologists have
known for a long time that people are
can learn fear to snakes but they
discovered in primates recently a set of
neurons Paulding or neural neurons which
are specialized that's an old old
perceptual systems reveal
neurobiological evidence of past
selection for rapid detections of snakes
so that's from 2013 so the snake
definitely woke us up color vision as an
adaptation to fruit eating in primates
it's not by accident that women make
themselves look like ripe fruit in order
to be attractive to men right and that's
also not socio-cultural in origin
so and they heard the voice of the Lord
God walking in the garden in the cool of
the day and Adam and his wife hid
themselves from the presence of the Lord
God amongst the trees of the garden
that's interesting
so what's the implication prior to being
woken up prior to recognizing nakedness
and vulnerability there was no reason
for God for men and women to hide from
God now are they hiding from God well
they're naked they're vulnerable
okay so think about this think about
this it's like imagine that you have the
capacity to live truthfully and
courageously and forthrightly just
imagine that and then imagine why you
might not do that and then imagine well
how about fear and shame how would that
work
well let's say that the idea of living
forthrightly and truthfully and
courageously is analogous given what we
already know about these stories to
walking with God in the garden well what
stops people from doing that what stops
people from hiding well it's their own
rage the recognition of their own
inadequacy they look at themselves and
they think how in the world is a
creature such as I supposed to live
properly in this world with everything
that's wrong with me
and so what are you hide from well you
you go home you sit on your bed for five
minutes and ask yourself what have you
hidden from in your life man you'll have
books of knowledge reveal themselves to
you in your imagination right say well
why are you hiding well it's no bloody
wonder you're hiding it's no wonder that
people hide that's the thing that's so
terrifying about this story we woke up
and we thought oh my god look at this
place like this is seriously there's
some serious trouble here and we're in
some serious trouble and we're not what
we could be and so we hide and that's
what the story says people woke up they
became self-conscious they recognized
their own vulnerability and that made
them made them hide from manifesting
their divine destiny it's like yeah
that's exactly right and the Lord go
there I love this part of the story and
that's so funny and the Lord God called
and we could use a little humor at this
point and the Lord God called unto Adam
and said unto Him where art thou and
Adam said I heard thy voice in the
garden and I was afraid because I was
naked so in case there was any doubt
about that that's why and I hid myself
and God said who told you that you were
naked
did you eat of the tree where have I
commanded you that you should not eat
and this is where Adam shows himself in
all his post-fall heroic glory and the
man said the woman whom thou gave us to
be with me she gave me of the tree and I
did eat so that's that pert man that's
such that it's so you know again there's
a modern feminist interpretation of the
story of Adam and Eve that makes the
claim that Eve was portrayed as the
universal bad guy of humanity for
disobeying God and eating the Apple
it's like fair enough you know looks
like she slipped up and then she tempted
her husband and you know that makes her
even worse although he's was foolish
enough to immediately eat so it just
means she was a little more courageous
than him then got there first
but it's Adam who comes across as really
one sad creature in this story as far as
I'm concerned welcome buddy manages in
one sentence it's like first of all it
wasn't him it was the woman and second
even blames God so it wasn't just the
woman it was it was that woman and you
gave her to me and she gave me of the
tree and I did eat it's like so hey
Adams all innocent except now he's not
only is he naked and disobedient and
cowardly and ashamed
he's also snively backbiting think he
rats her out like the sick and he gets
the opportunity and then he blames God
it's like and that's exactly right
that's exactly right man you go online
and you read you read the commentary
that men write about women when they're
resentful and bitter about women you
read it it's so interesting it's like
it's not me it's those [__] okay
that's right it's not me it's them and
not only that what a bloody world this
is in which they exist it's exactly the
same thing it's exactly the same thing
and it is
absolutely pathetic all right and the
Lord God said unto the woman what is
this that thou has done and the woman
said the serpent beguiled me and I did
eat well he she has a bloody excuse
first of all it's a snake I mean those
things there was we already found out
there's subtle and second it turns out
that the damn snake is Satan himself you
know and he's rather treacherous so the
fact that she got tangled up in his mess
let's say is well problematic but it
it's a hell of a lot better excuse that
Adam has and the Lord God says unto the
serpent because thou has done that done
this thou art cursed above all cattle
and above every beast of the field upon
thy belly shalt thou go and dust shalt
thou eat all the days of my life
and snakes by the way are lizards that
lost their legs just so you know and I
will put enmity between thee and the
woman and between thy seed and her seed
it shall bruise thy head and thou shalt
bruise his heel I love these pictures
they're so smart and again strip the
religious context from them and just
look at them for a second what do you
see you see the eternal mother holding
her infant away from the snake see it
down there right crocodile snake
everything predatory that's been after
us for like 60 million years the reason
we're here is because of that that's why
it's a sacred image now this one I like
even better see down there there's
something like the moon and then there's
this reptile down there that Eve is
standing on this is really old and I
showed you this before but I think it's
so cool she's coming out of this thing
that's like a hole in the sky you know
because it indicates the eternal re
presence of this figure it's something
like that the eternal recurrence of this
figure it's an archetype but then the
the the potential out of which she is
emerging these are all musical
instruments back here and so what the
artist is representing is the great
powder
complexity of being and the emergence of
the protective mother from that
background protecting the infant
eternally against predation it's like
how can that not be a holy image if it
isn't a holy image if you don't think
it's a holy image then there isn't
something wrong with the image there's
something wrong with the perceiver unto
the woman he said well God's just
outlining the consequences of this right
now it's like okay well now you've gone
and done it you've woken up this is
what's going to happen I'll greatly
multiply thy sorrow and thy conception
in sorrow thou shalt bring forth
children and thy desire shall be to thy
husband and he shall rule over thee
doesn't say he should says he will and
why in sorrow shalt thou bring forth
children well when you develop a brain
that big so that you can see it's not
that easy to give birth anymore and then
you produce something that's dependent
beyond belief and that's one of the
things that you would say dooms you to
precisely this so that's Eve's
punishment for waking up and Adam
because thou has hearkened unto the
voice of thy wife and has eaten of the
tree of which I commanded thee saying
thou shalt not eat it cursed is the
ground for thy sake in sorrow shalt thou
eat of it in all the days of thy life
what's that
it's the invention of work thorns and
thistles shall it bring forth to thee
and thou shalt eat the herb of the field
it's the invention of work what do
people do that animals don't work what
does work mean means you sacrifice the
present for the future and why do you do
that because you know you're vulnerable
because you're awake and so from here on
in from this point there's no return to
unconscious paradise I don't care how
many problems you've solved so that
today is okay you've got a lot of
problems coming up and they'll bloody
matter how much you work you're never
going to work enough to solve them and
so all you're gonna do from here on in
is be terrified of the future and that's
the price of waking up and that's the
end of paradise and that's the beginning
of history and that's how that story
goes in this sweat of thy face shalt
thou eat bread till thou return unto the
ground for out of it
though taken for dust thou art and unto
dust thou shalt return and Adam called
his wife's name Eve because she was the
mother of all living
unto Adam also and unto his wife did the
Lord God make coats of skin and clothed
them that's William Blake by the way and
the Lord God said Behold the man has
become as one of us to know good and
evil and now lest he put forth his hand
and take also of the tree of life and
eat and live forever I'll go over this
again next week
therefore the galore God sent him from
the forth forth from the Garden of Eden
to till the ground from whence he was
taken so he drove out the man and he
placed at the east of the Garden of Eden
cherubims and a flaming sword which
turned every way to keep the way of the
Tree of Life
one more thing and then we'll stop so I
thought why in the world so Adam and Eve
are tempted by the snake they eat the
fruit they wake up they realize they're
naked they realize that they're
vulnerable they realize the future they
realize they're gonna die they realized
that they have to work it accounts for
difficulty and conception and the fall
of humankind from unconscious paradise
okay that makes sense what about the
knowledge of good and evil what in the
world does that mean the Mesopotamians
believed that human beings were made out
of the blood of King knew who was the
worst monster that time out who was the
goddess of chaos could imagine and then
produce so their idea was that whatever
was about humanity there was something
deeply deeply deeply demonically flawed
so that's their conception and the some
of that same milieu that these stories
emerge so what is opening your eyes and
realizing your vulnerability have to do
with the knowledge of good and evil
really I thought about that I really
thought about that I got to tell you I
thought about that for like 20 years
because I knew there was something there
that I could not put together and at the
same time I was I was reading things I'm
gonna tell you something truly awful and
so if you need a trigger warning you're
you're getting one and and believe me I
do not give trigger warnings lately so
I'm gonna tell you something you will
never forget so this is what unit 731
used to do in China and China said
Japanese unit during the first Second
World War right as far as I can tell
they did the most horrific things that
were done to anyone during World War two
and that's really something so this is
what they did they took their prisoners
and they would put them in a position so
that their arms would freeze solid and
then they would take them outside and
pour hot water over their arms and then
they would repeat that till the flesh
came off the bones and they were doing
that to investigate the treatment of
frostbite for soldiers now you can look
up unit 731 if you want to have
nightmares
so that's a unit 731 that's human-beings
someone thought that up and then people
did it
that's knowledge of good and evil here's
the here's the key man you know you're
vulnerable no other animal knows that
you know what hurts you because you're
vulnerable now that you know what hurts
you you can figure out what hurts
someone else and as soon as you know
what hurts someone else and you can use
that you have the knowledge of good and
evil well it's a pretty good trick that
the snake pulled because it doesn't look
like it's exactly the sort of thing that
we might have wanted if we would have
known what the consequence was but as
soon as a human being is self conscious
and aware of his own nakedness then he
has the capacity for evil and that is
that's introduced into the world right
at that point and here's the rest of
this story so there's the snake right
and you're some tree dwelling primate
and the snake eats you and that sucks so
let's like let's watch out for the damn
snakes and then you think well wait a
minute your brain grows and you think
wait a minute well there's not just a
snake there's where snakes live why
don't we just get the hell out of the
tree and go hunt down the snakes and get
rid of them so those are sort of like
potential snakes and so the snake
becomes a potential snake and it's the
same circuit that you're using to do
this thinking and then you get rid of
the damn snakes
it's like st. Patrick chases the motive
are no more snakes
everything's paradise it's like no no no
that's not that's not how it works no
well now you've got the human snakes
you're a tribe you've got tribal enemies
you got to defend yourself against the
human snakes right so maybe your empire
expands and you get rid of all the human
snakes and then what happens well they
start to grow develop inside it's like
you get rid of all the external enemies
and you make a big city and all of a
sudden there's enemies that pop up
inside because the snake isn't just the
snake in the garden and the snake isn't
just the possible snake and the snake
isn't just the snake that's your enemy
the snake is your friend right because
your friend can betray you and then it's
even worse than that because you can
betray you
and so even if you get rid of all the
outside snakes you've got an inside
snake and god only knows what it's up to
and that's why the bloody Christians
associated the snake in the Garden of
Eden with Satan it's unbelievably
brilliant because you got to think
what's the enemy well it's the snake
fair enough
but you know that's good if you're a
tree dwelling primate but if you're a
sophisticated human being you know with
six million years of additional
evolution and you're really trying to
solve the problem of what it is that's
the great enemy of mankind well it's the
human propensity for evil right as such
well that's the figure of Satan that's
what that figure means just like there's
a logos that's the truth that speaks
order out of chaos at the beginning of
time there's an antithetical spirit the
hostile brother that's Cain to Abel
which we'll talk to talk about next week
that's doing exactly the opposite that's
motivated by absolutely nothing but
malevolence and the willingness to
destroy and it has every reason for
doing so and that's what's revealed in
the next story and Cain and Abel in one
paragraph the first glimmerings of that
outside of the strange insistence by the
Christian mystics let's say on the
identity between the snake in the Garden
of Eden and the author of all evil
himself
[Applause]
okay so we only have 15 minutes today I
I wanted to finish that so apologies for
going over a little longer all right hi
dr. Peterson over the last couple weeks
and further back you talked a lot about
consciousness and the importance of it
but I was hoping to get your opinion on
an issue of consciousness that has often
seen Christianity among other groups and
politics kind of clash so I'm hoping to
get your views on the consciousness or
lack thereof of a human fetus and how
that's impacted you views an abortion
whatever they are and any thank you
thank you okay so the first question is
do I have an answer for that that's a
good enough answer to actually reveal no
I don't but I'll I can flail about a
little bit around it
abortion is clearly wrong I don't think
anybody debates that you wouldn't
recommend that someone that you love
have one okay now having clarified that
that mere statement doesn't eliminate
the complexity of the situation the
first question is is should everything
wrong be illegal that's a tough question
everything that's wrong isn't illegal
then there's the additional complication
of the difference let's say in gravity
regarding the problem in relationship to
men and women and we don't know how to
deal with that having said that I would
say that it's actually the wrong
question there's a something Leonard
Cohen said once he said that in a
massacre there's no decent place to
stand
and what he meant by that was sometimes
you're where there is no good decision
left no matter what you do it's wrong so
then the question is how did you get
there well let's say you're in a
position where you are inclined to seek
an abortion the question is how did you
get there
now we have a lot to straighten out
about sexual relationships between men
and women in the modern world they're
bent and warped and demented out of
shape one of the things I see with young
people for example is that they will
engage in sexual acts with one another
that they would not talk about with one
another
I mean couples will do that for that
matter like married couples will do that
but they're married that's that's a
different story
it seems to me that if you are willing
to engage in a sexual act with someone
with whom you would not discuss that act
you probably put the cart before the
horse so the discussion regarding the
legality of abortion is nested inside a
larger discussion about the morality of
abortion and that's disconnected inside
a larger discussion about the proper
place of sexuality and human behavior
and to me that's the level at which the
problem needs to be addressed now I
don't have the answer to that you know
because the old answer was get married
that was a good answer and it's an
answer that people should still listen
to but we'll put that aside momentarily
I had a client at one point who was I
don't know she was probably I'm not I'm
gonna disguise her in a variety of
different ways she was 27 2008 come from
a relatively conservative background
quite a timid fearful person and also
not very well not sophisticated in
relationship to relationships and she'd
never had sex well there's a bunch of
things she'd never done well the answer
from me to her wasn't continue to be
timid about everything because that
wasn't working out for her she needed to
go have some adventures
now sexual adventures like other
adventures are dangerous and so you have
to be very careful when you encourage
people to go out and have adventures but
but but too much timidity and caution
also constitutes a pathway to perdition
let's say you can't just say to people
in the modern world well you know sex
till you're married unless you're gonna
get married when you're very young and
perhaps you should I don't know about
that
but I don't think that we're mature
enough as a culture to have a serious
discussion about sexual propriety
especially in the aftermath of the birth
control pill and we seriously need to do
that and we have it and so I think the
eternal debate about abortion horrible
as it is is a it's the surface
manifestation of a much deeper problem
now I talked a little bit today about
the utility of marriage like the
spiritual utility of marriage and that's
something that I think we're so
immaturely cynical as a culture like we
don't we're not wise enough to look at
an institution like marriage and to
really think about what it means and
what it signifies it signifies a place
that people could tie the ropes of their
lives together so that they're stronger
it signifies a place where people can
tell the truth to one another it
signifies a place where sexuality can
properly be integrated into life that's
no easy that's no easy task it's a place
where children at least in principle can
be put first and foremost as they should
be once they exist and so there's a much
broader discussion that has to happen I
think before any concentration on the
legality of abortion is liable to get
anywhere at all that's what it looks
like to me so that's the best I can do
with that question
hi dr. Peterson earlier you showed a
picture of [__] seein nua yeah right uh
and and Osiris and in your maps of
meaning like yes you also explained that
cultures around the world have these
twin snakes there yeah they're
everywhere man yeah and so you mentioned
that you believe this is a
representation of DNA you would bring
that up to Jesus what is it with you
guys tonight huh yeah well yeah no I
wouldn't say I believe that I have my
suspicions that that might be it yeah
because believe is too strong a word but
those representations are everywhere and
read this book this is a good one
oh man now I have to remember the book
it's by an anthropologist who went down
to the Amazon jungle and experimented
intensively with ayahuasca I think it's
called the cosmic serpent I think that's
the name of the book you could read that
there's another one called breaking open
the head which is also pretty damn
interesting and there's something to
those books I mean the cosmic serpent
kind of goes off on a bit of a tangent I
would say although breaking open the
head is it's better better it seems to
stay more constrained and tight but
there's we don't know the limits of our
perception and especially under certain
conditions and I think people have had
intimations of DNA as the cosmic serpent
for ever so yeah but that's a like
that's way out on the frontiers of my
knowledge right like I'm guessing in a
dreamlike way when I'm making statements
like that so some some dreams and
interpretations that we could have
perceived as it is right well yes we did
we didn't objectively but I'm not so
sure we didn't subjectively but and
means very strange that these that these
double helixes exist in so many places
and that they're often utilized as
healing symbols with the snake so
anyways like I said that's what do you
call that
I'm it's not hypothesizing it's one
thing worse than that speculating those
are speculations I'm I'm operating at
the edge of my understanding but our
perceptions can are very mutable and
they can we can see things under some
conditions that you wouldn't think that
anybody could see so okay yep
so I have a thought while you're talking
about sort of getting to the end of the
talk about the snake and in the Apple
and so on so is what you're saying is
the moment that that that Adam and Eve
eat the Apple they become nervous or
whatever so that's awareness of their
own vulnerability so then like you said
it's also awareness of their own
capacity to do harm so it's like when
they were eating the Apple then that's
them their immediate sort of nervous
reaction is is because they ate the
Apple and they kind of became evil in
that moment or something like that
well they woke up and because they they
woke up and realized how they could be
hurt how they could and would be hurt
over the over the over the upcoming
overtime it's the same as the discovery
of the discovery of your own nakedness
and the discovery of time are very very
similar phenomena I mean sure as soon as
you know how you can be hurt well you
know if you have to just consult your
evil fantasies it's like what'll really
hurt him oh yeah that would work it's
like how do you know that well you just
think about it what would happen if that
happened to me
that would hurt oh yeah that'll work
it'll hurt him or her and you know you
probably think that way twice a week or
maybe twice a day Jesus every time you
have an argument with someone all you
have to do is look at the back of your
mind a little bit you don't want to
that's for sure but if you do you'll see
these sorts of thought process is
generating constantly it's like you know
in a back-and-forth discussion
particularly with people you love it's
like you're always looking for a place
to put the knife in
so then it seems really similar to me or
seems like they're kind of discovering
the kind of like Union shadow within
themselves so that that is the moment
where it got introduced into the human
spirit sure one of the things about the
shadow is that it's also when you
integrate that that's what makes you a
substantial person right no it's like it
seems to me that on one hand well it's
it seems like this tragedy that Satan
the most evil the father of evil
whatever has introduced into people but
it also seems like without that shadow
that people are kind of insubstantial so
yeah well duh right right I mean that
like I said that there's been a
multitude of interpretations emerge as a
consequence of that story what was God
up to was was God in fact evil the
initial God like why would he create a
snake why would he put it in the garden
why would there be these trees what the
hell is going on with the whole Satan
thing you know it's very very
problematic well we'll talk about it
more and this again is let's call it
speculation well if you want to make
something strong you test it and maybe
if you want to make something ultimately
strong you test it ultimately and I
think that there's an aspect of being
that has that element is that human
beings are tested ultimately it's partly
because we know good and good and evil
now and so that's the landscape in which
we exist so you could say the landscape
is across its chaos and order and it's
good and evil and we're stuck in the
middle between those two things it's a
very common theme by the way in
videogames exactly that chaos order good
evil it's that it's the basic plot of
endless video games and that's perhaps
because it's the basic plot those are
the things we have to contend with well
I had a vision once I shouldn't tell you
this but I will anyways I had a vision
once that that I went to heaven and I
was put in a in a Roman amphitheater
with Satan just like Thor encountering
the Hulk right that's coming up in that
new Avengers movie and so it was
a shark because I thought there was a
hell of a thing to happen in heaven and
so I had this battle and I won and at
the end I came up to God and said like
you know what's with the whole Roman
amphitheater thing there it seemed like
it over the top to me said why would you
put me in a ring with some one thing
like that and he said because I knew you
could win and you know I don't know what
to make of that one thing I should teach
you should make of it as I shouldn't
tell you but whatever but you know
there's something there's something to
that in my estimation it's like do you
protect the people you love or do you
try to make them strong so you think
it's that it's not that we have like
Satan to thank for making us substantial
it's that God gave us Satan in order to
make us substantial
well I'd hesitate to say that because
you know it's it's so cut and dried but
I would say that there's a that's a
strong underlying theme in the biblical
narrative yes now it's certainly not the
only scene it's not the only
interpretation by any stretch of the
imagination but there is something there
and there's something there you know at
the end we didn't talk about this God
puts up this flaming sword and these
cherubim to keep you away from the tree
of life it's like it's seem if paradise
and immortality are the promised land
and what's with the whole flaming angel
and sword thing we could have just had
the damn fruit five thousand years ago
and not bothered with the problem well
it seems to me that there's something
like I don't know what it is
consciousness through tragedy clarity
through suffering maybe something like
that or maybe the perfection that lurks
as a potential in the future is
something that has to be earned rather
than given maybe it has no value without
free choice maybe we have to distinguish
between good and evil now that we have
the capacity to actually apprehend them
maybe that's what life is about
maybe that's the separating of the wheat
from the chaff see that's the idea in
Revelation right because when Christ
comes back in the book of Revelation he
divides the Damned from the saved and
the same
the people who lived in logos roughly
speaking and and the Damned or those who
don't and so there's this idea that
there's this dynamic that underlies
experience that is in fact that's
sorting now I don't know what to make of
that at all but that's the story but
what I can make of that is that I I
can't put a lever underneath the
argument that I just made tonight about
the relationship between the development
of vision the snake the fruit nakedness
time the future work and most
importantly the emergence of evil that
seems to me to be I cannot find a way to
undermine that argument it seems I can't
break it and that's what I'm always
looking for when I'm trying to formulate
ideas I'm trying to look for something
that no matter how hard I try I cannot
break and I can't break that set of
ideas now what the full implication is
of that set of ideas god only knows
right but but I could say also
practically you know one of the things
that I've observed is that lies and
deception destroy people's lives and
when they start telling the truth and
acting it out things get a lot better
gotta stop
[Applause]
you